<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply unto severall treatises pleading for the armes now taken up by subjects in the pretended defence of religion and liberty. By name, unto the reverend and learned divines which pleaded Scripture and reason for defensive arms. The author of the Treatise of monarchy. The author of the Fuller answer his reply. By H. Fern D.D. &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Ferne, H. (Henry), 1602-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E74_9</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859580</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859580</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111670</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111670)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 13:E74[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply unto severall treatises pleading for the armes now taken up by subjects in the pretended defence of religion and liberty. By name, unto the reverend and learned divines which pleaded Scripture and reason for defensive arms. The author of the Treatise of monarchy. The author of the Fuller answer his reply. By H. Fern D.D. &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Ferne, H. (Henry), 1602-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 97, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "A treatise of monarchie" by Philip Hunton, "A fuller answer to a treatise written by Doctor Ferne entituled The resolving of conscience upon this question" by Charles Herle, and "Scripture and reason" by Herbert Palmer.</note>
                  <note>"A London counterfeit issue"--Madan.</note>
                  <note>In this edition title page line 11 ends "arms." and p. 97 begins "I would to God,".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nov: 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hunton, Philip, 1604?-1682. --  Treatise of monarchy --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Herle, Charles, 1598-1659. --  Fuller answer to a treatise written by Doctor Ferne, entituled The resolving of conscience upon this question --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Palmer, Herbert, 1601-1647. --  Scripture and reason --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111670:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> REPLY UNTO SEVERALL TREATISES PLEADING FOR THE Armes now taken up by Subjects <hi>in the pretended defence of</hi> RELIGION AND LIBERTY.</p>
            <p>By name, unto The Reverend and Learned Divines which pleaded <hi>Scripture and Reaſon for defenſive Arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of the <hi>Trea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe of Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of the Fuller Anſwer his <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>H. Fern D. D. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>Leonard Lichfield</hi> Printer to the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niverſity.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:111670:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111670:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of the ſeverall SECTIONS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> The Preface. In which the contradictory Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Adverſaries, <hi>pag. 2, 3.</hi> The Generall Reſolution of the Cauſe, <hi>pag. 4.</hi> Doctrine of Sedition, <hi>pag. 5. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Caſes of Reſiſtance, in regard of times of peace or War; and in regard of Perſons, Private or publique, <hi>pag. 7.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> A defence of Subjects Armes in vaine, ſought by the diſtinction of Monarchy, <hi>pag. 11. 12.</hi> The Governing Power is ſo derived from God upon Him, who is Supream, that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot leſſen or limit it, but onely in the exerciſe, <hi>pag. 13, 14.</hi> Of an Abſolute and Limited Monarch, <hi>pag. 15.</hi> Limitation and Mixture may be by after condeſcent of the Monarch, and onely reach the Exerciſe of the power, <hi>pag. 15. 16 17.</hi> Mixture differs from Derivation of Power to ſubſtitute Officers, <hi>pag. 17. 18.</hi> Of Monarchy by Conqueſt, <hi>pag. 18.</hi> Providence may ſo farre diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſelfe by Conqueſt, that the People Conquered ſhall be bound to conſent and yeeld obedience to the Conqueror, as to a Prince ſet over them by God <hi>pag. 19. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. IIII.</hi> The Conſtitution of this Monarchy; The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Saxon and Norman Conquerours urged, not to prove our Kings abſolute, but to diſprove ſuch an Originall Limitation and Mixture, as the Adverſary phanſyeth in this Monarchy, <hi>pag. 21.</hi> to <hi>28.</hi> Reaſons for ſuch Originall Limitation and Mixture anſwered, <hi>pag. 28. 29.</hi> Proofes for it from His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Grants anſwered, <hi>pag. 30. 31. 32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Of Reſiſtance in relation to an Abſolute Monarchy, <hi>pag. 33. 34. 35.</hi> in relation to a Limited Monarchy, <hi>pa. 36. 37. 38.</hi> Limitation and Mixture in Monarchy doth not infer a power of Reſiſtance in Subjects <hi>pag. 39. 40.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> A Refutation of the moſt conſiderable paſſages of
<pb facs="tcp:111670:3"/>His Reply, that firſt ſtyled himſelfe Author of the <hi>Fuller Anſwer, pag. 43.</hi> to <hi>56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> Places of Scripture out of the Old Teſtament. The Inſtitution of the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> Kingdome, in which the <hi>Jus Regis</hi> implyed a ſecurity from Reſiſtance, <hi>pag. 56, 57, 58, 59.</hi> The Reſcue of <hi>Jonathan, pag. 60. Davids</hi> demeanour towards <hi>Saul</hi> infers not a power of reſiſtance in Subjects, <hi>pag. 61, 62.</hi> His enquiry about the intent of the <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilites, pag. 63.</hi> Something extraordinary in the example of <hi>David, pag. 64 65.</hi> The Prophets never called upon the Elders of the People for this pretended duty of Reſiſtance, <hi>pag. 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> Of Reſiſtance forbidden in the <hi>13.</hi> to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> The place is conſiderable, as it ſpeakes of Government in Gener all, and as it relates to thoſe Times and Governours, <hi>pag. 67</hi> That it is <hi>Powers</hi> in the plurall and in the Abſtract, vainly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and applyed by the <hi>Reverend Divines, pag. 67, 68, 69.</hi> That Subjection is not here reſtrained to Legall Commands in Civill matters only, as they would have it, <hi>pag 69.</hi> to <hi>77.</hi> That Chriſtians might not reſiſt, becauſe Religion then was not eſtabliſhed by Law, and becauſe the Emperours then were Abſolute (as the Author of the <hi>Treat. of Monarchy</hi> would have it) is not the reaſon of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles prohibition, <hi>pag. 77. 78.</hi> Of the abſoluteneſſe of thoſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours before <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> time, and of the Power of the Senate, and of the <hi>Lex Regia, pag. 79,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> Nine Reaſons againſt Power of Reſiſtance in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, drawn from the Conſideration <hi>of the wiſdome of God,</hi> who put his people under Kings without power of Reſiſting them, in the Old and New Teſtament. <hi>pag. 84. Of the Ordinance of God,</hi> that places the Power of the Sword in Him that is ſupreme, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eluded by ſaying, they reſiſt not the Monarch, but miſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed fellow Subjects about Him, <hi>pag. 85. 86. 87. Of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes and inconveniences</hi> that would follow upon ſuch a power of Reſiſtance in Subjects, &amp;c. <hi>pag. 90. 91.</hi> Their reaſons to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary anſwered,—<hi>pag. 93.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>A brief conſideration of the Caſe: That they are far from (what they pret nd) the defence of Religion, Laws, and Liberties, by theſe Armes, and the Reſiſtance now made, <hi>pag. 96. 97.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111670:3"/>
            <head>A REPLY TO SEVERALL TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, pleading for the Arms now taken up by Subjects in the pretended defence of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and and Liberties.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. THE PREFACE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it be enquired, why any Reply at all, or why ſo late? I may ſay, I had determined not to be any more troubleſome, and that there was no juſt cauſe why I ſhould be, were it well weighed what was ſaid on both ſides: but I muſt once again beg leave to ſay ſomething (the Importunity of Adverſaries or the expectation of Friends enforcing it) by way of Anſwer to ſome Books not long ſince iſſued forth.</p>
               <p>There are two eſpecially which have drawn the eyes of many upon them; the one bears this title, <hi>Scripture and Reaſon pleaded for defenſive Armes,</hi> by <hi>Divers Reverend and Learned Divines.</hi> Who by laying their heads together have not found out any more forceable Arguments or ſatisfying Anſwers, then they which went before them; but only ſome newcaſes of Reſiſtance to amuſe the Reader, and new inſtances to inforce former Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111670:4"/>and ſome popular amplifications to ſet off the old An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, thereby making the book ſwell to that bigneſſe it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in.</p>
               <p>The other book bears this Title, <hi>A Treatiſe of Monarchie,</hi> by whom I know not: but ſurely the Author (however he looks not with a ſingle eye upon what I had written, miſconſtruing it many times) doth with much ingenuity diſclaime, and with no leſſe reaſon confute ſeverall Aſſertions of thoſe <hi>Learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> and other Writers of the Party; aſſertions that have very much help't forward this Rebellion: ſuch as theſe, <hi>That the King is</hi> Univerſis minor. <hi>That the People, which make the King, are above Him, by the Rule,</hi> Quicquid efficit tale eſt magis tale. <hi>That the finall judgement of this State is in the two Houſes. That the Chriſtians in the Primitive times might have reſiſted, had they had force.</hi> Theſe and the like he ingenuouſly diſclaimes, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing engaged he ſets up his Reſt upon a groundleſſe fancy of ſuch a mixture and conſtitution of this Monarchie, as muſtinable the Houſes to reſtrain the exorbitancies of the Monarch, by the Arms of the Kingdom: and to induce a beliefe of this, he has prefixed a diſcourſe of <hi>Abſolute, Limited,</hi> and <hi>Mixed</hi> Monarchies, ſo fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as is moſt applyable to his purpoſe.</p>
               <p>He that wrote the <hi>Fuller Anſwer</hi> to my firſt <hi>Treatiſe</hi> had this conceit of <hi>Mixture,</hi> whereby he placed the Houſes in the very <hi>Supremacy</hi> of power, and did thence (as one falſhood being granted doth neceſſarily inferre another) conclude, that the Members of the Houſes were the Kings Subjects <hi>diviſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> taken ſeverally, not <hi>conjunctim,</hi> as they are gathered together in their Houſes; for indeed how could they be His Subjects, and He their ſupreame Head, if they be fundamentally mixed or joyned with Him in the ſupremacie of power? The Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> did ſee that this was repugnant to Law and Reaſon, and therefore doth acknowledge them to be ſubjects <hi>conjunctim,</hi> under the King as their Supreame Head, yet being engaged he holds the ground upon which that abſurd aſſertion is raiſed, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming and endeavouring to prove, that the Mixture is in the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie of power,</hi> pag. 40. How then will he make the King ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, and they His Subjects? for this; he gives the King <hi>Apicem poteſtatis,</hi> the top or Excellency of Power: that is, the King is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111670:4"/>the Crown or top of the head, but the two Houſes muſt be our head too and our Soveraignes, if they be joyned with the King in the very <hi>Supremacy</hi> of power: and ſo the matter will be well mended. Again, The <hi>Full Anſwer,</hi> did from the ſame falſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed mixture inferre, that the finall Reſolution of this States judgement reſided in the two Houſes, when the King refuſeth to diſcharge His truſt for the ſafety of the Kingdom; the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> did ſee and confeſſe, that it plainly overthrowes the Monarchy to place ſuch judgement in the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Yet being ingaged, He gives them power to take the Armes of the Kingdom; but leaſt they ſhould ſeem Authoritatively to Iudge or command in that caſe, they muſt declare and make the appeale to the Community, as if there were no government, and as men are in Conſcience convinced they are bound to give aid and aſſiſtance; ſo he <hi>pag.</hi> 8. 29. and elſewhere. A ready way to confuſion; but of theſe and ſuch like contradictory conceits of the Aſſertors of Reſiſtance more below.</p>
               <p>Of this <hi>Mixture</hi> there was not a little ſpoken in my <hi>Reply</hi> to the <hi>Full Anſwer:</hi> but this Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>Reverend Divin's</hi> take notice only of my firſt Treatiſe, Having therefore made ſome ſhort Animadverſions upon their Bookes as they came to my hand, I ſtill wayted to meet with ſomething directly againſt the <hi>Reply,</hi> but as yet have ſeen no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, beſides two trifling Anſwers; the one a wild diſcourſe by whom written I know not, but by ſuch a flirting phanſy, I am ſure, that he who reads one part, will not caſt away his time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reſt: the other by him that ſtiled himſelfe Author of the <hi>Fuller anſwer,</hi> ſtill like himſelfe; if he can be but witty or faſten a ſeeming contradiction upon his Adverſary it is enough; what he has materiall about the <hi>Mixture</hi> of Government (which is the whole buſineſſe of his book) is more accurately delivered and urged by this Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy;</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is extreamly confident, I ſhall beſtow a Section upon him below, and that is more then he deſerves.</p>
               <p>Therefore what <hi>the Reverend Divines,</hi> or the Author of this <hi>Tract of Monarchy</hi> have drawn from <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify their grounds of Reſiſtance, I ſhall briefly examine, after that I have declared my intent at firſt, and my purpoſe now of proceeding in this Argument.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:111670:5"/>
               <p>It was the intent of that firſt <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of mine, to reſolve the <hi>Conſciences of miſled People, Touching the unlawfulneſſe of Armes now taken up againſt the King:</hi> and becauſe Conſcience, if it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve for them, muſt conclude upon theſe premiſes <hi>(Subjects may take Armes againſt their Soveraigne for defence of Religion and Liberties, apparently in danger of Subverſion. But ſuch is the caſe now,)</hi> and muſt be certain of the truth of both of them, for if either of the premiſes be falſe or doubtfull, Conſcience is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided in the concluſion; therefore the whole Reſolution of the caſe was to this purpoſe, as here it lyes ope to the ſight in theſe two aſſertions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Were the caſe ſo as they ſuppoſe,</hi> that is, <hi>Were the King, as they would have people believe, ſeduced to proceed in a way tending to the ſubverſion of Religion and Liberties, it were not ſafe to bear part in the Reſiſtance of Armes now uſed againſt him, there being no warrant for taking Armes upon ſuch a caſe, but evidence againſt it both from Scripture and Reaſon. So that at the beſt the caſe can be even to them, that plead for reſiſtance, no better indeed then doubtfull, and then Conſcience according to its two Rules</hi> (what is not of Faith is Sin, <hi>and,</hi> in doubtfull caſes, the SAFER WAY is to be choſen) <hi>will tell them they ſhould forbeare and ſuffer, rather then reſiſt, for they may be ſure that is a</hi> SAFE WAY, <hi>were the King indeed what they ſuppoſe him to be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Seeing the caſe is not ſo as they ſuppoſe, nor is it ſo with the King as they would have the People believe, but moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that He is conſtrained to take Armes for the defence of His juſt Rights, and the Protection of His Subjects; Every man may be clearly perſwaded in Conſcience that the Reſiſtance now made is unlawfull and damnable, and that he is bound not only to forbear from reſiſting, but alſo to aſſiſt His Majeſty in ſo juſt a cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The contrary <hi>Reſolution</hi> (which concludes, <hi>That it is Lawfull upon ſuch a caſe ſuppoſed to take Armes: &amp; that the Caſe is now:</hi>) I doubt not to call a <hi>Blaſpheaming of God and the King; Of God,</hi> in charging ſuch an imputation upon his Word, as if it taught Subjects to take Armes for the defence of Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties againſt their naturall Soveraigne: <hi>Of the King,</hi> in caſting ſuch aſperſions upon His Majeſty, as if He were ſeduced to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Religion and Liberties.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:111670:5"/>
               <p>Now although His Majeſties Cauſe be juſtified not ſo much by the falſhood of this their Principle and ground of Reſiſtance <hi>(it is lawfull in ſuch a Caſe to take Armes)</hi> as by the clearneſſe of His innocency, He being farre from what they ſuppoſe or proclaime of him to be: Yet becauſe the very ſeeds of Rebellion are ſowne upon that ground, and there cannot want either made pretences to bring them forth, or Fears and Jealouſies to cheriſh and ripen them; it is needfull to ſhew, that as Rebellion is not a plant of Gods ſowing, ſo neither is that ground a Truth of His Laying.</p>
               <p>The Author of the <hi>Fuller Anſwer,</hi> in his late Reply <hi>Pag</hi> 27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. imputes the beginning of this controverſie <hi>(whether Subjects upon ſuch a Caſe may take Armes?)</hi> to my firſt unhappy and unchallenged Treatiſe (as he calls it) which has expoſed the other party to a neceſſity of a Reply, and cauſed ſo much to be ſaid, eſpecially by Divines, in this ſad and unwelcome ſubject. So he. Theſe men are loath to bee called to account for what they ſay or doe, as if they were the very rule of Juſtice and Truth. They have Preached and Printed this ſeditious doctrine over and over, welneere a twelve month before that unhappy Treatiſe was publiſhed, thereby perſwading the People into Armes, under pretence of defending their endangered Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Liberties; and now they thinke much it ſhould be called in queſtion or be made a Controverſie. It had beene happy for them if they could have carried the matter ſo clearly without being put to a Reply; or if now being put to Anſwer, they could make others the Inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndiaries for the kindling of that fire which they have begun, and fomented with ſeditious doctrines, blowne over all the Kingdome. Surely if the Divines and Lawyers, that are of contrary judgement to them throughout the Kingdome, had in good time declared themſelves herein, it would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a ſeaſonable and happy check to theſe ſeditious principles, and to the unhappy Rebellion that has been raiſed thereon; I for my part thought it concerned mee to examine a doctrine ſo much Preached and publiſhed, and could not think it poſſible that Conſcience ſhould be truly ſatisfied in the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ſecured of the truth of both the <hi>Promiſes,</hi> of which this ſeditious doctrine is the firſt, <hi>That Subjects may take Armes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111670:6"/>againſt their Soveraigne for the defence of Religion and Liberties, when in danger of ſubverſion:</hi> for which as then I could ſee no warrant that Conſcience might reſt on, no more can I now, but doe finde it a Doctrine deſtitute of Scripture and true Reaſon, as will be cleared in the proceſſe of this book. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Upon the examination of places of Scripture, it wil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that Gods People were continually under ſuch Kings, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom they might not reſiſt, and that Gods word as it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords us no precept, ſo nor any juſt example for reſiſtance, but much every way againſt it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Upon the Examination of Reaſon it will appeare, how inconſiſtent ſuch a power of reſiſtance in Subjects is with Government, and that (which ſeemes to be the reaſon of the Wiſdome of God, putting his people under Kings without any power of Reſiſtance) moe inconveniences and miſchiefes would follow upon ſuch a power placed in the People, then if they were left without it.</p>
               <p>I muſt needs ſay it doth at firſt ſight ſeeme unreaſonable, that Subjects ſhould be left without this Remedy, and I confeſſe my owne thoughts (according to that naturall inclination wee all have to Liberty) have been heretofore ready to ſuggeſt as much: till ſeeking warrant for conſcience from Gods word, I could meet with none, but found Reaſon preſently checked with that ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.25. <hi>It is enough for the Diſciple that he be as his Maſter.</hi> It is enough for us now, if by the denial of Reſiſtance and Armes we can be in no worſe condition then our Saviour was, and the Chriſtians of the Primitive times, and Gods people were ever in.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe when I expect the Adverſaries ſhould bring ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Scripture (without which they profeſſe not to attempt any thing of ſuch moment) for commanding or allowing this ſuppoſed Duty of Reſiſtance, I find them altogether failing, and in their Anſwers to places of Scripture, much diſagreeing among themſelves. So that indeed all their faith and perſwaſion here is reſolved into an appearance of Reaſon, raiſed upon <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> grounds or Principles, laid for the framing of a government, and the meanes of reſtraining Tyranny.</p>
               <p>Upon thoſe grounds and Principles, <hi>Buchanan,</hi> and <hi>Iunius
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111670:6"/>Brutus</hi> goe ſo farre as to the Depoſing and taking away of an Exorbitant or Tyrannous Monarch, — The writers of theſe dayes though they will not ſeem to harbour ſuch an intention, and the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchie</hi> doth expreſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it unlawfull; yet do they all agree to uſe what force they can againſt ſuch a Monarch for the ſuppreſſing of his Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie, to give him battell in the field, and make him acceſſary to his own death, if he fall by their hand.</p>
               <p>To cleare the way in the entrance of this Cauſe, I am called by the <hi>Learned Divines,</hi> and the Author of <hi>the treatiſe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie,</hi> in the firſt place to conſider the ſeverall Caſes of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the ſeverall kinds of Governments and Monarchies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>Caſes of Reſiſtance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Reverend and Learned Divines,</hi> (who plead for <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Armes)</hi> to ſhew what great paines they have taken for the ſatisfying, or rather troubling of the Conſciences of the people, doe every where blame the <hi>Reſolver</hi> as indiligent and careleſſe. Firſt in the explication of the Queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, that he undertaking to reſolve Conſcience about <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,</hi> did not ſet down all poſſible Caſes, which they by laying their heads together have found out. Then in the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the 13. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> that he mainly inſiſting upon that place did not Analyſe the Chapter, as they have done by brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it into ſo many pieces, as if they had meant to draw out ſo many points to preach upon, rather then arguments to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute by.</p>
               <p>My Anſwer is, I did not intend that <hi>Treatiſe</hi> as a juſt Tractate of <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> but as a <hi>Reſolution</hi> of a particular Caſe; and therefore did not undertake or endeavour to ſatisfie all doubts which every working braine (that ha's ſtrained it ſelfe to the diſturbance of this State and people) might raiſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Reſiſtance in generall, but to reſolve the Conſciences of miſled People in relation to the reſiſtance now made. Now
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111670:7"/>becauſe they muſt have things delivered in groſſe to them, if we meane they ſhould apprehend them, I did therefore think it ſufficient, firſt, in the Explication of the Queſtion to direct their thoughts upon the notorious Reſiſtance then uſed, <hi>viz.</hi> by ſetting up a <hi>Militia,</hi> raiſing Armies every where, and uſing them in Battell againſt His Majeſty, for unto that Reſiſtance the Caſe propounded did relate, as was intimated SECT. I. and then in the clearing of the 13 to the <hi>Rom.</hi> it ſeemed ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to let the people underſtand, That the King was the <hi>Higher</hi> or <hi>Supream</hi> power in this Kingdom; that All under the higher power were forbidden to reſiſt; that Tyranny and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution were not ſufficient cauſes of Reſiſtance, which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the conſideration of thoſe times; laſtly, that the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Reſiſtance concerned all times, becauſe the Apoſtle's Reaſons againſt it, being drawn from the inſtitution of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and the end or benefit of it, are perpetuall and concerne all Governments. Theſe few neceſſary particulars deduced out of the Apoſtle, I thought more fit to let the People underſtand, then to puzzle them with many needleſſe termes of analyſe and diviſion.</p>
               <p>And now let us conſider the Caſes propounded by the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; amonſt them all, that onely is pertinent which enquires, whether the reſiſting of a Captain of the Souldiery having his commiſſion from the King, and comming to act any illegall commands with his bands of armed men, be a reſiſting of the King, and ſo forbidden? <hi>pag.</hi> 1. <hi>Anſ.</hi> They might eaſily have anſwered themſelves, who, I know, are perſwaded that the reſiſting of Captains having Commiſſion from the Houſes, and comming to plunder or take away the Eſtates of <hi>Malignants,</hi> is a reſiſting of the Parliament; but more to this caſe preſently. Onely let us conſider their leading Caſes firſt: What if it be doubted, ſay they, whether a King be diſtracted, or bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, or forced by ſuch as have him Priſoner, or otherwiſe a command upon him; are Subjects bound from reſiſting His il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall commands? <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>Anſw.</hi> If it be cleare that a King is ſo, I ſuppoſe it is cleare in Law what courſe is to be taken; but being doubted onely (as the caſe is put) and that perhaps up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111670:7"/>as little ground as ſome have endeavoured to make the People believe, their King is now held Priſoner by his Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leires, and forced to doe what he doth; then the <hi>Safer way</hi> is to be taken, which is to doe no more by way of reſiſtance, then is Lawfull to doe, when it is cleare He is not Forced or diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and that will better appeare by the Caſe following: ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it be certain a King is not forced or diſtracted, yet doing as bad as any diſtracted perſon can doe by commanding Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Acts, why ſhould His Subjects hands be bound fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſiſting his followers, offering to act His Tyranny more then if he were forced or diſtracted? <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is needleſſe and odious, and cannot concerne the Caſe in Queſtion, but by refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting upon His Majeſty, but put this caſe of any King ſo doing: I Anſwer. 1. There is much difference twixt habituate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, and actuall extravagances or Tyrannicall attempts, for by that a Prince is not maſter of his Will, and is made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to bear the Power <hi>(i.)</hi> the adminiſtration of it, but by theſe he is not ſo. 2. Becauſe this falls in with the Caſe, as it is propounded in better termes by the Author of the Treatiſe of Monarchy, <hi>whether the forceable reſiſtance of inferiour Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons miſimployed to ſerve the illegall deſtructive Commands of the Prince be unlawfull? pa.</hi> 51. I anſwer, if by thoſe <hi>miſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed perſons</hi> be underſtood, the Commanders and Souldiers of the Kings Armyes, I cannot ſee (nor any man elſe, I think) but the reſiſting of them by a contrary <hi>Militia</hi> or Armes raiſed by Subjects, is a reſiſting of the King and unlawfull; and unto this Reſiſtance the Caſe, as I propounded it did relate, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the firſt Reſolution was, <hi>That were the King what they ſuppoſed him to be, there was no warrant for ſuch reſiſtance.</hi> But if by thoſe miſimployed perſons be underſtood other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of oppreſſion in times of Peace before it come to Armes, ſuch as the <hi>pleaders for defenſive Armes</hi> doe ſuppoſe (in their laſt Caſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 2.) to have counterfeited the Kings Seal or Warrant, and by it to Spoyle and Murther all the Kings faithfull Subjects if they be not reſiſted; or ſuch as the <hi>Author of the Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> doth (in his inſtances <hi>pag.</hi> 57.) ſuppoſe indeed to have the Kings Seale or Warrant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111670:8"/>they might range through the Kingdome, waſting and ſpoyling, taxing and diſtraining, yea might deſtroy the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament as they ſit in their Houſes, if they might not be reſiſted. <hi>Anſ.</hi> For that of the counterfeited Seale, it is not to the purpoſe; if there be cauſe to doubt or ſuſpect ſuch a Seale, there are undoubted Miniſters of Power and juſtice to makeſtay of it till it be made known above; as we ſee thoſe dealt with, that bring counterfeit Briefes, and as ſome years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, he that counterfeited a Commiſſion for taking up Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for <hi>Virginia,</hi> was ſtaid by authority and brought to Iuſtice. But ſuppoſe ſuch inſtruments of oppreſſion have indeed the Kings Seale, and Warrant to Taxe, Diſtreine, &amp;c, May not private men reſiſt ſuch in their murthering aſſaults, and the Miniſters of Power and Authority ſuppreſſe them in each County by Force? I anſwer. This is an enlarging of the Caſe, which concernes the preſent reſiſtance as now it is underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Subjects with Armyes in the field. Yet for farther ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and without prejudice to that which clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth the preſent reſiſtance as unlawfull, I conceive it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to ſay. Firſt, if private men be ſuddainly aſſaulted in their Perſons by ſuch inſtruments, without any foregoing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or reaſon (as of Taxing, Diſtraining, Arreſting) ſo that their life is imminently indangered, and no meanes of avoiding by ſlight, then is perſonall defence Lawfull; for ſuch ſudden aſſault carries no pretence of authority with it; but if ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imployed inſtruments come firſt to Taxe, Diſtraine, Arreſt, (as it is ſuppoſed) private men ought not to reſiſt, and ſo draw on the endangering of life, but to ſeek redreſſe above from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and, if it may not be had, yet not to reſiſt. Secondly, If the Miniſters of Power in each County doe at firſt ſtay, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, and commit ſuch miſ-imployed inſtruments, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the matter again to the King; if the two Houſes of Parliament alſo, deale in like manner with thoſe that by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of any ſuch Warrant ſhould notoriouſly treſpaſſe upon them, this is not to reſiſt; for here is only a deſire of informing the King aright, not a will of contending with him, if he will not be of another mind. Now (as the <hi>pleaders for defenſive
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111670:8"/>Armes</hi> ſay <hi>pag.</hi> 2.) <hi>The Law ſuppoſing the King can doe no wrong ſuppoſeth wrong may be done in His name,</hi> and therefore teacheth the Miniſters of Power and Iuſtice under him, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſuch illegall Warrants and ſurreptitiouſly or by fraud procured, and ſo at firſt to make ſtay of ſuch miſ-imployed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and to bring the matter again to the knowledge of the King.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Should a King be ſo obſtinate, as to perfiſt in the maintenance of thoſe illegall courſes, and to that end imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Militia</hi> or power of Armes, wherewith he is inveſted, it is neither Legall nor Reaſonable, that the Miniſters of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er under him, ſhould purſue the oppoſition to the ſetting up of a <hi>Militia</hi> or contrary power, to the introducing of a Civill Warre. For though ſuch Miniſters of Power ought to uſe all faire and <hi>Lawfull means</hi> for the reſtraining of ſuch miſ-imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inſtruments, and it is not for me to ſet bounds how farre they may proceed in preſerying the Kings Peace, by uſing that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er againſt miſ-imployed Perſons, yet ſurely they cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed ſo farre as to a conteſtation of Power with Him whoſe Miniſters they are, much leſſe to a Levying of Warre, as at this day, and an appoſing of Armies againſt Armies. This is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance ſuppoſed in the Caſe, and in this Caſe to reſiſt the Kings Forces is to reſiſt Him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>Severall kinds of Monarchy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the next place we are called to a conſideration of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall kinds of Monarchicall government, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, whether in any of them this Reſiſtance by force of Armes may find allowance or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>The Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> obſerving there was but little pretence from Scripture, either by precept or Example, for Reſiſtance, confeſſeth that the Kings, under which the People of God were in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, might not be reſiſted, and therefore layes all the defence of Reſiſtance upon reaſon, drawn from the ſeverall condition
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111670:9"/>of an <hi>Abſolute</hi> and of a <hi>Limited</hi> or <hi>Mixed</hi> Monarchy. For which purpoſe he ſpends the firſt part of his book, in clearing the poynt according to his own principles, and then comming to apply what he had ſaid, touching Limited and Mixed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchyes, to the Government of this Land, he complaines of us Divines, that we plead for Abſoluteneſle of Monarchicall power in this Kingdome, never making any difference of Powers, but bringing proofes for Subjection and againſt Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from places of Scripture (a ſore fault) and examples which concerne the manner of the government of <hi>Iudah, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, and the Romans:</hi> as if that which holds in our govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did alwaies hold in another, ſo he <hi>pag.</hi> 33. And then he endeavours to prove this Monarchy, to be ſo mixed, as that the Houſes of Parliament be originally joyned with the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch in the Soveraign Power. Whence he thinks he has both an anſwer to places and examples taken out of Scripture, that they belonged to <hi>abſolute Monarchies,</hi> are not appliable to ours; and alſo a demonſtration of his concluſion for Reſiſtance. <hi>viz.</hi> that by the <hi>Mixed</hi> condition of this Monarchy (as he phanſyeth it) the two Houſes are veſted with power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine with force of Armes the Exorbitances of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It was never my intent (nor was, I ſuppoſe, of other Divines) to plead for abſoluteneſſe of Power in the King, if by abſoluteneſſe of power be meant (as it ſhould be) a power of Arbitrary command, but if by Abſoluteneſſe of Power this Author means (as he doth ſometimes) a Power not to be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted or conſtrained by force of Armes raiſed by Subjects, ſuch a power we plead for, and do ſay, That as thoſe places and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples out of Scripture did forbid reſiſtance then, and ſhew, no warrant for it can be had either by precept or example out of Gods word, ſo doe they condemne reſiſtance in this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, though <hi>Limited,</hi> as ſhall be ſhewen.</p>
               <p>We allow a diſtinction of Monarchies, and admit the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Kingdomes to be of divers Kinds, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111670:9"/>a Legall reſtraint upon the Power of the Monarch in this Kingdome; but when this Author has made all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage he can of his <hi>Limited and mixed</hi> formes of Monarchy, it will not availe him for the Countenancing of Armes taken up by Subjects: for this will appeare to be truth, agreeable to Scripture and Reaſon. That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>overnment is not the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man, but the inſtitution of God, whereby he rules men by men ſet over them in his ſtead; and though hee doth not now immediatly deſigne thoſe his Vicegerents, but by other meanes, bee it by the choice of the People; yet have they their power not from the People, (to whom it belongs to bee governed, and doe by chooſing a Governour, ſeeke a benefit ſafely) but from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, by vertue of his inſtitution of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Alſo, that the Governing Power, is one and the ſame, which God gives and ſettles upon the Perſon that is <hi>Supreme,</hi> and ſtands immediatly next to God, betweene Him and the People: onely that Power may bee <hi>Limited</hi> in the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of it, as the People by agreement at firſt, or by Petition af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter can procure. Alſo, that where the Prince ſtands <hi>Supreme,</hi> and next to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od above all the People, there Subjects may not take Armes, and make forceable Reſiſtance, notwithſtanding he be exorbitant in the exerciſe and uſe of that Power, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of ſuch Rights and Priviledges, as they enjoy by firſt compact, or after procurement.</p>
               <p>The pleaders for reſiſtance on the other ſide, do wilfully em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and reſt upon the Opinion of Heathen writers, touching the beginning of Government, and the derivation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Power from the People, as if they had not Scripture (which the Heathen wanted) to give them better direction herein.</p>
               <p>The Authour of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy</hi> ſeemes to referre the beginning of Government to Gods ordinance, and to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the power to be from God, <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. but in the proceſſe of his booke, wee ſhall finde him deriving it indeed from the People, and <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. he concludes thus for both. <hi>They, which ſay that Soveraignes have their Power from God, ſpeake in ſome ſenſe truth, as alſo they Which ſay that originallie power is in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111670:10"/>People, may in a ſound ſenſe be underſtood; and in theſe things we have D.</hi> Fernes <hi>conſent in his diſcourſe upon this Subject, Sect.</hi> 3. Anſw. you had not his conſent in your ſenſe; for in that Sect. it was his intent to ſhew that the Governing Power, <hi>(i)</hi> ſuch an Authority or ſufficiency for command and coertion, was from God, though the deſignation of the Perſon be by choice of the People, and the limitations of that power in ſeverall kinds of Monarchy be by their conſent and agreement. Now if to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne the Perſon, or procure limitation of the power in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of it, bee in your <hi>ſound ſenſe</hi> to give the power, there's no great harme to us, or advantage to you: you muſt have the power originally from the people in another ſenſe, or elſe you can make no pretence by it for your grounds of Reſiſtance; and ſo you doe, when you tell us, <hi>Pag.</hi> 16. they ſometime <hi>reſerve a power</hi> to oppoſe or diſplace the Magiſtrate: ſometime they make the Monarch Supreme, and then they diveſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of all <hi>Superiority,</hi> and have no <hi>power left</hi> to oppoſe him in Perſon, and <hi>Pag.</hi> 63. you call them <hi>Architectonicall powers,</hi> committing the power of Government and Armes, &amp;c. This is the riddle of this governing power originally in the people, they are <hi>Architect. powers,</hi> but build upon foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations laid in the aire; they are inveſted with <hi>Superioritie, but</hi> none can tell over whom, beſides themſelves; they <hi>reſerve a power,</hi> but ſuch as they never had; for before Government eſtabliſhed, they have not any power of a community or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique power, whereby a command may be laid upon others, but onely a naturall power of private Reſiſtance, wherewith every one of them is in particular endued, which power they cannot uſe againſt the publique Magiſtrate, when once they have deſigned him.</p>
               <p>Now let us take a neerer view of the formes of Monarchy ſpoken of by this Author, and make a few obſervations upon ſuch particulars, as wil be of more neceſſary conſideration, when we come to the examination of Scripture, of Reaſon, and of the Conſtitution of this Monarchy.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he tels us, Abſolute Monarchy is when the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty is ſo fully in one, that it hath no limits or bounds under
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111670:10"/>God, but the Monarchs owne will: ſo it is when a People are abſolutely reſigned up or doe reſigne up themſelves to be gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by one man, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. We allow this deſcription, but muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it below, when this Author will tell us, the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> Kings were abſolute Monarchs, which will not appeare by this deſcription, alſo when he tels us that to make a Monarch irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible, is to make him abſolute, for we ſee by this deſcription it is not the denyall of reſiſtance that makes a Monarch abſolute, but the denyall of a Law to bound his will.</p>
               <p>In the next place he tels us, He is a limited Monarch who hath a Law beſides His owne will for the meaſure of His pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>pag.</hi> 12. This alſo is true. But he ſuppoſeth firſt, that this Monarch muſt be limited in the very power it ſelfe, not onely in the exerciſe of the power, for an abſolute Monarch may ſtint himſelfe, in the exerciſe of his power, and yet remaine abſolute. <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, if ſuch a Monarch limit himſelfe to ſuch a Rule in ſuch a caſe, reſerving power to vary from it when hee ſhall ſee good cauſe: but if he that is Originally abſolute and unlimited doe in ſome particular caſes fixe a Law with promiſe not to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from it, he is ſo farre forth, and onely ſo farre as concernes thoſe caſes, limited and not abſolute. Secondly, hee ſuppoſes, ſuch a Monarch muſt bee Radically <hi>(i.)</hi> Originally inveſted with ſuch a meaſure of limited power, and that hee muſt have his bounds or limit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of power <hi>ab externo,</hi> not from the free de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of his own wil. <hi>pag.</hi> 12. yet at the beginning of the next page, hee tels us, that ſoeveraignty comes thus to bee deſined to a rule, <hi>(i)</hi> to bee limited, either by Originall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, or by after condeſcent, when a Monarch, originally abſolute, deſcends from His abſoluteneſſe to a more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate power. That which he has to ſalve it is, that this limiting by after condeſcent, is equivalent to that which is by Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſtitution; for there is in it a <hi>change of title,</hi> and a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Monarch to be <hi>Subject to</hi> in no other way, then according to ſuch a Law, <hi>pag.</hi> 13. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Where here is ſuch a change of title as this man ſuppoſeth, it is done at once, and by expreſſe and notorious reſignation of the Monarchs former title and power. But it is not neceſſary that an Abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111670:11"/>ſhould come to a limited condition after that manner, for a Monarch that was unlimited at firſt, by degrees may li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and bind up his power, and give oath for greater ſecurity, that he will rule accordingly, and requires <hi>not to be ſubject to,</hi> but according to ſuch limitations or Lawes; and ſo it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that the pious Princes of this Land have anciently done. Only when it is ſaid, they <hi>require not to be ſubject to but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp;c.</hi> it muſt be underſtood in regard of <hi>Active</hi> ſubjection, which they cannot expect, if they ſhall command againſt thoſe Lawes, nor in regard of <hi>Paſſive</hi> ſubjection, as if they allowed their Subject to reſiſt upon ſuch commands; for it can ſcarce be imagined, that any Prince ſhould condeſcend to a limited uſe of his power, and blinde himſelfe by Oath not to tranſgreſſe the limits, hee ſhould alſo have the bands of force and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint caſt upon him, for the keeping of Him within thoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits.</p>
               <p>The other diſtinction, which moſt concernes the buſineſſe in hand, is of <hi>Monarchy</hi> into <hi>ſimple,</hi> without any Mixture of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocracy or Democracy, and <hi>Mixed,</hi> that has an allay from one or both of thoſe. In the explication of which, that hee may lay convenient grounds for ſuch a <hi>Mixture</hi> as he would make in this Monarchy, he tels us; if the compoſition bee of three, then muſt the ſoveraigne power be in all three Originally, and not one holding his power from the other, but all equally from the fundamentall conſtitution; His Reaſons are. 1. Becauſe elſe it would be no <hi>Mixture</hi> but a <hi>Derivation</hi> of Power to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which is ſeene in the moſt ſimple Monarchy. 2. Becauſe the end of <hi>Mixture</hi> (which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to keepe each ſtate from exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy) could not be obtained by a derivate power; for ſuch a power cannot turne back, and ſet bounds to its beginning, ſo he, <hi>pag.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſee by thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where he will place the two Houſes, in a Society of the Soveraigne Power, and that by Originall conſtitution, which will appeare but a phanſy when wee come to examine it below; but for the grounding of it, hee ſuppoſes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111670:11"/>that <hi>Mixture</hi> muſt be in the very ſoveraigne power, and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally, or from the beginning of the government; neither of which is neceſſary: for I conceive that as <hi>Limitation</hi> in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is in regard of a Law or Rule, which bounds the will of the Monarch for thoſe particulars that Law concernes; and ſuch limitation may be onely of the exerciſe of the power not of the power it ſelfe; ſo <hi>Mixtures</hi> is in regard of Perſons joyned to the Monarch for certaine Acts and purpoſes; but that ſuch Perſons ſhould have a ſhare with the Monarch in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Power, is ſo farre from being neceſſary to that mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which Monarchy will admit of, that indeed it cannot conſiſt with that Supremacy which is ſupped to be in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, for it would make ſeverall independent powers in the ſame State or Kingdome, which is moſt abſurd. If therefore the concurrence and conſent of ſuch perſons be required as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the <hi>exerciſe</hi> onely of the Soveraigne power in ſuch or ſuch Acts, it is ſufficient to make a <hi>Mixture</hi> in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>In like manner as it was ſaid above of <hi>Limited</hi> Monarchyes, that it is not neceſſary they ſhould bee ſo Originally, but may become ſuch by after condeſcent, ſo may it be ſaid of <hi>Mixed</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies. And it is cleare that in moſt Monarchies of <hi>Europe,</hi> which have beene parts or branches of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire and by force of Armes broken off from it, the Monarch at firſt had abſolute power, (like as the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours had over their conquered Provinces) but by degrees have received <hi>Limitations</hi> to governe according to ſuch and ſuch Lawes, and have admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Mixtures</hi> by a concurrence of ſuch and ſuch perſons, whoſe conſent ſhould be requiſite and neceſſary to ſome exerciſes of their ſoveraigne power.</p>
               <p>Now to his Reaſons I anſwer, Derivation of power is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon ſubſtitute Officers and Miniſters, which ſupply the abſence of the Monarch in the execution of Power and Juſtice for him upon his People, and ſuch derivation of Power is in the moſt ſimple Monarchy: or elſe it is upon ſuch Perſons or ſuch an order of men, whoſe concurrence and conſent is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to certaine Acts of Monarchicall Power, and this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111670:12"/>makes a Mixture, though they have no ſhare in the very pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but concurre to the exerciſe of it only, and have not that neither Originally, but upon condeſcent of the Prince; yet have it certainly and irrevocably by Law ſetled upon them. Now if this Author will not call this a <hi>Mixture,</hi> becauſe it is not Originally in the power it ſelfe, we cannot help it; we are ſure it makes a large and reall difference in Government, and may obtain its end (the keeping of each State from exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy) in that way it's intended to doe it in; which will give anſwer to his other Reaſon. For though a Derivative power can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> bounds to the Soveraigne power, yet may it ſtand to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> way, thoſe bounds, which the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power has ſet to it ſelfe, and made the Derivate power the keeper of. The Kings of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>des</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> were in moſt things abſolute, yet in this had they bound themſelves, not to alter a Decree made by the advice of the <hi>Septemviri,</hi> or the Princes and chiefe Counſellors of the Kingdome, as we ſee <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.14. and <hi>Eſt.</hi> 1.19. So may it be eaſily conceived in any other State; the Prince, though unlimited at firſt, may bind up his Power from ſuch or ſuch Acts, unleſſe he has the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of ſuch Counſellors unto them; which conſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence does not give them a ſhare in the Soveraign power, but makes them as Bounders in the Exerciſe of it; nor does it imply in thoſe Perſons a power of forceable conſtraint, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Legall and Morall reſtraint, as will appear in the fifth Section.</p>
               <p>I will conclude this Section with a brief conſideration of what he delivers concerning <hi>Monarchy</hi> by <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> Firſt, <hi>If the Invaſion,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>be made upon pretence of Title, and the Pretender doth prevaile, it is not conqueſt properly, but a vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a Title, and then the government is ſuch as the Title is by which he claimed,</hi> pag. 21. I will not diſpute whether a people ſo ſtanding out doe forfeit thoſe Priviledges and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they formerly enjoyed, or whether a Prince ſo forced to vindicate His Title <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſubduing the People be not free from the former Limitations, to which Princes peaceably entring bound themſelves, and whether He may not uſe ſuch a People
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111670:12"/>as a Conqueror? I ſhould commend the Clemency and Piety of that Prince, that would not, but I doe not ſee the injuſtice, if he ſhould ſo uſe them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He blames the Cenſure, which the <hi>Fuller An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> gave of Conqueſt, <hi>that the title of it was ſuch as Plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers have, &amp;c.</hi> and tells us, <hi>the Right of Conqueſt is ſuch, as the precedent Warre is, if that he Lawfull ſo is the Conqueſt, yet is it not the Conqueſt that makes them Morally bound, but their own Conſent in accepting of the Government, pag.</hi> 22. Well, but a forced conſent will ſuffice, and ſuch will ſcarce be wanting to a Conqueſt, and they that plead title of Conqueſt doe not divide it from ſuch a forced conſent of People, but from a free limiting election.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He grants that while their naturall Soveraigne is in being, the People cannot by conſent devolve a Right to the Conquerour: But ſuppoſe they have not that tye upon them, may they perpetually ſtand out againſt the Conqueror, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they not bound to conſent and yeeld to His yoake, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they ſee they are wholly ſubdued, and he has ſetled a frame of Government among them? Hee tells us <hi>Conqueſt may give title and power to diſpoſe of the Country, goods, and lives of the Conquered, but ſtill it is in the Peoples choyce to come to a Morall condition of Subjection: if they will ſuffer the utmoſt of Violence from the Conquerour rather, then conſent to any termes of Subjection, as</hi> Numantia <hi>in</hi> Spain, <hi>they dye or remain a free people, nor doe they reſiſt Gods Ordinance, if at any time of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, they uſe force to free themſelves from ſo violent a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion:</hi> ſo he pag. 22. <hi>It is an uncontrouleable truth in Policy, that the conſent of the People, either by themſelves or their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, is the only Mean in ordinary Providence, by which Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty is conferred upon any Perſon or Family;</hi> ſo he concludes pag. 23. Anſw. That conſent of People is the <hi>only meane,</hi> in your ſenſe, may be an <hi>uncontrouleable</hi> truth in the <hi>Policy</hi> lately framed; but it is certain, that God has power to diſpoſe of us in ordinary providence, without expecting our conſents and choice; it is plain by Scripture, that Conqueſt is a <hi>Mean</hi> of tranſlating Kingdoms and diſpoſing of People in the way of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111670:13"/>providence; it was ſo when God gave <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> as an hire for his ſervice done upon <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſo when the <hi>Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Edomites</hi> were ſubdued by <hi>David,</hi> of which ſee below, <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. againſt the <hi>Fuller Anſwer.</hi> Had theſe no right over thoſe conquered Nations, but by expecting their conſent? Yea, will he ſay, a Right to diſpoſe of their Lands and Goods, and lives, but not to challenge their Morall Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Well, we doubt not but ſuch Conquerors could force their conſent; but I aske, were they not bound to yeeld it? is there no way for that providence, which tranſlates Kingdoms, to diſcover it ſelfe, but by the conſent of the Conquered People, that if they pleaſe to be obſtinate, his providence ſhall give no Right? his ſetting up a King by Conqueſt over ſuch a people ſhall be no inſtitution o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ordinance? this is good <hi>Policy</hi> but bad Divinity: I conceive it all <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> controuleable</hi> truth, that when the invading Prince has perfectly ſubdued a People (there being no preſent Soveraigne or apparent Heire of the Crown, to whom they are bound) as has ſetled &amp; diſpoſed all things and conſtituted a frame of Government, then I ſay provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doth ſufficiently diſcover it ſelfe, and ſuch a people ought to ſubmit, and conſent, and take their Prince as ſet over them by the hand of Providence; ſo that, if they will perſiſt finally to reſiſt (as this Author ſaith they may) they reſiſt the Ordinance of God. If he will not beleeve me, let him heare <hi>Calvin,</hi> who in his <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>nu.</hi> 26, 27. doth inforce obedience to that Prince which is over us, by a reaſon drawn from that Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, which diſpoſeth Kingdomes, and ſets up over us what Kings he pleaſes, and from the example of <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar, Ier.</hi> 27.8. doth inferre; <hi>Cuicunqve ergo delatum fuiſſe regnum conſlabit, ei ſerviendum eſſe ne dubitemus:</hi> But how ſhall we diſcover his providence and will herein? the next words tell us: <hi>Atque ſimul ac in Regium faſtigium quempiam evebit Dominus, teſtatam nobis facit ſuam voluntatem, quòd regnare illum velit.</hi> So in his Comment upon 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet multi avaritiâ, ambitione, crudelitate invaſcrit regna &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peria, tamen Dei voluntatem pluris eſſe, quam omnia illa, faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endam ſciamus; ac proinde nos illis ultro ſubmittamus, quos Deus
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111670:13"/>Reges nobis praefecit.</hi> This is very home againſt this Authors aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, wherein he denyes Conqueſt to confer a Soveraignty, and will not ſuffer God in the ordinary way of Providence to diſpoſe of a people without their own conſents. But enough of this; We come now to make Application of what hath been ſaid to the Particular <hi>Monarchy</hi> of this Land.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Of the Conſtitution of this Monarchy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore we come to examine how this Author has ſtated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he poynt of Reſiſtance in relation to the ſeverall kinds of Monarchy, it will not be amiſſe to conſider unto what kinde this Monarchy belongs; whether it be ſuch a <hi>Limited Mixed</hi> Monarchy, as this man would have it, Originally and Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, by the placing of Nobles and Commons, as ſharers with the Monarch in the Soveraign power. It would be ſeeme the skilfull in the Law to ſpeak to this point (if they could be induced to deliver what they know) but ſeeing there is enough in Hiſtory and Reaſon, which ſpeaks the Frame and beginning of this Monarchy otherwiſe, then this Author or others before him have ſanſyed: it will not be hard to ſay ſo much, as may (which was heretofore endeavoured in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y Reply) let Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſee, it can have no plea for Reſiſtance from the ſuppoſed grounds, upon which theſe men lay the platforme of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</p>
               <p>I had twice occaſion in my firſt Treatiſe to ſpeak of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Government, in the Armes of the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> which was not (as this Author feignes, <hi>pag.</hi> 33. 34.) to prove our Kings Abſolute; herein I challenge his ingenuity, if either I propoſed this as a Concluſion to be proved, <hi>That our Kings are Abſolute,</hi> or urged the entrance of the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> as an argument to prove it by; but onely all adged it twice by way of Anſwer to what was ſpoken by them, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a right in the People by virtue of ſuch a capitulating ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction at firſt, as they ſuppoſe to have given beginning to this Monarchy; in both which places I expreſſely intimated, thoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111670:14"/>Conqueſts were not mentioned to win an Arbitrary power to the King, but onely to exclude Reſiſtance and ſuch a ſuppoſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</p>
               <p>The beginning of this Engliſh Monarchy, and the root of ſucceſſion of the Monarchs we muſt fetch from the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and this Author bids us look ſo far back, when (to cut off the advantages that may be made againſt him from the <hi>Normans</hi> entrance) he tels us, pag. 35. that Duke <hi>William</hi> came upon <hi>the old limited Title, whereby the Engliſh Saxon Kings his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors held this Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How the <hi>Saxons</hi> entred upon the Kingdome is well known: they made themſelves maſters of this Kingdome by Armes, which although it doth not inferre our Kings are now <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute,</hi> (an inference as farre from my intention as his) yet doth it plainly overthrow ſuch an originall <hi>Mixture</hi> in the ſoveraign power, as this Author has phanſyed: and herein (becauſe I have ſpoken to this point, as occaſion required, in the third Sect. of my Reply to the <hi>Full Anſwerer</hi> (who had the like conceit of ſuch an Originall <hi>Mixture,</hi> though not ſo refined as this Author has given it us) I ſhall be the briefer in my Anſwer to this.</p>
               <p>Firſt, This Author ſaith, <hi>It was not a Conqueſt that the Saxons made, but an expulſion,</hi> pag. 35. <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is neither true nor greatly materiall. Not true, for it cannot be imagined but a great part of the <hi>Brittaines</hi> remained under the <hi>Saxon</hi> yoake; ſo M. <hi>Cambden</hi> tells us, they were the fewer that fled towards <hi>Wales,</hi> and defended themſelves againſt the <hi>Saxons</hi> in the Weſt: his words are, <hi>Victi omnes in gentem, leges, nomen, linguam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vincentium, praeter paucos, quos locorum aſperitas in occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentali tractu tutata eſt, conceſſerunt. Camb, Britan. Saxon.</hi> Nor is it greatly materiall, for if we could imagine that the <hi>Brittaines</hi> were not brought under the yoke, but expelled, yet can we not imagine, that the Government of thoſe <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings (being made ſuch by the acclamation of their Souldiers, as when the <hi>Praetorian</hi> guard, or ſome Army abroad ſaluted a <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour) was at firſt any other, then is the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or command of Generalls over their Souldiers, that is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111670:14"/>
                  <hi>unlimited;</hi> much leſſe ſo <hi>Limited</hi> and <hi>Mixed,</hi> as this Author phanſyeth it, who looking upon the Modell or Platforme of this Monarchy, pag. 44. 45. doth admire their Wiſdome (as more then humane) that had the contriving of it; but can any one ſuppoſe ſuch a Platforme laid, that conſiders the beginning of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Monarchy, or imagine ſuch admirable Wiſdome more than humane, in thoſe rude and violent beginnings?</p>
               <p>But he tells us in the ſecond place, <hi>the Saxons planting themſelves here under their Commanders, no doubt continued the freedome they had in</hi> Germany, <hi>and ſo changed their ſoyle not their government,</hi> pag. 35, but what proof to put this out <hi>of doubt?</hi> a conjecture out of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> that wrote of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> ſome hundreds of years before this entrance of the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> Among the <hi>Germans</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Nec Regibus aut infinita aut libera potestas.</hi> True, but we may ſee by thoſe Authors, that M. <hi>Cambden</hi> alleadges for the Originall of theſe <hi>Saxons,</hi> that in probability theſe <hi>Suxons</hi> were not then among thoſe people of <hi>Germany,</hi> that <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpeakes of, but did afterward break out of the <hi>Cimbrica cherſoneſus,</hi> into that part of <hi>Germany</hi> where now we find the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and into this Land; But why ſhould we reſt upon ſuch dreames and uncertainties, as theſe men would put us upon? this is certain, that the <hi>Saxons</hi> being entred, and having vanquiſhed the <hi>Brittaines</hi> did by degrees, as they could winne upon the <hi>Brittaines,</hi> raiſe ſeven King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes or Monarchyes independant, yet ſo as that ſtill one of them, the moſt powerfull, was Monarch of All, or King of all England, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cambden</hi> and others ſhew out of <hi>Bede,</hi> till at length the King of the <hi>Weſt Saxons, Egbert,</hi> vanquiſhed the reſt, and ſetled the Succeſſion of the ſole Monarchy in his Line, and thoſe that ſhould come after him.</p>
               <p>Now would I fain know, how this Author, or any other of their beſt phanſies can conceive, that ſuch a <hi>Mixture,</hi> as joynes <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in the Soveraign power with the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> (for ſo they would have it) can poſſibly conſiſt with ſuch a beginning of Government? was it in them all ſeven? or could it conſiſt with that ſoleneſſe or height of Monarchy which was ſtill in one of them, and transferred from Kingdom
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111670:15"/>to Kingdome, not by any fundamentall conſtitution, but by power, and the perſonall Proweſſe of the Monarch? Or did <hi>Edgbert</hi> (that ſetled that condition of ſole and chief Monarch upon his own ſucceſſors by the ſubverſion of the other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes) know any Subjects of His to be ſharers with him in the Soveraigne power?</p>
               <p>This Author indeed tryes what his phanſy can doe, pag. 44. Where by ſix ſuppoſitions he endeavours to bring the Reader to an apprehenſion of the platforme of this Monarchy; <hi>When you have made theſe ſuppoſitions</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in your mind, you have the very Modell and Platforme of this Monarchy,</hi> Pag. 45. So the Reader muſt reſt upon his ſuppoſitions againſt the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of all Hiſtories and Chronicles; and thoſe his ſuppoſitions begin thus pag. 44. <hi>Suppoſe a People</hi> (1.) <hi>Nobles and Commons ſet over themſelves by publique compact one Soveraign, &amp; reſign up themſelves to Him and His heires, to be governed by ſuch and ſuch fundamentall Lawes; then ſuppoſe them Covenanting with their Soveraign, that if cauſe be to conſtitute any other Lawes, he ſhall not doe it by His ſole power, but they erſerve at first, or afterwards it is granted them (which is all one) a hand of concurrence therein, that they will be bound by no Lawes, but what they joyne with him in the making of.</hi> and ſo he goes on with ſix ſuppoſitions; but firſt he muſt have a ſtrong phanſy that can conceive (as I ſaid) this conſiſtent with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Government, as if it could be laid in ſuch a platforme. Secondly, in giving us the briefe of this Platforme he ſtill tells us that by the Admirable wiſdome of the Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects of this Government, the Nobles and Commons have their power and Authority, not depending on the Monarch, but radically their own, by fundamentall Mixture, ſo pag. 41. and elſewhere: but in the ſix ſuppoſitions wherein he would lay this platforme open to the view, he brings up the Houſes to this power they have, by ſteps of time; and comming to make thoſe ſuppoſitions, he ſpeaks doubtingly of the Originall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving of this government, <hi>whether</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>done at once, or by degrees found out and perfected,</hi> pag. 44. but this contriving muſt be made at once and at firſt, when they choſe the firſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111670:15"/>King, or elſe they cannot have this power and Authority radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally their own. And we cannot imagine but <hi>Bede,</hi> and other Hiſtorians, would have obſerved ſuch convention of Nobles and Commons (as this Author ſuppoſed) for the contriving of this Government, in which they demeaned themſelves with ſuch admirable wiſdome; or if they could not tell us of ſuch a convention of them at firſt, for the contriveing and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Government, they could not but obſerve ſome meetings of them after, for the uſe of this power in the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Government.</p>
               <p>Aſſemblies doubtleſſe there were for repreſenting of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to the Monarch, and for giving adviſe in the redreſſe; and among the Orders, of which thoſe Aſſemblies did ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſt, there were <hi>Procuratores cleri,</hi> the repreſentatives of the Cleargy, (as I have heard good Lawyers affirme, and one of my former Anſwers had it in his Margin, though little to his advantage) but here we are call'd by this Authour to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or rather ſuppoſe an aſſembly conſiſting of Nobles and Commons, veſted with part of the Soveraign power by orgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſtitution; when as neither he nor any other Author could bring any one Record for it above the <hi>Norman</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; and thoſe Hiſtories or Chronicles, which mention the beginning of Parliaments as now they ſtand in Authority, doe not riſe ſo high as thoſe times; Now ſeeing the Parliament it ſelfe, 24 H. 8. c, 12. doth declare, <hi>that this Realme of England has beene ever accepted for an Empire, governed by one ſupream Head &amp;c.</hi> and tells us, that Hiſtories and Chronicles ſhew as much, why ſhould theſe Chronicles be ſo many ages ſilent in the originall Conſtitution, by which this Anthor gives the two Houſes their power from the beginning of this Monarchy, if either ſuch a conſtitution ever was, or indeed could conſiſt with <hi>this Empire,</hi> and <hi>this one ſupream head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Author tells us, pag. 36. that the <hi>Tryall by twelve men and other fundamentalls of Government, wherein the Engliſh freedom conſiſts, were left untouched by the Conquerour.</hi> But why could not he tell us as well, that this power which he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to the two Houſes was left untouched? he would if he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111670:16"/>could have made it appeare to have been before the Conqueſt; Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> names the King before the Conqueſt, that firſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the tryall by twelve Men, but what Chronicle can doe as much for the other? the like originall to that of the tryall by twelve men, had other Liberties of the Subject, to wit by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condeſcent of the Prince, and yet this Author calls that Tryall a <hi>fundamentall:</hi> and ſo it is, not of the Monarchy, but of the Subjects liberty, or, as he ſaid, of the <hi>Engliſh freedome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We need not after all this (which has been ſpoken of the beginning of the Engliſh <hi>Saxon</hi> Government (into which this Author ſaith Duke <hi>William</hi> ſucceeded, and in the ſame right of thoſe <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings) ſeek advantage from the entrance of that <hi>Norman</hi> Conquerour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yet this we can ſay (and it appeare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of ſeverall Authors cited by Mr. <hi>Cambd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> in his <hi>Britan. Norman</hi>) that the Conquerour <hi>invictoriae quaſi Trophaeum,</hi> as a Trophy and memoriall of his Conqueſt, diſpoſed of the Lands of the Conquered, changed, their tenure, abrogated what <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Lawes and Cuſtomes he pleaſed, and gave them what Lawes he thought good, and unto this the People were content to yeeld, which is more then can evidently be ſaid by this Author for the ſtating of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours in a condition irreſiſtable, as we ſhall ſee below upon the 13. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> as we can ſay this to the overthrow of their ground of reſiſtance (that fundamentall mixture or joyning the Houſes with the Monarch, as ſharers, in the Soveraign power) ſo do we ſay, that what Limitations, Lawes, Priviledges, Cuſtomes, have been after procured by, or reſtored to the People, all thoſe the King as He is ſworn, ſo is He bound to obſerve, becauſe of the <hi>Cath of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that this Author ſpeakes but his own Phanſyes, when he concludes thus upon <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour. <hi>By granting the former Lawes and Government, he did equivalently put himſelfe and his ſucceſſours into the ſtate of Legall Monarchs, and in that Tenure have all the kings of this Land held the Grown unto this day, when theſe men would rake up and put a Title of Conqueſt upon them, which was never made uſe of by him who is the root of their ſucceſſion, pag.</hi> 37. How farre Duke <hi>William</hi> made uſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111670:16"/>of his Title by Conqueſt, &amp; how he granted the former Lawes and Government appeares, by that which was ſpoken even now out of M. <hi>Cambden,</hi> that is, he made uſe of it ſo farre forth as he pleaſed, and graunted what Lawes he pleaſed of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Government, and what new ones he pleaſed, thoſe he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on the people; and unto this they agreed, willingly or unwillingly it matters not, as is ſometimes graunted by this Author. But by this he did <hi>equivalentlie put himſelfe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſucceſſors into the ſtate of Legall Monarchs:</hi> He did ſo in a good ſence, but not as this Author meanes it; for we know (by that which was obſerved above <hi>Sect.</hi> 3 concerning a Monarch originally unlimited, but falling off into a more moderate and limited condition) that his meaning is, that Duke <hi>William</hi> by graunting ſuch Lawes did put himſelfe in ſuch a Condition, as if at firſt he had been limited ſo by the people, they reſerving to themſelves power of reſiſting his exorbitancies, which ſhould be deſtructive of thoſe Limitations and Lawes; this is a <hi>Legall Monarch</hi> in his ſenſe: but we ſay he became a <hi>Legall Monarch,</hi> that is bound himſelfe to rule according to ſuch Lawes as he had graunted. Nor doe we <hi>rake up a Title of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> for his Succeſſors, or would have them any other then <hi>Legall Monarchs;</hi> but by that (which has been ſhewen, and cannot be denied) it appears, that the <hi>Root of Succeſſion,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Norman,</hi> ſprang up by conqueſt, and that the Priviledges and Powers, wherewith we ſee the Subject in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted, were of an after ſpring, that is, of after agrement, or by condeſcent of the Monarch; which Powers &amp; Priviledges, grants, Liberties, though not originall, yet are they irrevoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Prince is bound, as was ſaide, to obſerve them becauſe of the <hi>Oath of God.</hi> I will but adde M. <hi>Cambdens</hi> expreſſion of the Monarchicall power. The Kings of this Land have <hi>pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem ſupremam &amp; merum imperium,</hi> ſo he in his <hi>Britan.</hi> which as it excludes all Subjects from haveing ſhare in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign power, for in that reſpect it is <hi>Merum imperium</hi> not <hi>mixtum;</hi> ſo doth it not exclude ſuch limitations and mixtures as have been by after condeſcent, for the bounding of that Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign power in the exerciſe and uſe of it.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:111670:17"/>
               <p>But now this Author will endeavor, againſt the credit of Hiſtory and Antiquiry, to reaſon us into a beliefe of ſuch a frame as he has moulded this Monarchy in. Firſt he would prove, <hi>That the Soveraignty of the King is radycally and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally Limited, not only in the uſe and exerciſe of it, but in the power it ſelfe,</hi> pag 31 then, <hi>That the Authority of this Land is Mixed in the very root and conſtitution of it.</hi> pag. 39.</p>
               <p>This were an argument fit for a skilfull Lawyer to Labour in, yet ſoe much in conſequence I can at firſt ſight perceive in his prooſes, that I dare pronounce them inſufficient to cleare what he undertakes. His proo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es are either his owne reaſons, or drawne from the Kings owne grants in his late expreſſes.</p>
               <p>His reaſons for the <hi>Limited</hi> condition of our Kings, are from the denomination of <hi>Leige</hi> and <hi>Legall</hi> Soveraigne, and from <hi>Proſcription,</hi> which evinceth, that in all ages beyond record, the Lawes &amp; Cuſtomes of this Kingdome have been the rule of Government. pag. 32 <hi>Anſw.</hi> This proves that our Kings are limited in the uſe or exerciſe of their power, and noe more for neither that Denomination, nor any preſcription can make us beleive that the Limitations of their power had any other begining, then from their voluntary and pious condeſcent to ſuch or ſuch moderations and allayes, which by conſtant uſage and cuſtome, or eiſe by expreſſe Lawes were made ever after inevitable and irrevocable by the Monarchs themſelves; the Oath alſo of ſucceeding Monarchs, binding them to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of ſuch Lawes and Cuſtomes.</p>
               <p>His reaſons Iikewiſe for the mixed conſtitution of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment doe prove a mixture, but not ſuch as he would have, nor from the begining or firſt conſtitution of the Monarchy; they are theſe: 1 Becauſe it is a Monarchy mixed with an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtocracy in the Lords, and Democracy in the Commons, but the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is no Mixture which is not in the root and ſupremacy of power, pag. 40. 2. Becauſe it is a Monarchy where the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tive power is in all three, and therfore mixed in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry root and eſſence of it, <hi>ibid.</hi> 3 Becauſe it is a Monarchy in which three Eſtates are conſtituted to the end that the power of one ſhould moderate and reſtraine from exceſſe the power of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111670:17"/>the other, and therefore mixed in the root and eſſence of it, <hi>ibid:</hi> the ſame reaſons he uſes, <hi>Pag.</hi> 43. to prove the Authority of both Houſes to be no derived authority, but equally originall and fundamentall with that of the King; and ſaith, <hi>he cannot deviſe, what can reaſonably be ſaid in oppoſition to theſe Grounds proving a fundamentall mixture. Anſw.</hi> And I muſt ſay, I cannot deviſe what ſh uld move a man of reaſon, (as this Author ſeemes to be) ſo often to proſfeſſe as he doth, that he is convinced of ſuch a fundamentall conſtitution of this Monarchy; for I cannot be convinced but his grounds are falſe ſuppoſalls.</p>
               <p>For firſt, it is not neceſſary, the mixture ſhould be in <hi>the root or Supremacy of power:</hi> but it is ſufficient, if there be a concu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Perſons, whoſe conſent is required to the exerciſe of that Supreame power, as was explained above, <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. when we ſpoke of mixture. Nay, if it muſt be <hi>in the Supremacy of power,</hi> as he will have it, how can he make the King the <hi>only Supream,</hi> and that <hi>one Head,</hi> to which the whole Body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique is bound and united, as he grants, <hi>pag.</hi> 42.43. He cannot ſalve it with his <hi>Apex potestatis,</hi> which he there gives to the King, unieſle the King muſt be the Crowne or top of the head only; for they alſo muſt be our <hi>Head</hi> and our <hi>Soveraignes,</hi> if they be mixed or joyned with him in the <hi>Supremacy of power,</hi> as this Author would have it,</p>
               <p>Secondly, the phraſe of <hi>Legiſlative power,</hi> aſcribed to the two Houſes is ſatisfied and explained by that concurrence and conſent of theirs in and to the exerciſe of the Supream power, as above; but I cannot be convinced, that it argues the power it ſelfe, which gives life to a Law, to be in them, but their aſſent to be requiſite and neceſſary, ſo that without it no Law can be made; which is enough if men could be content. So when it is ſaid, <hi>Be it enacted by the Authority of this Parliament:</hi> None denies, but to have ſuch Vote or power of affenting is a great Authority, but not ſuch as makes them ſharers in the <hi>Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of power,</hi> for then ſhould they alſo be our Head and our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignes, as was ſaid above; before that phraſe was uſed, we find it r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n thus, <hi>The King by the advice and aſſent of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111670:18"/>Earles, and Barons, and at the inſtance and requeſt of the Commonalty has ordained. &amp;c:</hi> which tells us plainly, where the fountaine of the <hi>ordaining</hi> or <hi>Legiſlative</hi> power is; &amp; how that power is excited or ſtirred up to Act, by <hi>the inſtance and requeſt</hi> of the Commons repreſenting to the King the grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his People; and that the efflux of that fountaine, or the exerciſe of that power is not ſoly in his Will, that is, comes not to the Act of ordaining without the conſent of Lords and Commons.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to his third Reaſon I anſwer; The end of this mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or concurrence is to <hi>reſtraine from exceſſe;</hi> but the reſtraint is morall and legall, not forcible by power of Armes, <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary</hi> by way of aſſent or diſſent to the ordaining power, not <hi>military</hi> by Armies in the Field; as will more clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the next Section concerning reſiſtance in mixed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchyes: Now ſuch a morall reſtraint doth not argue the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy mixed in the Root and firſt conſtitution, for the Houſes may be veſted with ſuch a power afterward; but the Reſtraint that this Author intends is a forcible reſtraint by Armes, a meer phanſy, for if the fundamentall Conſtitution had inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them ſuch a power, it would not have left a power in the Monarch to call them or diſſolve them, which would make this pretended power of theirs altogether in effectuall, but would have left them continually exiſting and in being.</p>
               <p>His proofes from the Kings owne Grants for the <hi>Radicall Limitation</hi> of this Monarchy are theſe, <hi>Pag.</hi> 31. His Majeſty who beſt knowes by his Counſell the nature of his owne pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſaith, <hi>That the Law is the meaſure of his power,</hi> and in his Anſwer concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> ſayes, <hi>If more power ſhall be thought fit to be granted them, then by Law is in the Crown, &amp;c.</hi> whereby it is granted, The King has no more power then by Law is in him: ſo he. Alſo for ſuch a <hi>mixed Condition</hi> of this Monarchy as theſe men would have, they uſually urge what His Majeſty has graciouſly ſaid in His Anſwer to the 19 Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, <hi>That there is a power Legally placed in the two Houſes, more then ſufficient to prevent and reſtraine the power of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> To this purpoſe it is alſo, that ſome make advantage of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111670:18"/>Kings ſpeaking of Himſelfe, as of one of the <hi>Three Eſtates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is well known, when the king was firſt forced to make his defence by writing, how few he had about Him, being drive<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from his learned <hi>Counſell,</hi> or they one way or other kept from Him. Yet truſting to the juſtneſſe of his Cauſe, &amp; integrity of his own intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, He returned ſuch Anſwers as did for the preſent much ſattisfie all reaſonable people, and will one day (what ever advantage is now pickt out of them) be witneſſes againſt thoſe Troublers of our peace, that put him to his defence.</p>
               <p n="2">II. It is very unjuſt, that the gratious Expreſſions, which his Majeſty has had of his Intentions and deſires to rule and Command no otherwiſe then according to law, ſhould be ſet upon the Rack and drawn out to his diſadvantage, for the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch a power to the Houſes, as the law ſpeakes not to be in them. If <hi>Trajan,</hi> fully purpoſing to rule Iuſtly, doth out of ſuch Confidence give a Prefect his Commiſſion and power, delivering him a Sword with theſe words, <hi>Hoc prome vtere ſirecte impero, ſi male cotra me; If I Command aright, uſe this ſword for me, if not againſt me.</hi> Shall it be concluded, that Officer might acordingly uſe his Sword againſt the Emperours? 'And if the King ſpeake of himſelfe as of One of the three Eſtates, ſhall any Subject diligently watch what fal's from Him, and return him his words again to his own diſadvantage, (as <hi>Ben. hadads</hi> Meſſengers did 1. <hi>Kings,</hi> 20.33. <hi>Thy Brother</hi> Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad <hi>(your fellow States S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. That which can fairely be gathered out of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as intended by his Majeſty, doth not come up to theſe mens concluſions; the firſt and ſecond ſpeeches do ſhew, how tender he is of doing any thing he may not do by law, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his power is bounded and limited by Law; but it doth not follow, that his power or Soveraignty, wherein it is not limited by law, is not abſolute and full; for ſo it is clearly, whereſoever a Monarchy, at firſt unlimited, doth afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Limits and Mixtures; of which Condition this Monarchy appeares to be by that which has been ſpoken in this Section.</p>
               <p>So in his Anſwer to the 19. Prop. His Majeſty acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111670:19"/>
                  <hi>a power Legally in the Houſes to restraine</hi>— which can not be extended beyond a <hi>Morrall, Parliamentary</hi> reſtraint; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe let them produce any law that inables the Houſes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain Tyranny by the Armes of the Kingdom; for as for their deductions from ſuppoſed Fundamentalls, we can deny them, as faſt as they bring them, either as failing in thire Antecedents and falſe ſuppoſitions, or as altogether inconſequent. Alſo when this author of the Treatiſe of Monarchy doth in regard of that power, which is placed in the two Houſes to reſtraine the ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bitancies of the Monarch, ſo much admire the frame of this Government, as compoſed by more then Humane wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom pag. 44. Doe's he fall into this admiration for the placing of a power of reſtraint by forceable reſiſtance? nothing admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in that, were that the frame of this Government. That which is commendable indeed and admirable in the Limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and mixtures of this Government, is that Way of Legall, Morrall, or Parliamentary prevention and Reſtraint, which is eſtabliſhed by law fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our ſecurity.</p>
               <p>Laſtly when his Majeſty hath ſpoken of himſelfe, as of one of the three Eſtates, he has but ſpoken to them in their owne phraſe (for they firſt ſtiled him ſo) and that uſually in the point of his Negative Voyce; for every Bill comes to him in the third or laſt place, the Lords ſpirituall and Temporall, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are two of the three Eſtates, making a Concurrence in one Vote or Voice. But his Majeſty did never uſe that phraſe with any intent of diminution to his Supremacy or Headſhip; for properly the Prelates, Lords, and Commons, are the three Eſtates of this Kingdome, under his Majeſty as their head.</p>
               <p>Thus if we will truſt our owne Eyes for what we read in Hiſtory and Chronicle, or ſtand to Reaſon for the cleare Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which may be drawne from the knowne lawes of this Land, or uſe any ingenuity in the interpretation of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlies Gratious Expreſſions, We can never be perſwaded that the begining of this Monarchy was ſuch, as theſe men ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that is, ſo <hi>Limited and mixed radically and fundamentally,</hi> as theſe Authors and others have deſcribed it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:111670:19"/>
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>Of Reſiſtance in relation to the ſeverall kindes of</hi> MONARCHY.</head>
               <p>VVE are now to conſider, how this Author ſtates the poynt of forceable Reſiſtance in theſe ſeverall kinds of Government, Which we ſhall find to be in away that lies very open to Rebellion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He grants the perſon of the Monarch in all thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall kinds of Monarchy to be above the reach of all force or poſitive Reſiſtance. This is true: but if this Author will allow as he doth, Subjects to rayſe Armes, and with them to give battle to thoſe that are about the Perſon of the Monarch, as his Guard, how ſhall His Perſon be ſecured from the Force and violence of the meaneſt hand? Nay the joyning of Battell with Him, as it is neceſſary conſequence of Refiſtance by Armes, which muſt come to that, if it be purſued, ſo is it a direct Force intended and offered againſt His Perſon.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Concerning an <hi>Abſuolte Monarch,</hi> he reſolves it thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If ſuch a Monarch ſhould ſo farre degenerate as apparently to ſeeke the deſtruction of the whole Community ſubject to him, then might ſuch a community constreined by the laſt neceſſity reſiſt by force of Armes againſt any inſtruments imployed to effect the ſame,</hi> pag 9. <hi>for ſuch an intention cannot be the Act of a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable will,</hi> pag. 10. But firſt, if he meanes by the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, <hi>the whole body over which the power is placed,</hi> as he ſpeakes, <hi>pag.</hi> 10 I grant it the Act of a moſt unreaſonable will, but cannot conceive, how ſuch an intention ſhould fall into the mind of the worſt Tyrant, as to leave himſelfe no people to reigne over. Secondly, if he meanes by that community a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſort of people, as were the <hi>Iewes</hi> in the Kingdomes of <hi>Ahaſnerus,</hi> and the <hi>Templars</hi> in theſe Weſterne Kingdomes; the deſtruction of ſuch a people may be the Act of a reaſonable will; <hi>Haman</hi> makes a faire pretence and reaſon for the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the <hi>Iewes, Eſt.</hi> 3.8. and <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> his decree was
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111670:20"/>the act of a reaſonable, though miſguided will; but that ſuch a Community, upon the knowledge of ſuch an intention may take Armes, is not proved by this Author; for to prove it as he doth) by <hi>Davias</hi> example, who was but a particular man, is to ſhew that a Community may doe it becauſe <hi>David</hi> in his owne particular might do it, and ſo to prove it by afferting a greater abſurdity, <hi>viz.</hi> that a particular or private man may take Armes againſt an abſolute Monarch. His other example he would prove it by, is the Revolt of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> from the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who reſolved to extirpate the whole people, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. But it is evident, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King intended the extirpation of the <hi>Protestants</hi> only; and as this Author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s told us here his opinion of the Revolt thereupon in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> ſo I would deſire him to deliver his opinion of the Revolt and Rebellion of the Papiſts in <hi>Ireland</hi> upon their cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge that their extirpation was contrived here, this Author knowes by whom; I plead not for them but could wiſh that the aſſertions and practice of Theſe times did not give them too much advantage; I could tell him the opinion and Reſolution of the <hi>Iewes</hi> under <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> that they would not take Armes for their defence till it was permitted them by the King, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt.</hi> 8.11. and the opinion of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans, that they alowed not reſiſtance, although the deſtruction of their whole Community was evidently attempted. This may be objected againſt his Reſolution of the point, to make it doubtfull; I muſt needs ſay this Caſe of generall deſtruction and <hi>Extirpation</hi> (which ſome call <hi>extreme Neceſſity</hi>) is a very hard caſe; and whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t will excuſe a people, that in ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity ſhall take Armes, I diſpute not, nor is it needfull I ſhould: for it neither concernes the Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as now it ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene our King and his Subjects, He inviting them by all faire offers to return from their obſtinate diſloyalty, promiſing aſſuring them the Preſervation of Religion Lawes, Liberties; and what not? Nor doth it concerne the Queſtion now in hand which ſuppoſes not <hi>Extirpation</hi> of a People as cauſe of their Armes, but only Exorbitancies of the Prince tending to a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Religion and Liberties, which Exorbitancies, if
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111670:20"/>they ſhould be patiently born for the time that they ſhall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, do not take away the being and ſubſiſtence of a people, as <hi>Extirpation</hi> doth; but only put them, for that time, under the inconveniences of arbitrary government; under which the people of God in the old Teſtament, and the Chriſtians in the New, were left without remedy by forceable Reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Againe, if any particular mans life be invaded without any plea or Reaſon for it, he thinkes that ſuch a one may uſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable Reſiſtance againſt any Agents in ſuch aſſault of murder, and that it is juſtified by the fact of <hi>David,</hi> and reſcue of <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> from the Cauſeleſſe cruell intent of <hi>Saul,</hi> pag. 10. The Rule here ſeemes to ſpeak no more then a Perſonall defence againſt a Murthering aſſault, which was allowed above <hi>Sect.</hi> 2 provided that it be ſuddaine without any foregoing reaſon or pretence of Authority, and alſo inevitable: but in the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples he would inferre more then he ſpeakes in the Rule; for he ſuppoſes the people would have reſcued <hi>lonathan</hi> by force, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Saul</hi> had perſiſted in his intent, and upon that falſe ſuppoſall, inſinuates thus much, that if particular mens lives be ſought after, others may interpoſe with Armes for their defence; and the <hi>Learned Divines</hi> doe expreſly inferre from it, that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries may aſlociate and bind themſelves by oath not to ſuffer any of the impeached Members to be cut off: good doctrines theſe from Scripture, as we ſhall ſee when we come to that place. So in <hi>Davids</hi> Example he would inſinuate that if par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular mens lives be ſought after, they may raiſe and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tame Forces for their defence, as <hi>David</hi> did; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f this ſeeme moſt abſurd &amp; dangerous (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indeed it is) and if the <hi>Jſraelitiſh</hi> Kings were abſolute (as this Author often grants) then muſt be acknowledge (what he accounts but one of my ſhifts, <hi>pag.</hi> 57.) that <hi>Davids</hi> example is not herein appliable, but in this way of defence, extraordinary. Of which more particularly below, when we come to places of Scripture, that concerne <hi>Davids</hi> behaviour towards <hi>Saul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, he tells us, (which he ſhould have done in the firſt place) that Subjects of an abſolute Monarch muſt without reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſubmit their eſtates, liberties, and perſons to his will,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111670:21"/>ſo it carry any plea or ſhew of reaſon and equity, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here the way is open enough to Rebellion, for every man will be ready to thinke there is no reaſon or equity in the will of the Monarch, when he is oppreſſed by him; and if the plea or ſhew of reaſon and equity muſt be the barre to Reſiſtance, it will lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle availe him to anſwer below, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors might not be reſiſted, becauſe they were abſolute, for never was there leſſe plea of Reaſon and Equity in the will of any Tyrants, then in theirs. But he will cloſe up the way by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, abſolute Monarchy reſolves all judgement into the will of the Monarch; ſo that if his will judicially cenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it juſt it muſt be yeelded to as juſt, ſo he, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. But did not <hi>Saul</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>David</hi> is one affecting the Kingdome, and therefore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to dye, which was the act of a Reaſonable will, though following a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ormed underſtanding; and did he not uſe a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dicary proceſſe in the Cauſe of <hi>Ionath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cing him upon the tryall of Lots, why then were theſe examples brought, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Author in the former page for Reſiſtance, if ſuch a will o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Monarch muſt be yeelded to? and why is there ſuch a condition added in the Rule, <hi>ſo it carry any plea of reaſon and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>?</hi> this is faſt and looſe; he that would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rection for reſiſtance is here left upon uncertaintie.</p>
               <p>Let us proceed to <hi>Limited</hi> and <hi>mixed Monarchies.</hi> In ſuch, he tells us, if the Exorbitancies of the Monarch be of leſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not ſtriking at the very being of the Government, they ought to be borne by publique patience, rather then to endanger the being of the State by a Contention betweene the head and the body. <hi>pag.</hi> 17. but if they be ſuch as being ſuffered doe diſſolve the frame of Government, and cannot be redreſſed by petition, then is prevention to be ſought by reſiſtance, <hi>pag.</hi> 18. and 29. Here I muſt firſt challenge the Ingeinuity of this Author, who citing my words <hi>pag.</hi> 49. taken out of my firſt Sect: <hi>(We may and ought to deny obedience to ſuch commands of the Prince as are unlawfull by the Law of God, yea by the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Lawes of the Land)</hi> could give this cenſure upon them, <hi>here he ſayes more then we ſay, yea, more then ſhould be ſaid; it is not univerſally true that we ought:</hi> conſidering, that the caſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111670:21"/>was there put concerning exorbitancies, not of <hi>leſſe moment,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut tending to <hi>the ſubverſion of Religion, Lawes, Liberties,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the queſtion upon it was, whether upon ſuch a caſe might we reſiſt, and the explication of the word <hi>Reſiſt</hi> was into a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of Active obedience, and an uſing of forceable reſiſtance. Now my ſaying was, that to ſuch commands of the Prince we ought to deny obedience, but not uſe forceable reſiſtance; they ſay (as he doth here) we ought alſo forceably to reſiſt; and yet <hi>I ſay more then they ſay.</hi> Secondly, we would know who ſhall be Judge of the ſubverſive Exorb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tances of the Monarch. He grants there can be no Authoritative Judge to determine it, for that would overthrow the Monarchy, <hi>pag.</hi> 17. This is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous, and doth indeed ſufficiently overthrow the conceit of the <hi>Full Anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erer,</hi> placing the finall Reſolution and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this State in the two Houſes. But what then muſt be done? In a limited Monarchy, he tells us, the Fundamentall Lawes muſt judge &amp; pronounce ſentence in every mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for in ſuch a caſe as tranſcends the proviſion of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, people are unbound and in ſtate, as if they had no government, and the ſuperiour Law of Reaſon and Conſcience muſt be Judge; ſo he, <hi>pag.</hi> 18. This is a ready way to Anarchy and confuſion: The people by this have liberty enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of their fundamentall Rights as they pleaſe, and of the Exorbitancies of their Prince, as may be moſt for their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, eſpecially being upon ſuch a caſe (which themſelves may make) unbound and at liberty, as if they had no government. But theſe are fitting grounds for Reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, in mixed Monarchyes, he tells us, the accuſing and wronged ſide muſt make it evident to every mans Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; alſo the appeal muſt be to the <hi>Community,</hi> as if there were no government, and then as every man is convinced in Conſcience, he is bound to give aſſiſtance, ſo, <hi>pag.</hi> 29. Here is good ſtuffe; not altogether ſo bad indeed as we ſee in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of theſe times, for here is no forcing of men to a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, no forceable taking of their eſtates away, but a leaving of them to their Conſciences: yet is this bad enough; for he ſuppoſes it as a thing poſſible, that two. Eſtates may make a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111670:22"/>conſederacy againſt the third, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. therefore ſo oft as they ſhall combine and declare againſt the Monarch, the people are at liberty, <hi>as if there were no government,</hi> and then it ſeemes they have all the power againe in themſelves, which they had at firſt according to theſe mens principles. Alſo in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, ſaith he, <hi>the appeale is to be made to the Community (i.)</hi> the people; which though we have ſeen practiſed at this day in many Remonſtrances, yet I thinke it was never given as a Rule before, it being in it ſelfe moſt unreaſonable and diſadvantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Monarch, for the people will be more ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve their Repreſentatives; and in the conſequence moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous the high way to confuſion, as will more ſully appeare when we come to Reaſons againſt this Reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, we would know, what power there is in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity to make reſiſtance. He tells us, if the Monarch invade the power of the other Eſtates, or run a courſe tending to the diſſolution of the conſtituted frame of Government, they ought to imploy their power to preſerve the State from ruine; for that is the end why they have the power of reſtraint, and of providing for the publique ſafety, ſo pag. 28. but what power ought they to employ? any other then they are expreſly inveſted with by Law? which is a Parliamentary, not Military power, a Legall reſtraining power, not a forceable conſtraint by Armes.</p>
               <p>Yea bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith he, it is not only Lawfull for the other Eſtates to deny obedience to illegall proceedings of the Monarch, as private men may, but it is their duty, and they are bound to prvent diſſolution of the eſtabliſhed frame, pag. 28. He doth not ſay to prevent it by Armes, but he meanes ſo by oppoſing their duty of prevention, to the duty of private men in den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all of obedience. But we muſt conſider that the duty of pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e men is concerned when the Lawes come to execution, the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the publique States is ſeen, when the making or aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Lawes is ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en in hand; alſo we muſt conſider that it is not the abuſe of power in the execution of Law that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves the eſtabliſhed frame, but the aboliſhing of old and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of new Lawes; whereupon we ſay, that the perſons that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111670:22"/>make up thoſe ſtates taken out of their Aſſembly or Parliament, are but private men, and then have no more power to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>illegall proceedings of the Monarch,</hi> then as private men by deniall of active obedience; in their Aſſembly or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, they have power of reſtraint by deniall or conſenting, to prevent diſſolution of the frame of Government, &amp; indeed if they uſe that Legall reſtraining power, as they are bound in duty to doe, the Monarch cannot alter the eſtabliſhed frame; he may perchance make ſome actuall invaſions upon their Rights and Liberties (as they may often upon his Right and Prerogative) and runne a courſe in it ſelfe tending to ſubverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alter the frame or change the Lawes without their conſent he cannot; and whether it be not better that ſuch arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary illegall Acts of a Monarch (which are tranſient and ſixe no new frame of Government) ſhould not for ſome time be borne with, then to ſeek remedy againſt them, by a Civill warre or contention of the body againſt the head, will appeare more fully when we come to Reaſons againſt ſuch Reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>I will conclude the examination of this part of his diſcourſe, with the proof of this aſſertion; that Limitations and mixtures in Monarchy, doe not imply a forceable conſtraining power in Subjects (as he ſuppoſeth) for the preventing of the diſſolution of the eſtabliſhed Government, but only a Legall reſtraining power, as was even now inſinuated: Firſt ſuch a power muſt be in them by reſervation, and then it muſt be expreſſe in the conſtitution of the Government, and in the Covenant twixt the Monarch and the People. But then, I muſt ſay, I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve but ſuch a condition is unlawfull and unreaſonable, againſt the order of Government, which will have the ſoveraign power ſecured, unprofitable for King and People, a ſeminary of Iealouſies and Seditions; we need not ſpend time about this, for it is confeſſed that in the conſtitution of this our govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (to which all the contention relates) there is no Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or Law expreſly enableing Subjects with ſuch power of Armes. This Author acknowledges, pag. 63. that when the Houſes by an Ordinance aſſume the Armes, wherewith the King is entruſted, and doe performe the Kings truſt, ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111670:23"/>is not <hi>formally Legall (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.)</hi> there is no expreſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution for it: yet is it <hi>Eminently Legall,</hi> juſtified by the intent of the Architects of this Government, when for theſe uſes they committed the Armes to the King; ſo he.</p>
               <p>Secondly, therefore let us ſee, whether it followes by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication upon the <hi>Limiting</hi> and <hi>Mixing</hi> of Monarchy. It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed, that an <hi>Abſolute</hi> Monarch is free from all forceable conſtraint by Armes, and ſo farre forth as he is abſolute, from all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egall reſtraint of poſitive conſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utions; now in Limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and mixture there is only ſought a Legall reſtraint upon the power of the Monarch; if any more were ſought or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, it muſt follow, either from the Nature of Limitation, or from the danger and inconveniencies of exorbitancy of the <hi>Limited</hi> Monarch, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the conſent and intention of the People chooſing the Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arch.</p>
               <p>But firſt, Limitation cannot inferre it, for an abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch is limited alſo, not by civill compact indeed, but by the Law of God, of Nature and Nations, which he cannot juſtly tranſgreſſe; if therefore an abſolute Monarch, being exorbitant beyond his bounds, which the higheſt Lawes have ſet him, may not be reſiſted, how ſhall we think a limited Monarch may, for tranſgreſſing the bounds ſet him by civ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll agreement?</p>
               <p>Secondly, the inconveniencies of exorbitancy in Limited and mixed Monarchie cannot inferr a power of reſiſtance by Armes, becauſe the inconveniencies and evills (which are pretended as cauſes of reſiſtance in ſuch Monarchies) are the ſame in Abſolute; for <hi>Limitations</hi> and <hi>Mixtures,</hi> are but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arres and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>itie, againſt injuſtice, cruelty and oppreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, which are exorbitances alſo in abſolute Monarchies, and evills that bring as much detriment and ſuffering to the Subject, as they doe in Limited Monarchyes; as for example, The imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſing of Taxes, if it be done when neceſſity requires not, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> very un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qually in regard of Perſons and eſtates, it is an injury and grievance even in an Abſolute Monarchy; only when neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty calls for ſuch L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vies of Money, the Monarch (that is of a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited</hi> and <hi>Mixed</hi> condition) is bound to take in the conſent of others, to which the Abſolute Monarch is nor bound. So in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111670:23"/>Tryalls for Life and Eſtate, an unjuſt ſentence is an oppreſſion in Abſolute as well as Limited Monarchy, only the limited or Mixed Monarch is bond to paſſe ſentence upon the verdict of twelve men, or the like, the Abſolute is not. Suppoſe then a Prince in ſuch a Limited or Mixed Monarchy ſhould, when ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity doth truly require, impoſe taxes, lay them equally, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend them faithfully; and in tryalls for Life or Eſtate, ſhould give right judgement without the verdictof twelve men, and in other poynts ſhould rule moſt juſtly, though not according to forme, unto which he is limited by poſitive Law; here would be the main Rule of Government obſerved, juſtice, and the end of Government (for which thoſe limits and Civill bounds were ſet him) obtained, peace and well-fare of the People; Will you then have ſuch a Prince reſiſted by Armes, and the Kigndome embroyled in Civil Warre, becauſe he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved not the forme, when he gives you the ſubſtance? Yea but this would be an ill procedent and very dangerous; true, there is danger, but no preſent evill; and what are the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or evill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feared? Cruelty, Oppreſſion, which other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might uſe, ſhould they have ſuch liberty; true, but theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills, when they are are evills in Abſolute Monarchies, and for them reſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance is not to be uſed there.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the conſent and intention of the people chooſing the Monarch cannot inferre: that a Limited Monarch may be reſiſted by Armes. This conſent and intention of the People is made by theſe men, not only the Ordinary meane of con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Power, but the very Meaſure of the Power it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elfe, and the Barre or inlet of reſiſtance; for by that conſent is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the people give what power they pleaſe, and reſerve what they will. To which I ſay. 1. That the conſent of the people, may be the mean of deſigning the perſon, and of ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubjection to him, who elſe could not challenge it, more then another man; alſo a mean of limiting that power in the exerciſe of it, according to agreement or procurement: but it is not the meaſure of the power it ſelfe, which in ſuch a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is given of God to all Soveraignes, and is not according to the peoples will reſiſtible or irreſiſtible but according to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111670:24"/>will of God above reſiſtance; forſeeing that people have not of themſelves, out of government, the main power, the power of life and death, how can they give it either for government, or reſerve it for reſiſtance?</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the intention of the People, in procuring Limitations of the Monarch's power, is, that they may be un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der a moderate uſe of the power; and what's their ſecurity for that? thoſe limitations which the Monarch agrees upon Oath to obſerve; now this cannot infere reſiſtance here, more then in abſolute Monarchies: for when a people leaves a Monarch Abſolute truſting to his prudence and moderation, they doe not intend he ſhould oppreſſe them; yet is it granted, ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention cannot enable them to reſiſt, in caſe he doe oppreſſe them. Now in agreeing for Limitations and ſet rules of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they gain a farther ſecurity of ſuch moderate uſe of the power according to thoſe limitations; for the obſerving of which, they have a tye upon their Monarch, not from a power of forceable reſiſtance in themſelves to conſtrain him by Armes if he exorbitate, but from His Oath or Covenant, and Gods vengeance thereupon, if he falſify it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If the Architects (as this Author ſpeaks) of a limited or mixed Monarchy, that is, the people ſetting up ſuch a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch over them, did intend, that the ſtates joyned with the Monarch ſhould aſſume the Armes of the Kingdome to reſtrain his Exorbitancies, ſurely they would not have left it in his power to diſſolve them, and ſo make all ſuch power ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. It appeares therefore, that by ſuch mixtures and limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons no more can be inferred, then a Legall or morall reſtraint upon the power of the Monarch. And all this, that hath been ſpoken againſt the power of Reſiſtance or aſſuming the Armes of the Kingdome, inferred from the <hi>Limited</hi> condition of the Monarch, as it is good and concluſive in Monarchies originally limited, ſo is it much more in Monarchies, that have afterward received thoſe Limitations and Mixtures, upon which this power of reſiſtance and aſſuming the Armes of the Kingdome is inferred; as it appeares this Monarchy has done. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude here, as I did premiſe in the ſecond Section,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111670:24"/>
                  <hi>Where the Prince ſtands ſupream, und next to God, above all the People, there Subjects may not by force of armes reſiſt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he be exorbitant in the exerciſe and uſe of his Power to the invaſion of ſuch Rights and Priviledges, as they enjoy by first compact or after procurement.</hi> And this being cleared already from thoſe ſhadowes of reaſons (which could be pretended againſt it from the ſeverall kinds of Monarchy) will farther ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that, which ſhall be ſaid out of <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>A Refutation of His Anſwer, that firſt ſtyled himſelfe the Author of the</hi> Fuller Anſwer.</head>
               <p>ALthough the ſubſtance of his diſcourſe is already anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, by that which hath been ſaid concerning <hi>Mixture</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> againſt the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> yet becauſe he is extremely confident, and many times unfaithfull in his Reply's, I will briefly touch upon ſuch paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as may ſeem moſt materiall, or any way availeable to abuſe the unwary Reader.</p>
               <p>It is his manner to gaine ſeeming advantages upon his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary by his own willfull miſtakings; as in his Anſwer to the Preface; that which was ſpoken of ſome particular Members, the Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aivers of this Revolt and Rebellion, is by him taken, and given out againe to the Reader, as ſpoken of all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Houſes, that have by the cunning of thoſe Few been drawne to Vote any thing in order to this Rebellion. Alſo, what was ſpoken of private houſes, where thoſe few Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers held their cloſe meetings <hi>(that it was Gods great forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, thoſe houſes did not breake downe, where the Conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been oft held for the direction of theſe wayes)</hi> he renders as ſpoken of the Houſes, where the Parliament ſits &amp; Conſults. But let them all, that have been Leaders or followers in theſe perverſe wayes, looke to it, and conſider, how much they are concerned in that place of <hi>Eſay,</hi> to which the alluſion there was made; for every one that lookes neerly upon it, (<hi>Eſa.</hi> 30. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13.) will eaſily ſee, (what ever application
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111670:25"/>this Author makes of it) who they are, that have ſilenced their Orthodoxe, and not long agoe admired Teachers, ſuffering none to ſpeake <hi>right things,</hi> but <hi>ſmooth;</hi> ſuch new unheard off doctrines as pleaſe them; who they are that doe <hi>truſt in oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and perverſenes, and doe ſtay thereon</hi> having no other way to uphold this Rebellion, but by perverſe obſtinacy, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble injuſtice exerciſed upon ſuch, as have not yet caſt off all Conſcience of <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>right,</hi> or cauſed the feare of <hi>the Holy one of Iſrael to ceaſe from before them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would adviſe this Anſwere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to looke upon two places more of <hi>Eſay,</hi> cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. v. 4. where they that have been oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhall ſay of <hi>Babylon, how hath the Golden City ceaſed?</hi> and v. 10. <hi>art thou become weake as we, art thou he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> like unto us?</hi> and <hi>cap.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 8. where he may find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> threatned againſt <hi>Tyre, the Crowning City, whoſe Merchants are Princes,</hi> and then I would deſire him to conſider, whether he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not cauſe to reflect upon that <hi>Golden, Crowning City,</hi> wherein he lives.</p>
               <p>In his ſecond Section alſo, he would ſeeme to gaine advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages upon his Adverſary, by faſtning upon him ſeverall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions or <hi>peices of non-ſence,</hi> as he calls them; but they are indeed ſo many wilfull or groſſe miſtakes of his owne. The firſt he thus delivers, as in my word, <hi>It's better to be under the Arbitrary Government of One, that challenges not obedience but according to Law:</hi> ſo he repeates them and then deſcants, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary government,</hi> and yet <hi>according to Law.</hi> But the words run thus in my <hi>Reply; Every man will thinke it more reaſonable to be under the Arbitrary government of One then of many: nay, under the government of One, that challenges not obedience as due, but according to Law, then of Many whoſe commands are Law unto us, as this Anſwerer makes them.</hi> In which the Compariſon, as any man may ſee, is double, firſt between the Arbitrary government of One, and of many; then a <hi>fortiori,</hi> betweene the Legall government of One, and arbitrary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Many.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Contradiction he thus expreſſes. <hi>The D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to ſatisfy Conſcience, that the Parliament hath not this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111670:25"/>power, and yet ſaith, he does not undertake to ſet down, what power the Parliament hath.</hi> 'Tis true the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> did undertake the firſt, and might doe it without undertaking to <hi>ſet downe the extent of the power and priviledges of the Houſes;</hi> tho e were the words, and where is the Contradiction? This Anſwerer may undertake to ſhew, the King has not ſuch or ſuch a power (as to make Lawes himſelfe, or the like) yet will not I hope, undertake to ſet downe the extent of the Kings power and Prerogative; it was the very Inſtance there uſed, and the Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of it was, ſo <hi>may we without offence conclude of the two Houſes, that they have not ſuch a power by the firſt conſtitation of this Government, &amp;c.</hi> A particular Negative may be clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by him, that cannot ſhew the extent of the Vniverſall Affirmative.</p>
               <p>A third Contradiction or Nonſence he has found in theſe words. <hi>This Coordination is but to ſome Act or exerciſe of the ſupream Power, not in the power it ſelfe.</hi> I acknowledge the words, and doe thanke him, that he tooke notice of them for their ſakes, who have miſtaken that part of my Reply, as if I granted a Coordination of Subjects with His Majeſty in the ſupream power but then I muſt blame his ignorance. that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>recontile this</hi> (as he ſpeakes) <hi>to any truce of Sence;</hi> for they that have written of Government and Policy, could have told him, that the concurrence and conſent of ſuch or ſuch perſons, required to ſome Acts of the ſupreame power, doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes argue a communication of the Power; and the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>Monarchy</hi> doth every where teach him to make a wide difference betweene the <hi>Power</hi> and the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of it. Out of this miſtake and ignorance of diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Power</hi> it ſelfe and the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of the Power, he runs away with it as a thing granted, that the Houſes are coor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate with His Majeſty in the very Supremacy of Power, ſo farre as the Legiſlative and ordaining goes, which is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, and that it remaines for him only to prove, they are coord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with His Majeſty in the other Act of power, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſyes, appointing Officers, Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> undertakes in his fourth Section, where we ſhall m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:111670:26"/>him. It was the worke of my third Section to ſpeake of the beginnings of Government in this Land, and to ſhew they were inconſiſtent with his Conceit of the making of the firſt King, and the firſt Coalition of Government, as he call'd it. To which after ſome trifeling, he replyes in his third Section, <hi>pag.</hi> 17. If the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> thinkes <hi>the uncertainties of the Britiſh or Saxon Conſtitutions not fit to ſatisfy Conſcience</hi> (as he ſpeakes) <hi>how being uncertaine, can he ſatisfy Conſcience (which is the title of his Boooke) that thoſe Conſtitutions were not ſuch?</hi> ſo he. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If thoſe Conſtitutions be uncertaine, it ſatisfyes Conſcience that it can have no warrant from them, which was the task of that book. 2, The uncertainties, which I ſaid he runne Conſcience upon, were in ſeeking the firſt King before the Saxons, for if we go no higher for the beginning of this Engliſh government (as indeed we ſhould not) we have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly enough to ſatisfy Conſcience, that this Government was not ſuch in the firſt conſtitution, as this Anſwerer would make us believe.</p>
               <p>But ſee him comming a pegge lower in the very next words. <hi>'Tis enough that the Conſtitution of our preſent Government was ſuch, at leaſt from the beginning of it's being ſuch; that by the ſame conſent of the people, whereby the firſt</hi> ſuch King <hi>was made, His Majeſty, that now is, becomes</hi> ſuch a King, <hi>that the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſtate, which firſt contrived the Government (however ſooner or leter) ſuch as now it is, remaines ſtill ſpecifically the ſame in that, which the law places it in,</hi> the Councell of the Land <hi>to actuate and apply it.</hi> Anſwer, Nothing can be truer, then that the government was <hi>ſuch</hi> from the time, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to be <hi>ſuch,</hi> but he bore us in hand before, that it was <hi>ſuch</hi> from the very firſt beginning of the Monarchy. &amp; ſo he ought to prove it to be; for elſe it muſt become <hi>ſuch</hi> by the conſent of the King in being, condeſcending from unlimited condition to a more moderate way of Government by ſeverall fixed laws; as was ſhewed above, when we ſpoke of <hi>Limitations</hi> and <hi>Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> Sect. 3. but can we think that while there was a King in being, the <hi>Councell of the Land</hi> had power to contrive and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the frame of this Government, and that in a way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiciall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111670:26"/>to the King, as this Anſwerer would make it?</p>
               <p>But he goes on. <hi>The truth is, the Doctor deales with us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in at Papiſts uſually doe with Proteſtants, if they cannot name the particular Raigne and yeere when ſuch a Doctrine tooke it's first riſe, however palpable it now be, we muſt believe there was no change at all: ſo if it be not aſſigned when ſuch or ſuch a part of the Governments Conſtitution began, however euident it be that it muſt have a beginning, becauſe a being, we muſt confeſſe it to have no beginning at all.</hi> No Sir, the Doctor deales with you as Proteſtants doe with Papiſts upon that point; for as they ſhew the Doctrine of the Romiſh Church was not from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and becauſe the yeere and age when every error crept in cannot be named, do thereupon conclude certainly, That thoſe errours came not in at once but by degrees: ſo we require not the particular Raign and yeer when each conſtitution came in, but doe ſhew that the Government was not ſuch from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and becauſe the time cannot be ſhewn, when the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations and Conſtitutions came in, that made it ſuch, we thereupon conclude, the Government did not become ſuch at once, but by degrees, and by the after Condeſcent of Pious Princes. To that which was alledged out of the Preamble of a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atute, 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. His poore ſhifts are, 1. That it is a piece of a preamble, not part of the Statute. Anſwer. What then? it ſpeakes never a whit the leſſe truth, nor ha's it the leſſe authority, but (which is more) ſpeakes an anciently ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed truth alwaies Confeſſed, and evident in <hi>Chronicles</hi> and <hi>Hiſtories, that this is an Empire, Governed by one Supreame Head, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. That the Title ſpeakes it an Act againſt appeales to <hi>Rome. Anſwer.</hi> It matters not what the occaſion was, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what it poſitively ſpeakes touching the Kings Supremacy and Headſhip. So they miſerably ſhift off the obligation, which the Oath of <hi>Supremacy</hi> ha's caſt upon them, as if the Kings <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> were aſſerted in it, in oppoſition to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> not in relation to the whole body politique; that if they deny the <hi>Popes Supremacy,</hi> they thinke they ſatisfie the Oath,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111670:27"/>what Subjects ſoever they joyne with His Majeſty in the very <hi>Supremacy</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>So in the third place he ſaith; that thoſe words in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute: <hi>To whom a body politique compact of all ſorts and degrees of peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, of the Spiritualty and Temporalty are bounden, &amp;c.</hi> cannot properly be meant of the Parliament, but of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome at large. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> If of the Kingdome at large, then is it true alſo of their Repreſentatives, if of the Kingdome in it's defuſive body, then of it's Collective. But I turne him over to the Authour of the Treatiſe of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> who ſufficiently Confutes this idle aſſertion, and doth ſhew the Lords and Commons in their houſes conjunctim are ſubjects, and the King their Head. And this is enough for his third Section.</p>
               <p>In his fourth Section, he endeavours to prove, the Houſes are Coordinate with His Majeſty in all other Acts of Supreme power, as the Calling of Aſſemblies, holding Treaties, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Embaſſies, appointing Judges, &amp;c. His proofe is firſt by reaſon, becauſe they are Coordinate with him in the Supream power of making lawes, which is the principall, and higher Cauſe to the Calling of Aſſemblies, Treaties, &amp;c. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> This he takes for granted, that they are Coordinate with His Majeſty in the Supream power of Ordaining, or making laws, which doth proceed (as I noted above upon his ſecond Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) from his miſtake or ignorance in not diſtinguiſhing the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi> of the power, and the <hi>Power</hi> it ſelfe, for they may concur to that, and yet not have ſhare in this.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He would prove it by Records, from <hi>pag.</hi> 22. to 27. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In theſe we muſt truſt his honeſty, which we finde not very faithfull in repeating the words of the booke he undertakes to confute. 2. Were they truely alledged, they yeeld but an Argument <hi>a facto ad Ius,</hi> Parliaments have done this or that, therefore they have right to doe ſo; it will be a bad argument in the next age to conclude any thing right and juſt, becauſe it was ſo ordained by the Houſes of this laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Though ſome particulars cited by Him, might of right belong to them, yet how doth it prove, it was ſo originally and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111670:27"/>fundamentally, and not by after condeſcent of the Prince, as we find many immunities, rights, and liberties of the Subject to be? But for theſe Records he is beholden to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Pryn's</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, who is ſaid to be the Author of that booke, which beares this title, <hi>The Soveraigne power of Parliaments,</hi> or <hi>the treachery and diſloyalty of Papiſts to their Soveraigne;</hi> To their Soveraigne? that is, to the two Houſes, by the former part of the title — let him take heed, he proves them not good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. But what ſhall we make of it? 'tis certaine, he fetches his teſtimonies from times of Popery, ſhewing what power Parliaments then have aſſumed and uſed againſt the <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> if he will give us leave to ſtyle the King ſo; but how he ſhould thereby ſhew the diſloyalty of Papiſts, and yet prove the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> power</hi> of Popiſh Parliaments, I cannot ſee, nor is it greatly materiall; for let all his inſtances be true, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords faithfully alleadged, yet will the argument be inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that from them ſhall conclude the <hi>Soveraigne power</hi> of Parliaments.</p>
               <p>After his Records, this <hi>Anſwerer</hi> enters a diſcourſe of his owne, touching the <hi>Mixture</hi> of this Government. That which concernes me in it, is <hi>pag.</hi> 28. The Dr in his former Treatiſe ſpeakes of the excellent <hi>temper</hi> of the three Eſtates, and in his Reply acknowledges them as <hi>Fundamentals of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> and if fundamentalls, how not all alike principall, and ſupream, he has not ſhewed in his Reply though provoked thereto; ſo he. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. The D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> did not any where call them <hi>Fundamentals of Government,</hi> but acknowledged the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution was <hi>fundamentall,</hi> that provided that <hi>Temper,</hi> and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Houſes that power which they have; this his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake I told him of in my Reply, <hi>pag.</hi> 16. and ſhewed him the abſurdity it leades him into, by Concluding thence, that the Houſes are alike Principall or Supreme with His Majeſty; an excellent argument to provoke an Adverſary upon; but this Anſwerer ſeemes to have made his Reply to one Section, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had read the next, and when he was come to that, to forget what he had read or writ before.</p>
               <p>In like manner he tells us preſently after, that he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111670:28"/>that the Finall Declaration and Reſolution muſt remaine beyond all further debate in the <hi>Councell</hi> of the Kingdome, which by its <hi>number, truſt, intereſt,</hi> is onely fit to manage it: to all which the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> hath not vouchſafed to ſay any thing, but that it wholly places the Supremacy in the two Houſes, ſo he, <hi>pag.</hi> 31. <hi>Anſw.</hi> If nothing elſe had been ſaid, it had been enough, and ſo the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that to place ſuch a finall Reſolution and declarative Judgement in the two Houſes, doth make them ſupreame, and this no Monarchy; but there was more ſaid, even the better part of three Sections was ſpent againſt that finall declarative judgement and Supply, which he places in the two Houſes, &amp; againſt his perſwaſions from their Intereſts, Number, Truſt; ſhewing, how poſſible it is for them to leſſen their number, to neglect their <hi>truſt,</hi> to make the private Intereſt devoure the publique; I need ſay no more, theſe times ſpeake ſufficiently — But it ſeemes this Anſwerer (as I ſaid above) wrote downe this, before he had throughly read thoſe Sections, and when he came to them, either had forgot, that he had ſaid, <hi>the Dr. vouchſafed to ſay nothing to his particulars;</hi> or elſe purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make it ſeeme ſo, by anſwering nothing himſelfe to that which the Dr. had ſaid, touching that finall declarative Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſupply, which he places in the Houſes.</p>
               <p>But for this mixture of three Eſtates in the Supremacy of power, he has found a new Argument in the Kings Anſwer to the 19. Propoſitions; wherein His Majeſty grants, <hi>That the Lords being truſted with a Iudicatory Power are an Excellent Skreene betwixt Prince and people — and that the power le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally placed in the two Houſes, is more then enough to reſtraine Tyranny.</hi> Upon this he makes a long deſcant, and propounds ſixe Quere's. I will for brevity's ſake, without any wrong to Him that propoſes them, reduce them to theſe two. 1. for the <hi>Iudicatory power;</hi> How can ſuch be in the Houſes, and yet not the declarative power of Law? For this, as before, I muſt turne him over to the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> who will aske him, how can ſuch a finall declarative power be in the Houſes, and yet this be a Monarchy and the King Supream?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111670:28"/>and I muſt farther aske him, why doth he not place the finall Judgement onely in the Lords houſe, ſeeing that Judicatory power is only in that, &amp; not in the Houſe of Commons. 2. For the power of Armes; If the Houſes have not ſuch a power, how have they a <hi>power more then ſufficient to reſtraine Tyranny?</hi> let the Dr. fairely reſolve the Anſwerer in theſe plaine inferences out of His Majeſties words, <hi>&amp; erit mihi magnus Apollo,</hi> ſo he.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I muſt firſt tell him, <hi>Apollo</hi> was more honoured for his Art, then for his bow, for his Rules of healing, then force of wounding; ſo the morall reſtraints of Rules, &amp; limiting Laws, and the obligation of an Oath, are more reaſonable and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull for keeping the will of the Monarch within bounds, then the forcible conſtraint of Subjects Armes. But this Anſwerer thinks there can be no ſufficient ſecurity for the people againſt the Tyranny of their Prince, unleſſe they have him faſt bound; is the tye of eſtabliſhed Law nothing? the band of a Sacred oath nothing to reſtraine him, unleſſe his Subjects have the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering power? God himſelfe thought leſſe means of reſtraint ſufficient for ſuch ſecurity, as he was content his people ſhould have under the <hi>Iraelitiſh</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Government; why ſhould not greater be held ſufficient for people under a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Monarch?</p>
               <p>Againe, when it was proved, that the Members of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were Subjects <hi>conjunctim,</hi> from their owne addreſſes to His Majeſty, wherein they ſtyle themſelves his Loyall Subjects: this Anſwerer replyes unto it, pag. 39. <hi>How weake is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from formes of addreſſes in words againſt a reall Right?</hi> what Right? to the Supremacy? how reall that is, appears by all that has been ſaid: but we may here returne him his owne Anſwer, to his inference from His Majeſties words, <hi>how weake is the argument from formes of words againſt a reall right!</hi> againſt His knowne Supremacy and Headſhip? Nay, how unequall is it to take ſuch large and gracious Expreſſions, iſſuing from the conſcience of his owne intentions and deſires altogether averſe from tyranny, and ſtretch them on the rack of finiſter Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to make them ſpeake to his diſadvantage? for indeed no other power is granted to be in the Houſes to reſtraine Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111670:29"/>then a Legall, Morall, Parliamentary power, not forceable and military. See above towards the end of the fourth Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where theſe and other. Expreſſions of His Majeſty were objected and vindicated.</p>
               <p>Now to his fifth Section: It was his Rule, <hi>Coordinates doe ſupply one the others failings;</hi> and thereupon he inferred, <hi>If the King refuſe, the Lords and Commons may ſupply.</hi> This was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted upon him in my Reply: If the Commons ſtand out and refuſe, then may the King and Lords by his rule of Coordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſupply, and command all. He anſwers, <hi>No qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtion they may ſupply, as farre as their repreſentation and truſt reaches, that is for themſelves, not for the Commons of</hi> England <hi>whom they doe not repreſent. Anſw.</hi> Doth this man know or heed what he ſaith? doth not he make the ſafety of the Kingdome the Cauſe and end of ſuch <hi>ſupply,</hi> when one of the Coordinates ſtand out? and now he tells us the King and Lords may ſupply for themſelves <hi>(i. e.)</hi> they may ſave themſelves, if they can, but they have nothing to doe with the Commons, whom they doe not repreſent: but can the ſafety of the Kingdome be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for by this <hi>ſupply,</hi> unleſſe they alſo be commanded by the Coordinate parts, which are to make the ſupply? and will he upon better thought's deny, that in order to that end (the ſafety of the Kingdome) the King and Lords alſo are entruſted for the whole people of England?</p>
               <p>Againe, this ſupply cannot be effectuall without a <hi>Iudicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power,</hi> but that power we find onely in the Lords, not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons houſe, as he himſelfe cited it above out of the Kings words; well then, muſt they exerciſe this <hi>Judicatory power</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves only, and not upon thoſe that the Commons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent? or can the Commons by themſelves ſupply? that's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own rule of Coordination: but if he will forget that, us he does, yet will he not thinke, they can make the ſupply without a <hi>Judicatory power.</hi> I will adde to this, what he has at the very end of this Sect. where we finde him as conſiderate as before: In order to his former rule, <hi>Coordinates ſupply one anothers failings,</hi> he had ſaid in his firſt Treatiſe, that he won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, we cannot ſee the King is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis minor,</hi> when as we
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:111670:29"/>may <hi>eaſily reckon, that of three, one is leſſe then all three.</hi> Upon this I call'd him again to his reckoning, telling him that, if the King and Lords concurre and the Commons refuſe, it is eaſy to reckon that of <hi>three one is leſſe then two,</hi> repeating his words ſo, not for any advantage, but meerly to make him ſpeake ſenſe; he becauſe he cannot anſwer the retortion, complaines of wilfull and groſſe miſtake of his words, which were, ſaith he, <hi>that of three one is leſſe then all three</hi> (i. e.) <hi>a part then the whole.</hi> But is that your meaning of <hi>Rex eſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis minor</hi> (i. e.) the King alone is leſſe then the King, Lords and Commons toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? who cannot ſee that the Compariſon is between the King and the other two? and that in your rule of three Coordinates, if one refuſe, there remaines but two to make the ſupply; and that thereupon you ſhould have ſaid (if you would ſpeake ſence) that <hi>of three one is leſſe then two?</hi> I have heard Children, when their diſorderly Babies have beene taken from them and preſently returned them again in frame and order, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe they received them not, as they parted with them; ſo doth this Anſwerer of the putting his words into ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Let us now ſee, how in the ſame Section he anſwers for the Kings danger at <hi>Keinton</hi> Battell. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the making of Lawes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the King preſence or abſence alters not the caſe, ſo in the executing of the Lawes againſt Delinquents, the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence can no more hinder then his command.— Anſw.</hi> His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or abſence does not indeed in the making Lawes, but his Conſent is all, which he may give either preſent or abſent, but will you for the <hi>Executing of the Lawes</hi> take armes without his conſent, and uſe them too againſt him perſonally preſent? or wil you ſay, that your giving him battell at <hi>Keinton,</hi> was an <hi>executing of the Lawes againſt Delinquents?</hi> produce your Law that enables you to ſuch a proceeding againſt your pretended delinquents. <hi>Nor were the hands of the Parliaments Army lifted up againſt the King more then Davids (whom the Doctor cites) who reſiſted his and the kings enemies, though about the kings perſon. ibid.</hi> Anſ. It doth not appeare where <hi>David</hi> did make that reſiſtance; but it is the unhappineſſe of theſe men to ground all their reſiſtance upon falſe ſuppoſitions; firſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111670:30"/>they ſuppoſe <hi>David</hi> would have done it, then they poſitively ſet downe, that he did it, thence they conclude they may doe it, and acccordingly have done it, and much more.</p>
               <p>The reſt of this Section he thought good (neglecting what was rationall in mine) to ſpend in naming Delinquents in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> for whoſe apprehenſion and the bringing of them to Juſtice, the Parliament tooke Armes. <hi>Anſw.</hi> All thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Delinquents followed their putting of armed men into <hi>Hull,</hi> their ſeizing the Magazine there, their denying the King enterance, their denying eo bring Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and in theſe, if any Delinquents were detained and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected from their juſtice, as he complaines, he may read the carſe of it: But theſe are matters of Fact, we are now upon the point of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>In his ſixt Section, he altogether neglects the caſes, which were put him, upon his placing the finall reſolution of this States judgement in the two Houſes, and onely faſtens upon that, which was ſpoken occaſionally concerning Conqueſt. Firſt, for his Anſwer touching the <hi>Ammonites</hi> ſubdued by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, That Abrahams poſterity was entituled to their Land by God, Gen.</hi> 13.14. I would deſire him to looke into, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.4. (where the Lord gives <hi>Moſes</hi> a ſight of that promiſed Land, ſaying. <hi>This is the Land which I ſware to Abraham, &amp;c</hi>) and to examine, whether he can find the Land of the <hi>Ammonites</hi> in that proſpect. And ſurely if the <hi>Ammonites</hi> had been of the Inhabitants of that Land, <hi>David</hi> would not have held league and frienſhip with them, as we ſee he does, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Next for <hi>Davids</hi> ſubduing of <hi>Edom,</hi> he anſwers, <hi>The Doctor himſelfe confeſſeth they revolted from Judah.</hi> What then? had they been before under <hi>Iudah,</hi> and upon their Revolt ſubdued by <hi>David,</hi> then indeed it had been not a Conqueſt but a Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but the Doctor confeſſes they revolted from <hi>Iehoram</hi> Ring of <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 21. therefore they were juſtly ſubdued or reduced (that muſt be his inference) by <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. doth he know what he ſaith? But God had given Iſrael (ſaith he) a ſpeciall promiſe for it too, <hi>over Edom will I caſt my ſhooe. Pſal.</hi> 60.8. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Pſalme was made upon that very
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:111670:30"/>expedition in which <hi>Edom</hi> was ſubdued, as appeares by the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of it; and were thoſe words ſpoken by the Spirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yet doe they not make a grant, but only ſpeak the ſucceſſe of that enterpriſe, which then was undertaken.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nor had the Romans any right over Iudaea by Conqueſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but by conſent of the People Conquered; without which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all his</hi> Momenta temporum, <hi>(he speaks of) to make a right or title, are like thoſe Moments of the Papiſts Antiquitie to make a Truth.</hi> Anſ. We finde the <hi>Iewes</hi> confederate with the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 8. and not long after, their Subjects, brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by <hi>Pompey:</hi> we cannot think they changed their condition willingly, but that their conſent was forced by the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; Conqueſt then wil eaſily command that, which will give it Title in theſe mens opinion: And though no antiquity can make falſhood Truth, yet are there <hi>Momenta temporum,</hi> when providence (which tranſlates Kingdomes and can give Title to the Conquerour) doth diſcover it ſelfe; and then the Conquered People ought to conſent to, and receive the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which the Conquerour ſettles among them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove at the end of the third Sect. where the Title of Conqueſt is examined.</p>
               <p>There is nothing in his ſeventh Sect. worthy of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders patience in hearing it refuted; onely hee makes ſhew of ſome Statutes, which truly I could not find, nor was there cauſe why I ſhould beſtow much time in ſeeking them, for a litle <hi>Logick</hi> will ſerve to diſcerne, that the words, he cites out of them, will not inferre any concluſions prejudiciall to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary.</p>
               <p>His laſt and eight Section concernes Scripture; he mutters ſome thing in it, concerning <hi>Davids</hi> fighting againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> and the abſoluteneſſe of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Kings; which ſhall be diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and largely conſidered in my next Section. And for the new Teſtament, he turnes his Reader over to the interpretation which the <hi>Reverend and learned Divines</hi> having given on the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and which he ſo farre magnifies, that he beelieves the Doctor will not reply in haſte; ſo he concluds his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111670:31"/>booke, and he ſhall ſee he had cauſe ſo to believe, when we come to the conſideration of that place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>Places of Scripture out of the Old Teſtament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw wee come to the examination of what is alleadged out of Scripture in this cauſe, whereby it will appeare, that there can be no warrant derived thence for reſiſtance, but that the Kings, we read of there, were ſuch as might not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, and that Gods people were alwayes under ſuch. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Old Teſtament, and will be very briefe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding only what is Materiall.</p>
               <p>This has beene heretofore clearly proved by theſe two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments eſpecially: 1. Becauſe the Inſtitution of the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> kingdome was ſuch, as doth plainly exclude reſiſtance. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo many Prophets, bitterly reproving thoſe wicked Kings for ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciſion of Religion and Juſtice, did never call upon the Elders of the people for this duty of reſiſtance. I ſhall open the firſt, and enforce it alittle more, and then anſwer what is brought againſt either.</p>
               <p>In the firſt of <hi>Sam. c.</hi> 8 we have the inſtitution of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; where <hi>Samuel</hi> is commanded to tell the people, <hi>Ius Regis</hi> the manner of the King v. 11. <hi>He will take your ſonnes.— your daughters—your field, &amp;c. And yee ſhall cry out in that day &amp;c.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, you deſire a King, and doe not conſider what power you put your ſelves under, ſuch an one, as if he command you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d yours at pleaſure, you muſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently endure; this is the meaning of <hi>Ius Regis,</hi> which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyet not a <hi>Right</hi> of doing ſuch unjuſt Acts, but a <hi>Security</hi> from reſiſtance and force if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oes them. <hi>Moſes</hi> did ſhew the right and Manner of the King, what he ſhould juſtly doe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>Samuel</hi> the right of the King, not in doing, but in being ſecure from the peoples force, if he did unjuſtly: <hi>Moſes</hi> admoniſheth the King of his duty, ſhewing what a good king ought to doe. <hi>Samuel</hi> endeavouring to diſſwade the People, ſhewes what they muſt patiently ſuffer from evill kings.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:111670:31"/>
               <p>Many Authors might be alleadged (if need were) for this meaning of <hi>Ius Regis,</hi> I will name one without exception, <hi>Calvin</hi> in his Comment upon the place, and in his <hi>Inſtitutions:</hi> He ſpeaks to this purpoſe; <hi>Samuel,</hi> when he would ſhew the People what great things they ſhould ſuffer under Kings, tells them, this ſhall be <hi>Ius Regis</hi> the manner of the King, <hi>He ſhall take your Sonnes, &amp;c.</hi> not that their Kings could doe ſo <hi>Iure</hi> juſtly, for the Law did teach them all moderation and juſtice, <hi>ſedjus in populum vocabatur, cui parere ipſi neceſſe eſſet, nec ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtere liceret,</hi> ſo he, <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>nu.</hi> 26. And in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the place, he doth ſufficiently ſet out thoſe, as Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall Acts, but ſheweth that for all that, Subjects ought not to reſiſt, <hi>nec quicquam adverſus Reges movere, licèt Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidem exerceaxt, &amp; rapinis ſint graves ſubditis, nullam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nec Dei nec aequi recti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> rationem habeant,</hi> what more full? which alſo appeares by the 18. v. <hi>Ye ſhall crie out in that daie, &amp;c.</hi> That they were left without this remedy of reſiſtance, <hi>Calv.</hi> in his <hi>Inſtit.</hi> the place above cited, thus, <hi>Eo ſo proripiet licentiae Regum libido, quam cohibere veſtrum non erit, quibus hoc reſtabit unum, luſſa excipere ac dicto audientes eſſe;</hi> and a little after, <hi>non weſtrum eſſe, his malis mederi; hoc tantum eſſe reliquum, Domini opem implorare,</hi> there can be nothing ſpoken more plainly againſt the power of reſiſtance in Subjects, then this. We have Adverſaries confeſſing the ſame, the Author of the <hi>Fuller Anſwer</hi> acknowledged, thoſe Kings of <hi>Jſrael</hi> might no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be reſiſted; and this Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchie</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that the People there had no other means to help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by, but cryes unto the Lord, ſo he, pag. 58.</p>
               <p>By this appeares what little weight there is in the exception which the <hi>Pleaders for defenſive Armes</hi> make to this place, <hi>This was</hi> (ſay they) <hi>a prediction of puniſhment, that ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them for their impetuous asking of a King, not a prohibition of reſiſtance,</hi> pag. 18. And in the ſame page, <hi>This prediction of puniſhment doth not prove, it was unlawfull, for them to defend their goods againſt their Kings Tyranny, but that it ſhould be vaine to them, becauſe if God would not heare their Cry, their defence would be to little purpoſe. Anſw.</hi> The puniſhment fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111670:32"/>is, that they ſhould be thus and thus evill intreated by their Kings, and that without remedy: but that in all this there is nothing to prove it was unlawfull for them to reſiſt ſuch Kings, is a bare aſſertion againſt former proofes, which ſhew there was on the Kings part a <hi>Jus</hi> or right of ſecurity againſt ſuch Violence. But to acknowledge, as they doe, that this prediction of puniſhment doth prove their defence would be vaine, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God did not heare their Cry, is to confeſſe, that, when God ſuffers Kings to exerciſe Tyranny and Oppreſſion upon the People, over whom he has ſet them, it is a ſcourge and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment from him upon that people for their ſinne, and that it is vain for them to ſeek remedy by reſiſtance; which is a moſt true and pious argument againſt reſiſtance, as we ſhall ſhew, when we come to reaſons againſt it.</p>
               <p>A ſecond exception is, that the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> Monarchy was Abſolute, and therefore excluded the reſiſtance of Subjects; ſo this Author of the Treatiſe of Monarchy. The pleaders for <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Armes,</hi> although they are againſt abſolute Monarchy as unlawfull, and therfore doe not ſay this Monarchy ſet up over Gods people was ſuch, yet doe they ſay, what was here fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told or enjoyned to that people, cannot be a Law or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intended to other Nations under oppreſſing Kings, no more then that, which the Lord impoſed on the <hi>Iewes</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations in <hi>Nebuhcadnezars</hi> Time, their putting their neck under his yoake, <hi>Jer.</hi> 27. can prove that any Nation is bound to yeeld to a forraigne enemy invading them, ſo they <hi>pag.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ</hi> I. Although this Monarchy of Iſraell were granted to be Abſolute, and the inſtances brought ſhould be peculiar to that people, not intended as Lawes, and Rules to other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet do: they ſufficiently prove what I intended in that part of my firſt Treatiſe, which was to ſhew that there was no Warrant for reſiſtance from Scripture, which ſtill gives us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Kings ſet over Gods people, who might not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted.</p>
               <p n="2">II How the Author of the <hi>Treat of Monarchy</hi> can ſay the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Kings were abſolute Monarchs according to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Abſoluteneſſe; which he gave above, I cannot ſee:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111670:32"/>for he told us, that Abſolute Monarchy is, when the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is ſo fully in one, that it hath no limits or bounds under God but the Monarchs own will; It is true they were not ſo limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as ſome Kings are now; but we know, there was a fixed judiciall Law, which in many particulars ſecured the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and liberty of that people, there were ſpeciall limitations for their Kings, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. There was alſo a ſtanding great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, <hi>the Saned<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im,</hi> whoſe ſentence in many things the King could not at his owne will and pleaſure reverſe, if we believe them that are skilfull in the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Antiquities. <hi>Grotius</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>de Iure belli &amp; pacis c.</hi> 3. places the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in a Middle condition between a meer abſolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and that which is altogether limited and conditionate, that is, thoſe <hi>Hebrew</hi> Kings were in ſome things abſolute, in ſome things Limited, which may be ſaid of every Limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy at this day, that was at firſt unlimited; and is true of the Monarchy of this Land, where I cannot but conceive the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch is free, and (if you pleaſe) abſolute in all ſuch things, in which he is not expreſly limited.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Inſtances drawn from that Monarchy againſt Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance are forceable in this Monarchy, if we either conſider what was now ſpoken againſt the meere abſoluteneſſe of that Monarchy, or look back to the Reaſons which were given in the end of the fiſt Section to prove that Monarchies are not therefore expoſed to reſiſtance, becauſe they are limited.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon this place 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. doth apply it to other Nations, even to all that are under Kings, who have not <hi>Epho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri</hi> or Magiſtrates over them, to whom they are accountable, as the <hi>Lacedaemonian</hi> Kings had, but our Kings have not; his words are theſe, <hi>Ex quibus apparet, ſubditos Regibus, nec poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe nec debere adverſus ipſos quicquam movere, licet Tyrannidem exerceant, &amp;c.</hi> and in his <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>nu.</hi> 27. Hee expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly takes away the Objection, (That this, which is impoſed upon the Jewes 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. and <hi>Ier.</hi> 27. was peculiar to that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſhewing plainly it was not <hi>peculiare mandatum,</hi> but tells us thus much in Generall, <hi>cuicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> delatum eſt Regnum, ei ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viendum,</hi> which being inferred from thoſe places, doth imply,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111670:33"/>we muſt ſerve the King, as the People ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> or their own Kings of <hi>Iſrael, viz.</hi> without reſiſtance, for, for that purpoſe <hi>Calvin</hi> alleadges thoſe examples. So that although this example doth not bind us to yeeld to a forraine enemy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading us, as the <hi>Pleaders</hi> needleſly replyed, yet doth it in <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> judgement bind us, to yeeld obedience without reſiſtance to that King, whom it appeares God has ſet over us.</p>
               <p>In the next place let us conſider the <hi>Reſcue of Ionathan,</hi> urged by the Pleaders for <hi>Defenſive Armes,</hi> pag. 11. It has been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that for this <hi>Reſcue,</hi> they did not of themſelves draw into Armes, but being preſent at <hi>Sauls</hi> command, did reſcue <hi>Ionathan</hi> from <hi>Sauls</hi> intended violence, not by force of Armes, but of a loving importunate violence by way of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, ſet off with a Souldierly boldneſſe. The pleaders te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. <hi>The violence was outragious enough, for</hi> Saul <hi>ſwore his death &amp; they his life,</hi> what then? this was ſtill but a Souldier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boldneſſe of ſpeech, But they make two collections thence. 1. <hi>That the people may ſweare an Aſſociation, that not one of the Parliament ſhall be put to death, unleſſe found guilty, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any Proclamation.</hi> A good inference! as if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of an Army doe agree among themſelves to intercede for a fellow Souldier, (one not ſo innocent as Jonathan, but juſtly ſentenced to death) and in that interceſſion be more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunately bold then they ought, &amp; through that importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty draw their King off from his reſolution of executing that ſentence: may I with any reaſon conclude thence that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Counties of his kingdome may enter an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him for the reſcuing of any unjuſtly ſentenced to death? 2. They collect from thence, <hi>That if</hi> Saul <hi>by himſelfe, or others, had attempted</hi> Jonathans <hi>death, they would have actually reſiſted them even with Armes.</hi> Imagine they would have done ſo, you have but an uncertaine ſuppoſition to ſecure your reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the heat of a Souldierly boldneſſe to defend the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſpoſition of your ſpirit; how farre theſe Souldiers would have proceeded, I know not, but we ſhall ſee below, that the Chriſtian Souldiers in <hi>Iulians</hi> Army would not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed ſo farre in the like caſe; and I dare ſay with <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111670:33"/>ſi iſt a ſedit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe fec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, quaſi</hi> Jonathanum <hi>Regiper vim trep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi, nullo modo poſſunt excuſari: if they had proceeded to force, they could not have been excuſed.</hi> How impertinently and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy</hi> made uſe of this <hi>Reſcue of Ionathan,</hi> was ſhewen above, <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning reſiſtance in abſolute Monarchyes.</p>
               <p>Now wee come to examine <hi>Davids</hi> demeanour towards <hi>Saul;</hi> in which his taking of Armes, and the uſe he made of them is conſiderable. The Anſwers, that were made to this objected example of <hi>David,</hi> did in generall inſinuate thus much. That they, which now pretend it for the defence of their Armes, have done farre more then <hi>David</hi> did or inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to doe, and that they have not warrant to doe ſo much, <hi>(i)</hi> that there is nothing alike in <hi>Davids</hi> Armes and Theirs. The particulars were theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt that <hi>Davids</hi> purpoſe in having armed men about him, was meerely to ſecure his perſon againſt the cut-Thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes of <hi>Saul,</hi> that is, againſt his private Emiſſaries, ſuch as were ſent to take away <hi>Davids</hi> life, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.15 or againſt the ſurprize of ill minded people, among whom he ſhould abide, ſuch as the <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phites,</hi> who elſe might have carried <hi>David</hi> himſelfe to <hi>Saul,</hi> as well as the newes of his being among them. The Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> page 51. and the <hi>Divines</hi> that plead for <hi>defenſive Armes,</hi> pag 12. reply, that this is enough for the reſiſtance they plead for. But who ſees not a large difference betweene ſecuring a mans ſelfe from ſuddaine ſurprizes of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Emiſſaries or cloſe Enemies, and appearing in the Field with Armes againſt the Armies of the Prince? if a private Gentleman doe endeavour the former by more then ordinary retinue, no man will ſpeake him guilty of the ſecond; for the one is uſed but in order to an eſcape by flight, but the other is in order to a forceable conſtraint and finall conteſtation with the Prince, if he will not change his mind; which is the Cauſe of theſe Times, and the thing ſuppoſed in the Queſtion: as we explained above, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we ſee that <hi>David</hi> did accordingly give place &amp; fly as <hi>Saul</hi> purſued, uſing no violence againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> or his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:111670:34"/>when in his power. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. The <hi>pleaders</hi> for <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Armes,</hi> reply, <hi>It was not wiſdome in</hi> David <hi>to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> Saul, <hi>for he was not ſtrong enough to doe it,</hi> page 12. <hi>Anſw.</hi> ſo ſhall we ſee theſe <hi>Pleaders</hi> below finding the like wiſdome in the primitive Chriſtians, as if they forbore to reſiſt, becauſe they had not force enough: which wiſdome do's fooliſhly charge the doctrine of the Goſpell, even in the judgement of the Author of the <hi>Treat. of Monarchy.</hi> But might not <hi>David</hi> with his 600 men have encountred 3000 ſleeping? he kenw that a ſleep was upon them from the Lord, and if he with <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhai</hi> alone durſt goe downe among them, what might hee not have done with 600 men? The <hi>Pleaders</hi> anſwer out of much compaſſion, <hi>That they which are upon the Defenſive, ought not in cold blood to kill ſleeping Enemies, or ſuch waking, farther then appeares much advantagious to the Defence.</hi> pag. 12. But doe they hold to this practice? doe any of the Kings party ſleeping or waking find this mercy? would they not thinke it much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantagious to the Defence, to let whole companies of them eſcape as <hi>David</hi> did here? for heare what followes, <hi>If the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of as many, as they could that night, wouldhave given hopes of ending</hi> Saules <hi>purſuit and making Peace,</hi> then the Pleaders doubt not, but <hi>David would have done it:</hi> It's pitty <hi>David</hi> had not then ſuch Counſellors about him as theſe; <hi>Abiſhai</hi> was too bloody in adviſing to have <hi>Saul</hi> himſelfe killed, but theſe men would have councelled him to ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ughter the Souldiers, and take <hi>Saul</hi> priſoner, and force him to other Conditions; ſo would they doe, if they had their King at the like advantage; and ſo if <hi>David</hi> would have done, he might have had hope of ending his troubles. If <hi>David</hi> would have uſed the meanes and practices of theſe dayes, if he would have proclaimed abroad what <hi>Saul</hi> was, and that he himſelfe endeavoured only to reduce him to a Religious and juſt way of Government, and thereupon called in more forces, he might have quickly had an Army able to encounter &amp; overmatch <hi>Saul</hi> in the open Field. But nothing is done by <hi>David</hi> to the countenancing of the Rebellious practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of theſe dayes. He gives not an ill word out againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> he invites none into his ayd; he called not theſe men he had to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:111670:34"/>
                  <hi>clangore tubae,</hi> as <hi>Calvin</hi> obſerves; he did not uſe them for the ſuppreſſing of any of <hi>Sauls</hi> bad inſtruments, but hee leaves him to the hand of God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.10. and them to the curſe of God. <hi>v.</hi> 19. he tels <hi>Abner,</hi> that he and his Souldiers are worthy to dye, becauſe they had not kept their maſter the Lords Anoynted more carefully, <hi>v.</hi> 16. How can our defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders now pretend <hi>Davids</hi> example for the lawfulneſſe of their fighting againſt the bad inſtruments of Oppreſſion, that are (as they ſay) about the Kings Perſon, when thoſe, that were about <hi>Saul,</hi> are juſtly blamed for not carefully keeping and defending their maſter againſt any violence, that might come from ſome miſguided hand of <hi>Davids</hi> men?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, concerning <hi>Davids</hi> intent to defend <hi>Keilab,</hi> againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> it was anſwered that ſuch an uncertain and improbable ſuppoſition was not warrant for Conſcience. The <hi>Pleaders</hi> reply, that <hi>Davids</hi> ſecond enquiry concerning the affection of the <hi>Keilites,</hi> and <hi>his going whither ſoever be could goe,</hi> as its ſaid, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.11. doe plainly ſhew, it was his purpoſe to have ſtayed there, and that he was diſappoynted of his purpoſe, <hi>pa.</hi> 12. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If <hi>David</hi> had at firſt ſuch a purpoſe of defending the Towne againſt <hi>Saul</hi> we ſee he fell from it, as he did from his purpoſe againſt <hi>Nabal,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. and has I f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us in both an example of forbearance, no warrant to proceed to ſuch extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. II. He might enquire concerning the <hi>Keilites,</hi> not out of a purpoſe to defend the City againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> (for had hee had ſuch a reſclution, he could have maſtered the Citizens and turn'd out the diſaffected, as they doe now, that pretend his example) but for the more timely providing for his flight out of a City, (which as the text notes) <hi>had Gates and Barres;</hi> leſt if he ſhould ſtay till <hi>Saul</hi> drew neare, the Towneſmen by trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery might hinder or impeach his flight, that be ſhould not get cleare of the Towne till <hi>Saul</hi> had beguirt it. But his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry <hi>&amp; his going whither, he could goe,</hi> do ſhew he depended on immediate direction from God in all theſe actions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his example not ſo imitable by theſe defendants; which gave occaſion to a fourth Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. It was anſwered: That <hi>Davids</hi> example was extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:111670:35"/>he was Anoynted and deſigned by the Lord to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>Saul,</hi> and queſtionleſſe had warrant for an extraordinary way of ſafeguarding his perſon. This concernes his having an Army about him for his guard; that as by the former parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars it was cleare, that thoſe, which have now taken Armes, have done far more in the uſe of them, then <hi>David</hi> did or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to doe; ſo by this laſt Anſwer it will appeare, that they may not doe ſo much, or that they may not pretend <hi>Davids</hi> exampl, for the ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſing or having an Army. The <hi>Pleaders</hi> reply. 1. Then might every ſucceſſour or Heire to the Crowne plead the like Authority in the like danger, pag. 13. <hi>Anſwer. Davids</hi> right to ſucceed did not authorize h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, but his being deſigned for <hi>Sauls</hi> ſucceſſour, as he was, makes it more then probable that he had ſpeciall warrant from God (whoſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction we ſee was not wanting to him) for this way of ſafeguar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his perſon: alſo, that (as ſome Interpreters have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) ſeeing <hi>Sauls</hi> poſterity was to give way to him, he might not come to the Crown, as one crept out of an hole or ſome lurking place, but accompanyed with a ſtrength; for which he is cal'd back by the Prophet into the Land of <hi>Iudah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.5. that the eyes of the people might be upon him, even while <hi>Saul</hi> lived.</p>
               <p n="2">II. They replie, <hi>Its a ſtrange way of anſwering Scripture Examples, that ſuch a thing is extraordinary, when no ſuch thing can be gathered out of the Text. The ancient Rule holds good,</hi> Praxis Sanctorum eſt interpres praeceptorum: <hi>David did thus against Sauls violence, therefore this is an Interpretation of the honour due by the fifth Commandement.</hi> Anſw. Beſide the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reaſon, it is plaine in every paſſage how <hi>Dauid</hi> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon extraordinary direction. <hi>Calvin,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.2. finds ſomething extraordinary and peculiar in <hi>Davids</hi> receiving theſe men for his guard: <hi>Peculiare factum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem regulam non trahendum;</hi> and ſhewes how ready men are to pretend this example of <hi>David,</hi> for the maintaining of a juſt cauſe by unlawfull meanes, ſaying, <hi>quare ego bonam &amp; juſtam Cauſam agens, non uterer medijs qua ſo miloi offerunt?</hi> Where's now his <hi>praxis Sanctorum,</hi> to ſay <hi>David</hi> did this, therefore I
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111670:35"/>may; nay <hi>David</hi> did not that againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> which theſe men pretend; and what <hi>David</hi> did, cannot be fellowed by another example to make it <hi>Praxin Sanctorum:</hi> whereas we have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples of Kings as bad as <hi>Saul,</hi> and find the Saints living under them, never attempting any thing tending to reſiſtance; there's <hi>praxis Sanctorum,</hi> imitable by us.</p>
               <p n="3">III. They reply, <hi>Davids unction ought rather to have ſtrengthned his faith, but this was a diſparagement to his faith and to Gods honour, that His Anoynted ſhould be ſafeguarded for ſo long together onely by a way, which in all others had beene abominable,—this proves the meanes both lawfull and ordma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> pag. 13. Anſw. <hi>Davids</hi> Unction did ſtrengthen his faith, but under ſuch means too, is it pleaſed God to vouchſafe him for the greater Corroboration, ſuch a Guard of ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds; God thought it no diſparagement for his honour to bring out his people with the ſpoyles of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and we muſt give him leave in the extraordinary diſpenſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to take what way it pleaſes him; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could have preſerved <hi>David</hi> from <hi>Sauls</hi> fury, as he did <hi>Eliah</hi> from <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bs,</hi> which was after a more private way, but he thought more fit to let <hi>David</hi> be ſtrengthned by the acceſſion of much people, as a <hi>praeludium</hi> to their falling off from the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> into him. Laſtly, if this way of preſervation by bends of armed men were <hi>ordinary</hi> (as theſe men will make it) then may one ſingle Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as <hi>David</hi> was, draw armed men together, be Captaine over them, and lead them up and down for his owne, &amp; their preſervation that do adhere unto him; which if they will not a low, then muſt there be in <hi>Davids</hi> example ſomething more then ordinary.</p>
               <p>And here I muſt challenge not onely the Reaſon of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Treat of Monarchy,</hi> who cals it a ſhuffling Anſwer, to ſay <hi>Davids</hi> example was extraordinary, <hi>pag</hi> 5.7. but alſo his Ingenuity, who confeſſes that the people under the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> Monarchy might not reſiſt, and had no other me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes to helpe themſelves, but cryes to God, <hi>pag.</hi> 58. and yet urges the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Ionathans</hi> reſcue, of <hi>Davids</hi> rayſing Forces, of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to defend <hi>Keilab,</hi> for the defending of armes taken up,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:111670:36"/>and uſed by Subjects in making reſiſtance. He deales with us herein, as the Popiſh writers doe in the point of <hi>Invocation</hi> of Saints, they acknowledge the Fathers of the Old Teſtament were not then in a condition to be invocated, yet doe they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge Teſtimonies out of the old Teſtament for the proofe of that point to deceive the unwary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eliſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> example was altogether impertinent, yet from thence occaſion was taken to ſpeak of Perſonall defence, upon which theſe <hi>Pleaders</hi> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a long and ted<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous Reply, <hi>page</hi> 14, 15, 16. The ſubſtance of which is delivered in the Reaſons, which the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy</hi> makes for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and therefore becauſe this Reply of theirs, is no way ſtrengthened by <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s example, but is altogother rationall, we will deferre the examination of what is materiall in it, to the laſt Section.</p>
               <p>To conclude, It was a generall collection, but yet a very forcible Argument againſt reſiſtance; that among ſo many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, bitterly reproving wicked Kings for ſubverſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; juſtice, there was not one, that celld upon the Eiders of the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple for this duty of making Reſiſtance. The <hi>Pleaders</hi> reply, ſcarce like <hi>Reverend and learned Divines. That in the times of good Kings we find the Princes, Elders, and Nobles very Corrupt, who then can marvail if they were ſtarke naught, where the King was maught, or why ſhould it be expected, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hets ſhould call upon them to reſiſt the King being on his ſide, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on theirs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> pag 20. <hi>Anſw.</hi> If it were the Duty of thoſe El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Princes (as theſe pleaders doe conceive it was) with force to oppoſe the exorbitances of thoſe Kings, then was it the duty of thoſe Prophets to admoniſh them of it; and the more cauſe had the Prophets to recall them to it, the further they were from it; the deſperate condition of ſuch Princes and El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers might take away hope of prevailing, could not excuſe the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſilence, and neglect. We conclude therefore, that the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament doe not give any Warrant by precept or example, for the Armes &amp; Reſiſtance of Subjects now againſt their Soveraigne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:111670:36"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>Of Reſiſtance ſorbidden in the</hi> 13. <hi>to the Romanes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the new Teſtament, that of the 13. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> is moſt conſiderable, the ful examination of which wil alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other places which may ſeeme to concerne the point in hand; leſt Servants and Subjects, upon the doctrine of Chriſtion Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, ſhould conclude themſelves free from Maſters and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nors, who then were cruell for the moſt part and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, the Apoſtle doth often call ſervants to a continuance of their obedience, and here Subjects to the duty of ſubjection without Reſiſtance: as likewiſe S. <hi>Peter</hi> doth, 1 <hi>Ep. cap.</hi> 2. The place is confiderable: firſt in it ſelfe, as it teaches the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> and the <hi>End</hi> of Government; by that the Power and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; by this the duties of Governors are ſeen, &amp; from both the duty of Subjects in yeelding Subjection and forbearing Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is inferred. Secondly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is conſiderable in relation to thoſe times, as it is applyable to the then governing powers, and to the Chriſtian Subjects, to whom <hi>S, Paul.</hi> then wrote; and thence we muſt conclude (if we will think <hi>S, Paul</hi> wrote pertinently, and meant that thoſe he wrote to, ſhould receive direction by what he commended to them) that however the Governours then were not anſwerable to the <hi>End</hi> of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and were farre from the duties there ſpecified, yet had they the Power and Authority, and thoſe duties which are there enjoyned for the yeelding of Subjection, and forbearing of reſiſtance, were to be performed by their Subjects then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Reverend Divines</hi> have written ſuch for the explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this place, to bring it to their pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſe, and have in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places of their book, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>forced the ſame things upon the Reader, to perſwade or weary him. What they have ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall I ſhall examine.</p>
               <p>Firſt. They obſerve that it is <hi>Higher Powers</hi> in the plurall; not <hi>Higher Power,</hi> as the Doctor, ſay they, uſually had it, and in this they ſuſpect a great fraud, <hi>Page</hi> 3. &amp; take it to be a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:111670:37"/>fallacy in the preſent queſtion, as if the King only were not to be reſiſted, <hi>page</hi> 9. when as we may not reſiſt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Officer, not a Conſtable, arreſting us, or diſtraining our goods, <hi>ibid, Anſw,</hi> A dang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ous buſineſſe. I promiſe you, and ſuch an one, as it concerned theſe <hi>Learned Divines</hi> to give the Reader ſo often warning of as they do; but to anſwer the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> once for all; <hi>The Higher power</hi> in the Singular was commonly uſed, not in alleadging the Text, as if it were ſo in the Apoſtle; but in the applying of it to the preſent caſe, which laying the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> or Queſtion between the powers themſelves in this poynt of Reſiſtance or Armer, might very well allow the King to be deciphered by the <hi>Higher power,</hi> or <hi>the Supream,</hi> in relation or oppoſition to other Governours under Him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they alſo be <hi>Higher powers,</hi> in reſpect of the people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and not to be reſiſted by their inferiours. It is but what themſelves have expreſſed in the ſame <hi>page,</hi> 3. <hi>By Higher powers are meant All in Civill legall Authority, which in Saint</hi> Peters <hi>phraſe, is of the</hi> King as ſupream, <hi>or</hi> Governours. <hi>for theſe are higher then the People, though lower then the King:</hi> the very ſame thing intended and ſpoken by me. But theſe men, when they have gotten a ſeeming advantage, and thinke the People cannot ſee the vanity of it, never know when to have done with it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> They obſeive, that it is <hi>Power</hi> in the abſtract, which notes the Authority, wherewich the Perſon is inveſted, and not the perſon in the Concrete; leſt that might be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of his perſonal commands beyond or againſt his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which the Apoſtle doth greatly prevent by uſing the word <hi>Power.</hi> So they <hi>page.</hi> 3. which is the ground-work of their diſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction between Reſiſting the Perſonall Commands, and reſiſting the power of the Governour: but we ſhall ſee the Apoſtle gives no ground for it.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe they have taken the hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of this their Cavil from <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ophylact,</hi> or rather from <hi>Chryſoſtom's</hi> words upon this place, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Apoſtles ſpeech is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of particular Princes, but of the thing it ſelfe</hi> (i.e. <hi>of the Office,</hi> which words are nothing to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:111670:37"/>the meaning of theſe men: for <hi>Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtome,</hi> obſerving that the Prince then governing were not ſuch, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtle deſcribes, <hi>v.</hi> 3.4.6. did therefore ſay the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the Office not of them that bore it (i.e.) not of thoſe individuall Perſons then in power, who were farre from the performance of thoſe duties; out if we look to the duty there required of Subjects in regard of Obed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence and reſiſtance, it was never i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomes</hi> mind to think that the Apoſtle did not ſpeake of that, as due to the Perſons then Göverning. Well, to let the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentator goe, let us looke into the Text, where it plainly appears, that it is the Apoſtles intent to ſhew the duty of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and for that purpoſe he ſpeaks of the power it ſelfe, and of the Perſon that beares it, that is from the power which he ſhews to be of God, he enforces obedience to the Perſons that are in power, yea with reſpect to the Perſons then governing.</p>
               <p>For firſt, Thoſe words, <hi>the powers that are,</hi> doe plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Perſons; becauſe Power in the Abſtract, cannot bee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> exiſtent, ſo as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of it here, making it the object of obedience. Againe, thoſe that he calls <hi>Powers</hi> in the firſt verſe, he calls <hi>Rulers</hi> in the third, and the <hi>Miniſters of God</hi> in the fourth <hi>v.</hi> And <hi>thou ſhalt have praiſe of the power, v.</hi> 3. What, can <hi>Power</hi> in the Abſtract give Praiſe? or is tribute paid to the Power in the Abſtract? In a word. The Power or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is the <hi>Reaſon</hi> why we yeeld Subjection and Obedience to any perſon, but the Perſon that bears the Power is the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of our Subjection and obedience; and becauſe he bears the Power and is ſet over us, we muſt not reſiſt him, though he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the Power.</p>
               <p>Their third obſervation or Conceit (upon which their m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. Anſwer to this place depends, and for which the <hi>Fuller Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerer</hi> has applauded them) is the reſtraint of Subjection en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned here, to Legall commands in Civill matters only: their words are, <hi>The things, about which the Authority and ſo the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection in this place is converſant, are Civill matters belonging to the Second Table, betweene Man and Man; for then the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates commanded not for but againſt Religion and the firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and therefore the Active ſubjection at leaſt here required is
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:111670:38"/>limited to Civill Matters, or at leaſt paſſive yeelding to the pet nalty of the Lawes, in caſe of not obeying actively; and neither active nor paſſive ſubjection farther, then to Legall Commands,</hi> ſo pag. 4. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. How farre they extend thoſe <hi>Civill matters,</hi> to which they will have this <hi>Subjection</hi> here confined, they have not diſtinctly ſkewen, whether to things onely of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency determined by the Roman Lawes, and belonging to the Second Table, in regard of the generall end of it, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they were ſo determined for the more convenient proceeding of Juſtice, and the better conſerving of order and Peac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tor to thing alſo in themſelves good or bad; for it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Roman Lawes alſo concerned theſe. There are indeed that ſay, by <hi>good workes,</hi> in the 3. <hi>v.</hi> are not meant workes <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> but <hi>Civilly</hi> good, which is very anſwerable to theſe mens re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>traint, whom it concerned to make the way they will goe in for <hi>Obedience,</hi> as narrow as they can, for that will leave the way for <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> ſo much the Wider; only I muſt returne the blame of carleſneſſe (which they would often caſt upon mee) upon themſelves, that making ſuch a reſtraint, they would not more diſtinctly fix the bounds of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is true, that the Apoſtle enjoynes them Subjection here to all Legall Commands <hi>in Civill matters,</hi> but it is not to be ſo reſtrained; for put the caſe, If they that were in Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhould command contrary to their owne Lawes in <hi>Morall</hi> things, or contrary to Religion &amp; the firſt Table; were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians bound to obey? for <hi>active obedience</hi> the poynt is cleare, they were not bound: but were they bound then to ſuffer for not obeying actively? Theſe <hi>Divines</hi> tell us the <hi>Subjection</hi> here enjoyned by the Apoſtle concernes onely <hi>Civill Matters,</hi> a thing of which there was leſſe doubt; and ſo Chriſtians are left altogether without direction, in regard of the other Matte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, which more concerned them: unleſſe they will take the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Reſolution theſe men give, as we had it above, <hi>Neither active or paſſive Subjection is here required farther, then to Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall commands.</hi> So then, Chriſtians, according to theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, were free and might reſiſt, when they had ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands impoſed on them; but can we think the Apoſtle ſhould
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:111670:38"/>give them ſo lame an inſtruction, as to teach them Subjection only in <hi>Civill Matters,</hi> and leave them either without dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction what to doe in the other caſes, or permit them to make the inference for reſiſtance, as theſe men doe, contrary to the very practice of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, and all the Apoſtles, and all the Chriſtians of thoſe primitive Times, who did yeeld <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive obedience</hi> under the illegall commands of the then govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Powers.</p>
               <p>But they endeavour to prove it; <hi>pag.</hi> 4. &amp; 5. from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text by the inference, <hi>Whoſoever therefore reſiſts, &amp;c.</hi> which is made, ſay they, from Gods ordaining the power; and if I be bound to be ſubject to Tyranny, or to ſuffer violence of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by vertue of the commandement here, then is Tyranny the Ordinance of God, and Magiſtrates have power ordained of God to uſe Tyrannous violence pag. 4. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It followes of Active Subjection, not Paſſive; If I be bound actively to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey ſuch commands of Tyranny, then would it be truly infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that Tyranny it ſelfe were the Ordinance of God; but if I be bound only to ſuffer patiently under the illegall commands of Tyranny, then doth it not follow, that Tyranny is theordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, but that thoſe Tyrants do beare the power or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God, though abufing it ſometimes for the juſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of thoſe they are ſet over by God. I would alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire theſe Divines to conſider, how finely they teach private men to reſiſt, by arguing as they doe here, <hi>If I be bound to be ſubject to Tyranny, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like inſtances repeated over and over they have in the beginning of pag. 5. which are ſatisfied by the like Anſwer, but they enquire a little after in the ſame pag. <hi>Seeing the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor will not ſay, that the moſt pereusptory refuſing to obey active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tyrannous Commands is reſiſtance, by what authority of Text or Context will he ſtretch the prohibition to the refuſing to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Tyrannous Violence? Or how doth any reſiſt unlawfully (though by Armes) when unlawfull violence is offered him, which God no where gave Authority to uſe againſt him, nor ever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to yeeld unto?</hi> Anſw. 1. Seeing your Argument from thoſe word words <hi>(the Ordinance God)</hi> would, if it were
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:111670:39"/>good, allow private mento reſiſt, I pray you by what authority of Text or Context doe your Patrons forbid Reſiſtance to be made by private men, but allow it to Magiſtrates or the infeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or powers? is it from the conſideration of thoſe to whom the Apoſtle wrote, who had not then any Magiſtrates of their own profeſſion among them? though that be no good ground to raiſe that diſtinction of private men and publique in the point of reſiſtance (for the Apoſtles reaſons againſt reſiſting of High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers doe concerne all times) yet will the conſideration of thoſe perſons to whom, and of thoſe times in which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle wrote, give us <hi>authority to ſtretch the prohibition to the refuſing to ſuffer Tyrannous violence;</hi> for we muſt conceive, that he gave them inſtruction which did neerely concerne them, which might in ſome reaſonable manner direct them, which was agreeable to Saint <hi>Peters</hi> advice, 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> which was conſonant to the practice of the Apoſtles, and all other Chriſtians of thoſe and the following primitive times; but the inſtruction that the Apoſtle here gives them cannot be ſuch, unleſſe it forbid the <hi>refuſing to ſuffer under the Tyrannous violence of thoſe times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Anſw.</hi> If he that reſiſts by Armes, doth not reſiſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully (as you ſay) when unlawfull violence is offered him, which God no where gave authority to uſe againſt him, where hath God, I pray you, given authority to Parents or Maſters to uſe unjuſt violence to their Children or Servants? yet is not their reſiſtance unlawfull? for though God has not given thoſe authority to doe it, yet has commanded theſe to ſuffer it, if done. The like may be ſaid of Kings and Subjects; for has not God put Kings, Fathers, &amp; Maſters all in one Commandement &amp; enjoyned this duty and reverence to them under one word, <hi>Honour?</hi> and S. <hi>Peter,</hi> next to the feare of God, has placed <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur the King,</hi> and adviſes Chriſtians to ſuffer though wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, under the then Tyrannous Governours, and <hi>froward</hi> Maſters. Did not God put his People under this Subjection, when he put them under a King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.? where this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of their Kings from their reſiſtance &amp; forceable Coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion is called <hi>Ius Regis,</hi> not becauſe God gave them power and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:111670:39"/>right to uſe unjuſt and oppreſſing violence, but becauſe if they did ſo, they were by the Law and Ordinance of God ſecured from the violence of the People, and reſerved for the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vengeance of God, that ordained them and ſet them over his people; as appeared above in the former Section.</p>
               <p>But they goe on; and ſeeme to conceive, that by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers not to be reſiſted, the Doctor meanes onely the Supream, and thoſe that Act his will; but denies the like ſecurity to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Magiſtrates, if they be Tyrannous, without any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from the Supream pag. 6. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Doctor by main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, the <hi>Supream power</hi> might not be reſiſted by the <hi>Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate powers</hi> under Him, did not thereby imply, that theſe might be reſiſted; but ſtill the higher ſpower is not to be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by thoſe that are under it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if he ſay, that neither</hi> Supream <hi>nor</hi> Subordinate <hi>may be reſiſted, then may every meane. Officer ruine the whole neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and ſo the bleſſed Ordinance of God in Magiſtracy ſhall turne to the greateſt Curſe to mankind,</hi> ſo they pag. 6, <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are ſuperiour powers that can protect, ſo that if the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate power doe wrong, the complai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t lies ſtill to the higher power; if the Supream or higheſt be engaged in the Violence, the redreſſe is to be ſought by petition &amp; ſuite, if not ſucceed, the complaint lyes to heaven, reſiſtance is not the remedy.</p>
               <p>They conclude; <hi>Therefore as the Apoſtle, in the following verſes, doth baniſh Tyranny out of the context, deſcribing, every where a righteous Magiſtrate: ſo is Tyranny baniſhed out of the interpretation of this Text, which allowes him that is a Tyrant no ſecurity that he ſhall be endured, and not reſiſted even with Armet; though it doth ſecure a juſt ruling Prince from all reſiſtance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heavyeſt penalty of Damnation,</hi> pag. 6. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true that the Apoſtle baniſhes Tyranny out of the duty of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by the following verſes, but it is alſo true, that he bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhesreſiſtance out of the duty of Subjects by the former verſes. He deſcribes a rightcous Magiſtrate; but could he then exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plity? were the Governours then ſuch? If not ſuch, as they were not then would this Text, according to the interpretation of theſe Divines, give but a lame direction to the Chriſtians,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:111670:40"/>how they ſhould carry themſelves towards the then unjuſt Governors; nor would this text, which forbids reſiſtance, at al ſecure thoſe Governors from their reſiſtance; nay, I would faine ſee what any Jeſuite can ſay or deſire more from this text then <hi>that it gives a Tyrant no ſecurity, that he ſhall be endured.</hi> Laſtly, if the penalty of Damnation laid upon the people, will ſecure a juſt ruling Prince from all reſiſtance, as they tel us, why ſhould not damnation laid upon every unjuſt oppreſſing Prince, ſecure the people from Tyranny? one would thinke it moſt equall that the <hi>Higheſt Power</hi> ſhould have the greateſt ſecurity, and ſo God in his wiſdome thought fit, when he put his people under Kings without power of Reſiſtance; as was ſhe wen in the former Section, and will be a forceable reaſon againſt reſiſtance, in the next Section.</p>
               <p>Now let us conſider this Text with application to thoſe Times, and to the Powers then ruling; upon that conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it was inferred, that Tyrannous &amp; oppreſſing Princes are not to be reſiſted by Arms, &amp; that the Apoſtles reaſons taught us; that for the good which is generally received by Ruling powers, we muſt beare with them, though abuſing their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as the Emperours then did; which alſo took away their diſtinction of reſiſting not the power, but the abuſe of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Theſe <hi>Divines</hi> in Anſwer to it, ſpend many pages, from <hi>page.</hi> 22. to 28. and againe, from 47. to 51. where, (after ſome thing ſaid of ſmall moment concerning the Kings Supremacy and the Roman Senate; <hi>page.</hi> 22.23, of which I have had, and ſhall have preſently occaſion to ſpeake upon more weighty conſideration brought by the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi>) They tell us. Firſt, <hi>The Doctors vaine Confidence will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in thinking he has made voyd the diſtinction of Refiſting not the power, but the abuſe of it; for when he grants that active obedience is to be denyed to the illegall Commands of the Prince, he diſtinguiſhes himſelfe hetweene the Power and the abuſe of it; and why may not wee diſtinguiſh upon the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond verſe, as well as he does upon the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in the firſt,</hi> ſo pag. 26. <hi>Anſw,</hi> You cannot ſo well make the diſtinction in in regard of <hi>reſiſtance,</hi> as it may in regard of <hi>ſubjection</hi> or <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:111670:40"/>for I can ſever the power from the abuſe of it, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying my active obedience to the abuſe or illegall command, &amp; by yeelding my paſſive obedience under ſuch a command; but by making reſiſtance you cannot ſever them, for you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſiſt the abuſe, but by reſiſting of the power in him that beares it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they tell us, that the Apoſtles reaſons forbid on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſiſtance to Legall Commands— and ſtill they aske, doth the Apoſtle elſe know what he ſaith, when in his reaſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e tells us, <hi>Rulers are not a terrour to good workes, and he is the miniſter of God to thee for good?</hi> can this be ſaid of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors then? therefore the D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> ſenſe muſt be renounced, and it muſt be ſaid, the Apoſtle medles onely with Civill matters here, ſo <hi>pag.</hi> 47.48. <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is, the Apoſtle medles with that, which did little concerne them, and gives them no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in that which did moſt pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe them: the Tyrannous Commands and violences of the then Emperors: can we think he was well adviſed, if he had made them a diſcourſe of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which they could make no uſe of, for the then ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſities? when therefore he ſaith, <hi>Rulers are not a terrour,</hi>— and <hi>they they are Miniſters of God for good, &amp;c.</hi> it was true of the then Rulers in regard of ſome Civill good which they did in ſome meaſure procure, (for S. <hi>Paul</hi> did often find reliefe in that Government, and was often reſcued from the violence and cruelty of his Enemies, as we read in the Acts of the Apoſtles) though it was true alſo, that their Government was full of Tyranny and injuſtice: what ſhall we ſay then to theſe reaſons of the Apoſtle, but that he forbids reſiſtance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe Tyrannous Governours, and urges it from the end of government, which was for good, and which their Subjects did in regard of <hi>Civill matters</hi> in ſome ſort enjoy under them? but we cannot thinke, that he medles with Civill matters on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or forbids refiſtance to Legall commands only, unleſſe we ſhould alſo think, that the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le left the Chriſtians to infer from theſe reaſons, as theſe <hi>Divines</hi> doe, that if <hi>Rule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> doe not accordingly <hi>miniſter for good,</hi> but are <hi>a terrour to good workes,</hi> they may and ought to be reſiſted, and that the Chriſtians, had
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:111670:41"/>they had force, might have reſiſted, ſo they affirme, <hi>pag.</hi> 49. We ſee then the concluſion they are neceſſitated to by their interpretation of this place, in reſtraining the prohibition of reſiſtance only to Legall-commands: which concluſion (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſcandalous to Chriſtian Religion, ſo oppoſite to the practice of the Apoſtles, and the expreſſe doctrine of thoſe &amp; after times) doth ſhew, that theſe <hi>Divines</hi> did not know what they ſaid, when they inferred from the Apoſtles reaſons, that Reſiſtance only to Legall Commands is forbidden, and that Chriſtians might have reſiſted.</p>
               <p>Let them heare what <hi>Bucer</hi> ſaith upon the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>be ſubject,</hi> the word, ſaith he, ſignifieth to be <hi>plenè ſub imperio &amp; in poteſtate, fully under the power of Rulers,</hi> and that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle by that word gives us to underſtand <hi>opertere noſtraomnia ponere in mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orum, qui publicam poteſtatem gerunt, ſed prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Dominum, idèo quae Domino debemus, ea ſemper &amp; ante om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia praestand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſunt: interim tamen ſi magiſtratsu ob id nobis non res odo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed ipſam etiam vitam conetur eripere, ferendum eſt, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poteſtati obluctandum;</hi> this is full, and forbids reſiſtance under illegall commands and ſufferings for obeying of God— Then upon the Apoſtles Reaſons, <hi>He is the Miniſter of God to thee for good, &amp;c.</hi> the ſame <hi>Bucer</hi> ſhewes, They are drawne from the good <hi>&amp;</hi> benefit for which governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was ordained, which good is obtained <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the moſt part, and in ſome meaſure; the like ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place—who perſwading ſubmiſſion under Tyrannous Rulers concludes thus, <hi>Nulla ergò Tyrannis eſſe poteſt, qua non aliquâ ex parte ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio ſit ad tuendam hominum ſocietatem,</hi> the like doth <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> upon the place.</p>
               <p>Let them alſo read how the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> cenſures theſe <hi>Divines</hi> for their inferences from the Apoſtles reaſons; that the <hi>Apoſtle, according to ſuch a meaning, ſhould have taught them a Doctrine of reſiſtance rather, then ſubjection, and that the received Doctrine of the Saints in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and moderne times, could never find in that place of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſuch a licence for Chriſtians, to uſe Armes in their defence, againſt the Tyranny of their Emperours,</hi> pag. 64. with ſeverall
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:111670:41"/>reaſons which ſhew the ſcandall of ſuch Doctrine, <hi>pag.</hi> 66.</p>
               <p>What then will this Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> that pleades alſo for Reſiſtance, anſwer to the Apoſtles prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of it? he grants they might not reſiſt in that Monarchy, but affirme, that Subjects may in this; why? Becauſe Religion then was no part of the Lawes, but here it is; Alſo becauſe, that was an Abſolute Monarchy &amp; Soveraignty, this a limited and Mixed. So we have two exceptions of his as he dilivers them, pag. 59. 64. and 66.</p>
               <p>His firſt exception is, <hi>Religion then was no part of the Lawes, and ſo its violation no ſubverſion of Eſtabliſhed government,— Herein we have Doctor Bilſon conſenting, who ſaith,</hi> That the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior power forbidden here to be reſiſted, is not the Princes will againſt his Lawes, but agreeing to his Lawes. <hi>I thinke the day it ſelfe is not more cleare.</hi> pag. 64. and 57. <hi>I doe concurre with</hi> Mr. Burrowes, <hi>profeſſing againſt reſiſting of Authority, though abuſed:</hi> That if thoſe who have power to make Lawes, make ſinfull Lawes, and ſo give authority to any to force obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, there muſt be either flying or paſſive Obedience, and pag. 66. <hi>In the caſe of the Armes now taken up, there is no need of thoſe offenſive Grounds</hi> which the Reverend Divines runne upon) <hi>Religion being now a part of our Nationall Law.</hi> So he. <hi>Anſw.</hi> What Dr. <hi>Bilſon</hi> and other of our Divines have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in favour of Reſiſtance, they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ane it of ſuch States, as may by the known Lawes uſe forceable reſtraint againſt the exorbitances of the Monarch; and as they were willing after thoſe motions of the Proteſtants in France, and the Low-Countries, to excuſe as much as might be, ſo had they lived to have ſeen the Commotions and Rebellion of theſe daies, I make no doubt, but they would have ſpoken more cautelouſly; I am ſure, the Homily againſt Rebellion ſpeaks home, &amp; will not admit ſuch diſtinctions, that make way to the Reſiſting or Rebelling againſt evill Princes, which command againſt the Lawes and Religion, for of ſuch it ſpeakes.</p>
               <p>But let us try the force of this exception; he profeſſes with Mr. <hi>Burrowes</hi> againſt reſiſting of Authority, though abuſed; &amp; with Doctor <hi>Bilſon</hi> admits of Reſiſting the Princes will againſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:111670:42"/>the Lawes; this is faſt and looſe, for what is the Princes will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lawes, but abuſing of Authority? It may be hee would ſalve at, as M. <hi>Burrowes</hi> ſeemed to doe, by telling us, that he means by <hi>Authority abuſed,</hi> the Authority, imployed in <hi>Making ſinfull Lawes;</hi> for ſuch Authority though abuſed, this Author acknowledges to be the Ordinance of God and not to be reſiſted, and diſputes it againſt the <hi>Reverend Divines,</hi> pag. 64. 65. I agree with him; but further would have him ſhew why Authority abuſed in the <hi>Execution of Law,</hi> that is, in purſuing the Princes illegall will, ſhould not be alſo the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God and ſecured from reſiſtance? Indeed there is a great difference betweene Reſiſtance made againſt a Prince commanding according to Law, and that which is againſt a Prince commanding contrary to Law, but it doth not make the buſineſſe <hi>as cleare as the day:</hi> nay it doth not at all ſatisfie him that will enquire—</p>
               <p>Firſt, concerning that government under which the Apoſtle lived; might Subjects then reſiſt, If the Higher Powers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded contrary to Law, as they did often? we find that the Chriſtian Orthodox Religion was part of the Lawes in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi> and the ſuceeding times, and that Chriſtians did not reſiſt when <hi>Iulian</hi> perſecuted them for it, nor did the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtians reſiſt when the <hi>Arrian</hi> Emperours endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſubvert the faith. If he reply, they were Abſolute Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, and that their Edicts made a change of the Law, by which ſuch Religion was eſtabliſhed: why then doth he, ſpeaking of theſe abſolute Emperours, diſtinguiſh the will of the Prince from the Law, and think to ſatifie us by telling us, <hi>Religion then was no part of the Law;</hi> when with one breath they could make any thing Law, and by another reverſe it; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Authors acknowledgement of their abſoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Nor will this exception ſatiſie him, that ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire concerning this Government. 1. Whether the firſt Parliament in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Raigne might have reſiſted her, endeavouring to change the then eſtabliſhed Popiſh Religion? Had thoſe Popiſh Lords and Commons, which Q. <hi>Mary</hi> left,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:111670:42"/>beene pleaſed to hold to that Religion which was <hi>then part of our Nationall Law,</hi> they might have taken the Armes of the Kingdome, and have uſed them in the defence of it, by the Rule of this Authour, and the pretences of the Armes now ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up; I would very faine ſee, how they will make this as cleare as the day. 2. How can they be juſtified, that did at firſt take Armes, and doe ſtill continue them (as themſelves ſticke not to profeſſe) for the pulling downe of Epiſcopall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (that I may not ſay, of the Church Liturgy and publique ſervice too) which is, and alwaies hath been a part of the Law of this Nation? So little can this Authour ſatisfie us in this firſt exception, by ſaying, <hi>Religion was then no part of the Law,</hi> and therefore Chriſtians might not reſiſt, but now it is <hi>part of our Nationall Law,</hi> and therefore allowes the Reſiſtance of theſe daies.</p>
               <p>His other exception is; they were <hi>Abſolute</hi> Monarchs, and therefore not to be reſiſted; <hi>He who reads</hi> Tacitus (ſaith he) <hi>cannot but ſee the Senate brought to a condition of baſeſt ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and all Lawes and Lives depending on the will of the Prince;—They were become the ſworne vaſſals of an abſolute Lord, we the Subjects of a Liege or Legall Prince,</hi> pag. 59. <hi>Anſw:</hi> This is the Sword to cut the knot when it cannot be untied: but the edge is eaſily taken off from it, by enquiring whether thoſe firſt <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours had <hi>de jure</hi> ſuch abſolute power; and by conſidering, whether the Apoſtle had any reſpect to ſuch abſoluteneſſe of their power, in his reaſons againſt reſiſtance: and laſtly, whether limitation of Power in the Soveraigne, doth inferre power of reſiſtance in the Subject.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It cannot be cleared that thoſe firſt <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours were ſo abſolute <hi>de lure</hi> Legally, by ſuch conſent and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the People and Senate, as is required to the eſtating them in ſuch an abſolute condition, There ſeemes to be two Reaſons inducing this opinion of their abſoluteneſſe. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they tooke upon them as abſolute Lords. That cannot be denyed indeed, but it makes no <hi>right;</hi> nay, they crept into the power by degrees, which argues, they had it not by ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:111670:43"/>as is pretended, but got it by practice. 2. Becauſe of the <hi>Lex Regia,</hi> which this man doth not mention, but it is much ſpoken of to this purpoſe; for thereby it is conceived, that they were eſtated in ſuch Abſolute ſoveraignty: thus it runs, as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> gives it us, A Law, <hi>quâ populus ei</hi> (Principi) <hi>&amp; in eum omne ſuum imporium &amp; poteſtatem contulit.</hi> Tit. de Conſtitut-Principis. That there was ſuch a <hi>Lex Regia,</hi> cannot be denied, but the Queſtion is, when it was made, and what or how much is granted by i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? This has cauſed ſeverall opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Civilians ſome thinking the people onely gave away their power, making the Prince their perpetuall Tribune. Some that the Senate alſo parted with their power. Some, that neither of them <hi>parted wholly</hi> with their power, but <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated</hi> it ſo farre forth to the Prince in the adminiſtration of the Commonwealth, that they ſtill kept the <hi>Summum impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium</hi> in themſelves. This variety of opinion is unfit to make a certaine ground for Conſcience, or to give interpretation to the Apoſtle, as if then be forbad Reſiſtance, becauſe thoſe Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours were Abſolute.</p>
               <p>I conceive it to be cleare that the draught of that <hi>Lex Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia</hi> appeares no where before <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> time; that the people had before parted with their power, but the Senate not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; therefore <hi>Auguſtus</hi> (to whom <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Principate</hi> was granted for life, as <hi>Srabo</hi> ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h towards the end of his laſt booke) tooke upon him as <hi>Tribune</hi> of the people, and had it from ten yeeres to ten yeeres, as <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iate</hi> ſhewes in a little Tract, <hi>de Magiſtratib. Civilibus.</hi> That the ſucceeding Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours encroached by degrees upon the liberty and power of the Senate, making their way by ſeare and flattery; but had not that power, which by fits they aſſumed, from ſuch a Covenant and Conſent of the State, as is required, to make that <hi>Legem Regiam,</hi> as <hi>Connanus</hi> ſhewes out of <hi>Dion, Suetonius,</hi> and <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> Alſo that the Emperours though they were, for the more ready execution and miniſtration of the affaires of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, <hi>ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti Legibus,</hi> which was firſt granted to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus,</hi> yet did they <hi>perquamdiu magnam poteſtatis partem cum Senatu communicare</hi> (as <hi>Hotoman</hi> ſhewes, <hi>de Constitutionib.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:111670:43"/>Princip</hi> and cut of that power, which the Senate did ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be in them, they declared <hi>Nero</hi> an Enemy to the State. Adde to this, that though we read not of <hi>Plebiſcita</hi> after the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of theſe Emperours, yet we meet with <hi>Senatus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulta;</hi> and of the power of the Senare in paſſing their Decrees, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acitus</hi> ſaith, They did it ſometime <hi>inſcio &amp; abſente Principe,</hi> but never indeed <hi>invito,</hi> againſt his will; <hi>Suetonius</hi> alſo tells us that <hi>Caligula</hi> intended to aſſume the <hi>Diade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> which was a ſigne of that <hi>Regia poteſtas,</hi>and had been a profeſſion that he would raigne abſolutely: <hi>nec multum abfuit, quin ſpeciem prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatus, in Regni formam converteret,</hi> but he was diſſwaded from it by his friends, faith that Hiſtorian.</p>
               <p>During theſe Times the Apoſtles lived and wrote; for I go not ſo low as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpaſian,</hi> unto whom that <hi>Lex Regia</hi> ſeems to be ſolemnly granted by a formall conſent; and yet after that we find <hi>Pliny</hi> in his <hi>panegyricke</hi> tell the Emperour <hi>Trajan, ſedem Principis tenes, ne ſit Domixo locus:</hi> which ſhews, they had not reſigned themſelves up to the Emperour, as ſworne vaſſals to an <hi>Abſolute Lord,</hi> but had ſet a Prince over them for the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſpatch of the affairs of the Common-wealth, which often ſuffered (and in thoſe times more then ever) by the croſſings and Diviſions of the People and Senate. The forme of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was thereupon, I acknowledge, changed, and the Supremacy ſetled upon the Prince: yet may it, I conceive, from the former allegations be as well concluded, that the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> had their ſhare in the Supremacy with the Prince till <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> time, as that the two Houſes are Originally <hi>Mixed</hi> or joyned with the King in the ſupreame or Soveraigne power, which this Author undertakes to prove.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is to be conſidered that the Apoſtle in his reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reſiſtance, has no reſpect to the <hi>Abſolute</hi> or <hi>Limited</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of thoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, nor to any conſent or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of the people, by which they ſhould be made ſuch, (for then he might have told them, <hi>If they reſiſt they reſiſt their owne Ordinances)</hi> but draws his reaſons from the Ordinance of God, who ſets up rulers, and from the End and Benefits of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which are Reaſons, common to all Government, not to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:111670:44"/>be eluded by ſaying, Ours are <hi>limited</hi> Monarchs, and therefore may be reſiſted; for thoſe reaſons tell us, that reſiſtance againſt Him, that <hi>beares the Sword, (i.e.)</hi> againſt the Supreame power, (for that is ſignified by thoſe words, as <hi>Muſculus</hi> and <hi>Bucer</hi> ſhew out of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi>) is unlawfull in all governments.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As the Apoſtle had no reſpect to the Abſoluteneſſe of Power in thoſe Emperours, nor to the conſent of the people, by which they are ſaid to have ſuch power, ſo neither indeed doth the limited condition of a Monarch inferre he may bete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted for his Exorbitancies more then an Abſolute may for his, whether we conſider the Exorbitancies of an Abſolute M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, which may be deſtructive of the publique, or look to the compact of the people (by which he is left Abſolute) who did not thereby intend, he ſhould oppreſſe and deſtroy them, or command and judge them beyond Reaſon and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as this Authour acknowledgeth, pag. 11. But it was proved more largely above at the end of the 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> That limitedneſſe of power in the Soveraigne, doth not inferre a power of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in Subjects. So that abſoluteneſſe of power in thoſe firſt Roman Emperours is cauſeleſly alleaged by this Author as the reaſon, why they might not be reſiſted.</p>
               <p>This Authour concludes, <hi>All that can be juſtly inferred out of the Text, we grant, but can any living man hence collect, that therefore no reſistance may be made to Fellow-ſubjects, executing deſtructive illegall Acts of the Princes Will in a Legall Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy? Will he affirme that the Ordinance of God is reſiſted, and Damnation incurred thereby? Gods Ordinance is the power, and the perſon inveſted with the power, but here force is offered to neither, pag.</hi> 59. Anſw. The Queſtion is not put of making no reſiſtance to fellow Subjects, but of ſuch reſiſtance, as is made againſt them under the command of their Soveraigne, by a contrary Army of Subjects, a reſiſtance that undertakes a finall conteſtation with the Soveraign, to conſtrain him to be of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mind, as it was explained above, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. Now if he meanes, this Reſiſtance cannot be collected out of the Text, becauſe it is made in a <hi>Legall Monarchy,</hi> then is it the ſame exception, which even now he made from the <hi>Abſoluteneſſe</hi> of thoſe <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:111670:44"/>Monarchs; but if he means it cannnot be collected, becauſe it is no reſiſtance of Gods Ordinance, from whence the Apoſtle drawes his reaſon againſt reſiſting; then I ſay. 1. That when Subjects are drawn into Armes by the Soveraign, who has the power of the Sword, and doe act and move under his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to make oppoſition by a contrary army of Subjects is a reſiſting of the power, and a taking of the Sword without the Soveraigne, againſt the Ordinance of God, and a ſhedding of blood without warrant. 2. This exception ſeemes to be the ſame which was made by the <hi>pleaders</hi> above, where they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, <hi>If I be bound by the Ordinance of God, to ſuffer violence of a Tyrant, then is Tyranny the Ordinance of God.</hi> This was anſwered above, and is rejected by that Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy:</hi> yet doth he in effect argue to the ſame purpoſe, as we ſhall meet with him preſently, among the reaſons of the next Section.</p>
               <p>And thus much of the 13. to the <hi>Romaxs,</hi> in the aſſerting of which, it has been ſhewn againſt the <hi>Rev. Divines</hi> who plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for <hi>defenſive Armes,</hi> That forcible Reſiſtance againſt the illegall and Tyrannous commands of the then ruling Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours was here forbidden; and, That Chriſtians, had they had force ſufficient, might not reſiſt. Alſo againſt the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy,</hi> That his exceptions from the Lawes being then againſt Religion, and from the Abſoluteneſſe of thoſe Emperours, were not ſufficient to ſatisfie, or make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that therefore the Apoſtle forbad them to be reſiſted; for we find him to draw his reaſons againſt Reſiſtance, from that which is common to all Times and Governments, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, the end and benefit of Government. There are many more places of Scripture uſually brought, which may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry aptly and powerfully perſwade patience under evill Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but I have choſen to inſiſt onely upon ſuch as are more pregnant and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to beare argument againſt the power of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in Subjects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:111670:45"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>Reaſon againſt the Power of Reſiſtance in Subjects.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is cleare, that (as it has been often inſinuated above) if a Prince ſtands ſupreame and next under God above all the People, His Subjects may not proceed to ſuch Reſiſtance by armed Forces, as is ſuppoſed in the Queſtion, and at this day practiſed to the utmoſt; It is alſo moſt manifeſt that our King is ſo, being expreſly acknowledged the onely <hi>Supreame Head and Governour:</hi> and this might be ſufficient Reaſon without more adoe, to conclude againſt Reſiſtance. The adverſaries not well knowing how to divide Supremacie and irreſiſtibility, have vainly endeavoured to joyne the Houſes as ſharers in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream or Soveraigne power, for which we had ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Mixture</hi> above; and doe think to ſatisfie that <hi>Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> they leave in the King, by yeelding his perſon to be above the violence of Reſiſtance; but as for the Forces about his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the armes of the Kingdome may be imployed againſt them, as againſt misimployed agents; and from the taking of thoſe armes to make this reſiſtance, they conceive they are not debarred by His being <hi>Supreaeme Head and Governour,</hi> but are enabled to it by a ſuppoſed reſervation of the people, and by the neceſſity of the States preſervation, requiring ſuch a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of reſiſtance in Subjects, upon which grounds their Reaſons for reſiſtance doe mainly proceed. I ſhall therefore ſo frame this tryall of Reaſon, (to which we are now come) as it may beſt meet with the force of their Reaſons and Exceptions.</p>
               <p n="1">I. It was the wiſdome of God to put his people ſtill under Kings, without power of reſiſtance, as we found it in the two former Sections: and that wiſdome of God ſhould be to us in ſtead of the moſt forcible Reaſon, and ſilence all gainſaying pretences.</p>
               <p n="2">II. If this power of Reſiſtance in Subjects were ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the preſerving of Religion and Juſtice, as is pretended, certainly the word of God would have given direction for it; but as in the Old Teſtament, we no where finde the Prophets
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:111670:45"/>calling upon the Elders of the people ſin th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuppoſed d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y of reſiſtance, ſo in the New Teſtament we every where finde pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in ſuffering for well doing no mended to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Treat. of Monarchy,</hi> doth often admire the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Architects</hi> of this Government, that ſo provided for the ſafety of it, by placing ſuch power of Armes and reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the two Houſes: but we doe not find ſuch a proviſion within that wiſdome and care, which it pleaſed God to ſhew in the Government he put his people under; nor would we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed finde ſuch a power of forcible reſiſtance, provided in the conſtitution of this monarchy, when we examined it above.</p>
               <p n="3">III. From the Inſtitution and Ordinance of God, which gives the power, according to the Apoſtles argument, who drawes his reaſon againſt reſiſtance, not from any Compact of the people, but from the Ordinance of God, which cannot be E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uded by any reſervation of the people (the pretended ground of reſiſtance) but ſhewes the power given by it muſt be borne with, though abuſed, as then it was, when the Apoſtle gave his reaſons againſt reſiſtance.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. To be Supream and next to God over the people, or to have the power of the ſword, implyes a ſecurity from reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; It is the <hi>Ius Regis</hi> which <hi>Calvin</hi> and moſt Authors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge upon 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.11. and is expreſſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.31. <hi>A King, againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi> It is generally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, that Princes which be ſupreame are free from the Coactive power of the Law; It is apparent, that reſiſtance cannot be made by Subjects, but by taking the power of the Sword which belongs to him that is ſupream. Laſtly, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in reaſon, that if the two Houſes be enabled to reſiſt and conſtraine the Prince by force to his duty, then have they the power of the <hi>Lacedaemonian Ephori,</hi> which, as this Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy</hi> acknowledges, does overthrow the Soveraignity of the Monarch.</p>
               <p>The generall exception, which the Adverſaries make to theſe two laſt Reaſons, is, that they reſiſt not the Soveraigne power, but only miſimployed inſtruments and fellow Subjects executing his illegall commands. <hi>Anſw.</hi> As if the Soveraignes
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:111670:46"/>could by himſelfe execute his Commands without under Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of power; ſo that the reſiſting of them, acting by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which he has committed to them, is a reſiſting of him. And ſuch a reſiſtance, as is ſuppoſed in the Queſtion, neceſſarily proceeds to an oppoſing of Him perſonally, in giving of Him Battell, and forcing of Him from His Right and Power to new grants of Security.</p>
               <p>In particular, This Author of the <hi>Treat. of Monarchie,</hi> thus reaſons from the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God. <hi>To Reſiſt ſuch miſimployed Inſtruments, is no reſiſting of the Ordinance of God; for it neither reſiſts the Perſon of the Soveraigne, for we spake of reſiſting his Agents; nor His Power, for the meaſure of that in our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the Law, &amp; therefore He cannot confer Authoritie to any beyond the Law,</hi> page 52. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I would deſire this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to looke againe upon the two Aſſertions of the <hi>Reverend Divines,</hi> which he rejects, page 63. They run thus, <hi>Thoſe Govern urs, whether Supream or others, who under pretence of Authoritie from Gods Ordinance, diſturb the quiet &amp; peaceable life in Godlineſſe and honeſty, are far from being Gods Ordinance in ſo doing:</hi> alſo; <hi>This Tyranny not being Gods Ordinance, they which reſiſt it even with Armes, reſiſt not the Ordinance of GOD:</hi> and then to conſider, whether thoſe D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vines might not in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thoſe Aſſertions anſwer, as he has done here, <hi>that to reſiſt the miſimployed Agents of Tyrants commanding againſt Law, is not to reſiſt the Ordinance of God, for they cannot confer Authoritie to any againſt the Law;</hi> for my part I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, how he can retaine his own Aſſertion, and reject theirs.</p>
               <p>But to Anſwer him more particularly; He that beares the Sword <hi>(i. e)</hi> has the ſupreame power, gives power and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to under Miniſters for executing of Juſtice and to other Officers for the <hi>Militia;</hi> If thoſe therefore, though abuſing the Power, be reſiſted by them who are under them, it is a reſiſting of the Power; and if theſe, in time of Warre and inſurrection, being drawn together by the Soveraigne, and acting His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands under Him, be oppoſed by contrary force and armes of Subjects, it is a reſiſting of the power lawfully placed in ſuch perſons, though illegally uſed and imployed; it is a taking and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:111670:46"/>uſing of the ſword to the ſhedding of blood with u Warrant.</p>
               <p>The defence (which this Author makes, <hi>pag.</hi> 62) of their taking the ſword without the Soveraign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and againſt his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, is grounded upon that former groundleſſe ſuppoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll of their being joyned with the King in the Soveraign power it ſelfe; of which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undantly in the 4th and 5th Sections above.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Becauſe Obedience, Honour, and Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue to a Ponce are enjoyned, and th Contrary forbidd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n without any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtincti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Good or Bad P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ince; S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhewes, that <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill muſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t he ſpoken of the worſt Rulers,</hi> Act. 23. <hi>What is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeſars,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saviour bids <hi>give unto Caeſar,</hi> when he was as bad as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght be; and for this Cauſe <hi>pay you Tribute, and Honour,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when the higher powers were extreme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y evnd. — This cannot conſiſt with taking Armes againſt a Prince: for they that doe ſo, muſt ſpeake evill of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, make Him appeare O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to His people, and will not, cannot let <hi>Caeſar</hi> have what is His, His Revenues, Cuſtomes, Tribute, Armes, but w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll tell Him, they are not His, but the King fomes, to uſe as the State ſhall thinke ſit, when he abuſeth them, And as the Scripture doth not, ſo not her doth our Law make any d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtinction of good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d bad Princes in this poynt; It enjoynes Honour, Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Allegiance, Cuſtomes, without any ſuch diſtinction, and determin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Inſurrection, and Levying of Warre to be Treaſon, not onely againſt a good King, but indefinitely againſt any.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. It is good reaſon, that He which has the Supreame Truſt next to God, ſhould have the greateſt ſecurity, but if the people have power of Armes upon ſuch or ſuch Caſes, the ſtrongeſt and laſt ſecurity is on their ſide. In other kinds of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, we ſee the ſecurity is ſtill upon the Governing Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; Parents are ſecured from the force and violence of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and as unto the firſt Rule of Fathers, the Government of Kings did ſucceed, ſo unto Kings is Honour commanded under the Name of Fathers, that we might conceive the unnaturalnes of Warre and forcible Reſiſtance againſt them. The Husband alſo, who is the head of the Wife, had the advantage on his part in the poynt of Divorce; He might give the Bill to her upon Jealouſies and diſpleaſure, ſhe could not to H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m; This Liberty
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:111670:47"/>was permitted to good and bad Huſbands equally, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the occaſion, that evill Huſbands might take thereby to be unjuſt and cruell; as it is uſually objected againſt this <hi>Ius Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> or advantage of ſecurity on the Kings part.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. From the end and benefits of the Governing power, for the enjoying of which it is good reaſon wee ſhould beare with the Exorbitancies of the power. The <hi>Divines,</hi> that plead for <hi>Defenſive Armes,</hi> reply. <hi>This is as good a Reaſon, as if wee ſhould ſay, God hath ordained Miniſters to Preach, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter his Sacraments for the good of the people, that they may be ſaved, therefore be their Miniſters never ſo careleſſe, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the Word and Sacraments, the people may not ſeeke their Soules ſafety from ſome other,</hi> pag. 56. <hi>Anſw.</hi> There's a great deale of difference betweene theſe two Reaſonings, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Remedy which may be had againſt unfaithfull, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Miniſters; for firſt, as theſe <hi>Divines</hi> ſuppoſe <hi>forcible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,</hi> to be the remedy againſt Exorbitant Princes, when the Good for which Government was ordained, cannot be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by them, ſo ſhould they in this their Reaſoning, have conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for a <hi>violent ſuppreſſion</hi> of ſuch Miniſters, as an anſwerable Remedy againſt that miſchieſe. Indeed this Age hath ſeen the proceedings againſt both much alike, Miniſters pull'd out of their Pulpits by the people, caſt out of their Houſes, ſpoyled of the benefit of their Livings, and Teachers drawne from the Loweſt of the people, thruſt into their places without any Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall proceſſe; and it is openly profeſſed, that theſe Armes are ſtill held up to pull Biſhops downe. Theſe men forget what our Saviour ſaid to the people, of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees, They ſit in Moſes Chaire;</hi> what then? pull them downe? No: <hi>heare them, and doe what they teach you</hi> out of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As againſt their Paſtors, ſo have they proceeded againſt their Prince, forgetting thoſe many precepts and examples, which the Scripture gives us, of Obedience and ſubjection yeelded even to Tyrannous Kings; now if they will reaſon thus, God has ordained Rulers for good, therefore we may uſe force to conſtraine them to their duty, that we may receive that good by them: So, God has ordained Miniſters for good, therefore
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:111670:47"/>we may violently ſuppreſſe them, and caſt them out, if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive that good by them; then I confeſſe, one Reaſon is as good as another, but both bad enough.</p>
               <p>Secondly therefore, we muſt conſider there is a Remedy to be ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>againſt unfaithfull ſcandalous Miniſters, by complaining to their Superiours, who ſet them over the people, and can diſpl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce them; but the Remedy againſt Princes that Rule not well, is by complaint to God, that ſet them up, and can turne their Hearts; now if they will reaſon thus, Paſtours are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for good, therefore if they doe not miniſter unto that, we may uſe the remedy againſt them, which God and good Lawes have allowed; ſo Rulers are ordained for good, and if they doe not attend upon it, ſuch r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>medy may be uſed as God and good Lawes doe approve of; then I confeſſe, both Reaſonings are good; but neither doth conclude for forcible Reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Now if we will conſider the force of this ſeventh Reaſon againſt Reſiſtance, which is drawne from the end and benefits of Government, we ſhall find it, however the <hi>Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> make light of it, to be the ſame that the Apoſtle makes, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Render therefore, &amp;c.</hi> wherefore? becauſe they are the Miniſters of God for good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But who were they, to whom Tribute, and Honour, and Cuſtome, was then to be <hi>rendered as due?</hi> Thoſe Rulers that were then farre from thoſe duties; yet, becauſe Rulers, appointed for that end, <hi>Render therefore,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place tells us, <hi>Loquitur denativo Magiſtratus officio, à quo tame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe non rarò degenerant, qui principatum tenent, nihilominus deferenda eſt us obedientia, quae principibus debetur.</hi> For whether we conſider Government in generall, it does (as <hi>Bucer</hi> upon the place ſpeakes) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for the moſt part ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tame its end in ſome good meaſure: or any Government in particular, there is a benefic of protection from it beyond the particular injuries ſuffered by it; to this purpoſe <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place, <hi>Quanquam ne ſic quidem unquam abutuntur ſuâ po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ne Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cipes bonos vexando, ut non in ſua Tyrannide speciem al quam just<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dominationis retineant; Nulla ergo Tyrannis eſſe pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt, quae non aliqua ex parte ſubſidio ſit ad tuendam hominum ſocietate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And P. <hi>Martyr</hi> ſhewes it by the reſcue, defence,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:111670:48"/>and protection, which <hi>S, Paul</hi> found through the benefit of the power, and by the appeal he made to <hi>Nero</hi> the worſt of Tyrants; all which appeares by ſeverall paſſages in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">VIII. This Power of Reſiſtance in Subjects, would be a Remedy againſt the Exorbitancies of Princes, worſe then the chſeaſe, and more ſubver ſive of a ſtate, then if they were left without it. This the Wiſedom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he God of Order did forefee, who put his people und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r King, wit ont ſuch p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wer of Reſiſtance, as was above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This both Reaſon and experience doth ſhew, that it is a remedy not to be managed without bringing greater danger; the being of ſuch power in Subjects would be a continua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Seminary of jealouſies twixt Prince and People, for the uſing of it, they would not want pretences cauſeleſly made, and in the uſing of it could not ſhew m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deration: they would not be content with the rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of their Liberties, but ſeeke to leſſen the Princes power for their farther ſecutity; they would not reſt upon the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces promiſe for it, &amp; then how would he upon theirs for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience? they would feare his returne to exorbitancy, and be their violence would proceed to a depoſing of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>; and what could be the iſſue but confuſion through the continuance of the Miſchiefes of Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te? The confideration of theſe times and of the perſons that have had the managing of this forcible Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to be a Remedy not to be uſed.</p>
               <p>The author of the <hi>Trea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſe of Monarchy,</hi> replies. <hi>Jt is ſtronge that the Reſiſtance of deſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uctive diſorder ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uld tend to the overthrow of Order, or be a remedy worſe then the diſeaſe; It may for a time disturbe, as Phyſick doth the Naturall body, while it is in working, if the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccant humours make strong oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, but as this tends to health, ſo dath Reſiſtance of diſorder to Order</hi> pag. 6. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not ſo ſtrange, for there is Order under the greateſt Tyranny, as was ſhewen in the former Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and in the exorbitances of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inces, which in themſelves tend to the ſubverſion of the eſtabliſhed Order, there is more Order, Law, and Juſtice, then in the uſe and effects of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy by reſiſtance. <hi>Such lewd Remedies</hi> (as it is in the firſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:111670:48"/>part of the Homily againſt Rebellion) <hi>are farre worſe then any other Maladies and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſorders, that can be in the body of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to his ſimili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude. In the applying of Phyſick, we look to the Medicine or remedy it ſelfe, and do not uſe the Sword to thoſe parts of the body, which will onely admit of Fomenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Lenitives, and patience for the cure of them: nor doe we commit the applying of the phyſick to every hand and judgement, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and and judgement, by which this ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick of forcible R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tance is that of the people, for this Author tels us, in ſuch a caſe <hi>the Appeale muſt be to the Community, and they muſt aid and aſſiſt, as they are in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence conviced.</hi> But how ſhall they be perſwaded to uſe a mean, who wil be ſtill applying and keeping this Phyſick working, when perchance the Houſes, that cal'd them to the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, would have it cea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>? doe we not ſee what Humours this phyſick hath ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irred in the body Politick? where there is any poſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, it is better to let Nature worke it cut, though we give it a longer time to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe it in, then to thinke to helpe it by a poyſonous purge.</p>
               <p>But if any ſhall thinke, the Art and wiſedome of the Houſes can correct the malignity of the Remedy, or the raſhneſſe of the people, that are uſed in the application of it, I appeale from his judgement to theſe Times; when could bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſucceſſe of this Remedy be expected? by whom could it better be applyed and managed then by the Members of this late Parliament, ſo much extolled for their Religion, Prudence, and Equity? yet let the iſſue ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k, what little good there is to be hoped for by the uſe of ſuch miſchic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous remedies. The fourth part of the Homily, above cited, ſpeaks thus. <hi>Peaceable King</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lomon <hi>was judged of God more meet to build his Temple (whereby the Ordering of Religion is meant) then His Father</hi> David, <hi>who had ſhed much blood in his warrs, though against the Lords Enemies: what Religion is it then, that ſuch men, by ſuch meanes would reſtore? Even as good a Religion as they are good Subiects, or as Rebellionis a good mean of redreſſe and reformation, being it ſelfe the greareſt deformation
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:111670:49"/>that poſſible may be. But as the Truth of the Goſpell being quietly and ſoberly taught, though it coſt them their lives that doe teach it, is able to maintaine the true Religion, ſo hath a franticke Religion need of ſuch furious mainteinance as is Rebellion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">IX.Laſtly, therefore wee are taught to referre the Remedy to God, who has told us, that the hearts of Kings are in his hand, and he turnes them whitherſoever he will, <hi>Pro.</hi> 21.1. to make us apply unto him for the turning of them. Hee ſhewes that he is the judge of the King, by that Conditionate covenant he makes with him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> c. 6. v. 16. Where the promiſes made to <hi>David</hi> for the continuance of his Kingdome, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated with this condition, Yet ſo that thy Children walk in my Law, So alſo 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 7.17. But the Covenant 'twixt King and People, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. is not Conditionate to render him obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious to their judgement and force. To this purpoſe <hi>Nation,</hi> in his firſt <hi>Orat.</hi> againſt <hi>Iulian,</hi> ſhewing how that wicked Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was repreſſed through the Mercy of God, doth blame thoſe, who being too much intent upon the preſent, cannot depend upon providence &amp; expect the execution of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell of God in his puniſhing of wicked Princes: <hi>P. Martyr</hi> in his Comment on the 13 to the <hi>Rom.</hi> ſhewing out of <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. that God tranſlates and diſpoſeth of Kingdoms, obſerveth this way of providence, that evill Princes are raiſed for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the wickedneſſe of a People, <hi>ſed poſtquam ſic caſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gatt homines ad Deum redierint, ille mitiores Principes, &amp; juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores provides,</hi> and accordingly, ſaith hee, wee find in Hiſtory of Kings, that God did, <hi>Tyrannis ſemper miſcere bonos aliquos &amp; juſtos Principes, Calvin</hi> likewiſe upon the 13 to the <hi>Romanes</hi> tels us piouſly and judiciouſly, That an evill Prince is the ſcourge of God upon the Peoples ſin, and therefore as we muſt acknowledge it is through our fault, that the great bleſſing of Magiſtracy is turned to our puniſhment, ſo muſt we neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe reverence the Ordinance of Power, which wee ſhall eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe, <hi>ſi nobis ipſis quiequid mali in ipſa erit, impatemus,</hi> if we impute the abuſe of the power, or the evil that we ſuffer by it, to our ſelves. I will conclude with the like advice, given us in the firſt part of the Homily againſt Rebellion, <hi>The heart of the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:111670:49"/>Prince is in the hand of God, wherefore let us turne from our ſinnes to the Lord, and he will turne the heart of the Prince to our Wealth: Elſe for Subjects, when they have deſerved through their ſins to have an evill Prince, then to Rebell againſt Him, were a double evill, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking God to plague them more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reaſons which the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe of Monarchy</hi> has brought for the power of Reſiſtance i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Subjects are ſuch as follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Becauſe to reſiſt misimployed inſtruments acting or aſſiſting to the performance of the deſtructive commands of the Prince, is no reſiſting of the Ordinance of power, becauſe power cannot be conferred to any beyond the Law. So he pag. 52. How far this concernes the queſtion, was ſhewen above un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my third and fourth Reaſons, where it was propounded and anſwered.</p>
               <p>His ſecond Reaſon. <hi>Becauſe without ſuch power of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the hands of Subjects all Limitation of Government is vaine; all formes reſolve into Abſolute and Arbitrary.</hi> pag. 53. Anſw. Your Argument is inconſequent by your owne deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Abſolute and Limited Monarchy, which you drew from the conſideration not of force or reſiſtance, but of Law to ſet bounds to the Monarchs Will as was obſerved above, <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. So that the reſtraint of a limited Monarch is Legall and Morall, not forcible and military. Nor is there, by the Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Monarchs power, a power of Armes acquired to the people, but onely a Morall ſecurity ſought after by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint or bands of Lawes and Oath caſt upon the Monarch: which makes not a <hi>vaine</hi> limitation of Government, but binds the conſcience of the Monarch, and by his Conſcience his hands are bound, more powerfully, then by a contrary power or force in the people, ſee above towards the end of the fifth Section, that Limitation of the Monarchs power inferres not a power of Reſiſtance in Subjects.</p>
               <p>He addes to the ſame Reaſon, <hi>If a Prince be taught, that hee may take, what he pleaſeath, from His Subjects without being reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, caſes and reaſons will ſoone be brought to perſwade him, &amp;c.</hi> pag. 53. <hi>Anſw.</hi> He is not taught he may Lawfully doe ſo: but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:111670:50"/>if Subjects be taught, that they may lawfully take Armes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch or ſuch caſes, and take from their fellow Subjects, what they pleaſe, to maintaine thoſe Armes, pretences and caſes will not be wanting, as at this day. In a word, ſome muſt bee finally truſted when all is done, and who may better challenge it then the Supreame Governour that ſtands next to God above the People, as was ſaid above in the fourth Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on: and it were fit we ſhould for the redreſſe of Evills in Government, truſt God and depend upon his providence more, then theſe men would have us.</p>
               <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s third Reaſon. <hi>Eccauſe ſuch power is due to a publicke State for its preſervation, as is due to a particular perſon,</hi> pag. 55. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Propoſition is not univerſally true, but is thus farre granted, ſuch power is due to a State for its preſervation, as is allowed by the juſt Lawes thereof; for as the body Naturall defends it ſelfe from outward force by its Law, ſo the body Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique by its Law. Now though a particular perſon by the Law of nature has power of ſelfe preſerva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion againſt the force of another private perſon, yet is this power yeelded up in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Civill power (by the benefit of which particular perſons have protection from the injuries of all other) and not to be uſed againſt perſons indued with ſuch power, againſt ſuch perſons illegally and ſuddainly aſſuiting a man, where t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e danger is imminent and unavoydable by flight, there was no more allowed in my firſt <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> then a meere perſonall d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, by warding of blowes without returning any: yet doth this Author complaine. <hi>The Doctor is ſo heavie a friend to the State, that he thinkes it not ſit to allow it that Liberty, he gives every private man,</hi> pag. 55. As the Liberty which this Author allowes a State for its preſervation, tends rather to its ſuoverſion, ſo are there many differences between it, and the Liberty or power allowed to private men.</p>
               <p>For firſt, That power of preſervation which is allowed to a private man, againſt a private man, is againſt an our ward force, but this which is challenged for the State is by a Civill conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body againſt the Head, or of other part of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> body againſt the Head, and another part of the body. 2. That de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:111670:50"/>which was allowed againſt Miniſters of Power in their unavoydable aſſaults, was without all off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nee, but this defence by Armies, which is challenged, for the State cannot be ſo. 3. That power of defence is ſuch as nature hath endued every particular man with, and the law of the Society hath not forbidden ſo farre forth, as was ſaid, to be uſed: but this is ſuch a power as no Law enables Subjects to, a taking and uſing of the Sword without warrant, as hath bin often ſhewn. 4. Such neere perſonall defence is not deſtructive of Order, but this by the civill contention of the Head and body, is, as at this day.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pleaders for Defenſive Armes,</hi> make a long reply to that which in my firſt <hi>Trea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> was ſpoken, concerning this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall defence, the ſubſtance of it is. Firſt, <hi>though the body na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall can doe nothing againſt, or without the guidance of the Head, yet the Body Politique can, being a company of Reaſonable men, whoſe actions may be divided from their Head.</hi> Pag. 14.15. <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are Reaſonable men, but as they make up the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy politique, the Law is their Reaſon, and they cannot move or act further then it directs them, nor can they divide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Head, to which the Law joynes them, nor of themſelves, performe the ſupreame Acts of Power belonging to the Head. 2. <hi>It is granted, the body Politique may defend it ſelfe againſt an outward force, then ſuppoſe the King imploy</hi> Danes <hi>or</hi> Iriſh, <hi>againſt the Kingdome, may we reſiſt,</hi> Pag. 15. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine nothing of their ſuppoſition, which I hope will never come to paſſe; but they ſhould have conſidered, when the <hi>Doctor</hi> ſaid, the Body politicke defends it ſelfe againſt an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force, li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e as the body naturall doth, hee did not take the body politick divided from the Head, as it is in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Contention. 3. <hi>The Doctor ſuppoſeth the Prince bent to ſubvert Religion, Liberties, Lowes, what greater deſtruction of Order can be feared by ſuch antention or reſistance.</hi> Pag. 15.16. <hi>Anſw.</hi> What was meant by that ſuppoſition, hath bin often explained, <hi>the Prince bent, or ſeduced to ſubvert, (i. e.)</hi> doing many acts arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, which of themſelves tend to ſubverſion, but indeed the Frame of Government &amp; Laws cannot be ſubverted without the conſent of the two Houſes. It may happen, that actuall
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:111670:51"/>invaſions may be made upon them; and it is plain, that ſuch had better be borne with, and other lawfull and reaſonable remedies ſought, then to endeavour a forcible redreſſe by a Civill Contention, for under ſuch actuall invaſions, of the Subjects Rights, nay under the greateſt Tyranny, there is more Order, Law, and Juſtice, then under ſuch civill diſcords and Warres, as was fully evinced above, by the 7. and 8. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>The fourth Reaſon of the Author of the <hi>Treat.</hi> of <hi>Monarchy</hi> is grounded upon that falſe ſuppoſall of the two Houſes being joyned with the King, in the very Soveraigne Power, <hi>pag.</hi> 55. which was at large examined above. His laſt reaſon is from the Power of inferiour Courts, <hi>where the Judge it to proceed to the Cenſure, and puniſhment of the Malefactor, notwithſtanding the Kings Warrant to the contrary, much rather may the aſſaults of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tvate men be reſiſted by the Parliament,</hi> pag. 56. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gument from the proceſſe of inferiour Courts to ſentence and puniſhment, or from the Parliaments power to reſiſt and commit ſuch private men aſſaulting them, is altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequent to prove their power to raiſe Armies, and by them to oppoſe the Forces of their Soveraigne, which is the reſiſtance ſuppoſed in the Queſtion, and condemned as unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable by al that hath hitherto bin ſpoken from the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of this Governement, from Scripture, and from Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>And all this that hath bin ſpoken hitherto, belongs to the Reſolution of the firſt Queſtion, <hi>That it is not lawfull for Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, upon the ſuppoſed Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of the Princes ſubv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſive Exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to take Armes and reſiſt as at this day,</hi> The other ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: <hi>that the Caſe ſuppoſed is not now,</hi> or, <hi>That they have no, thoſe Cauſes for their Armes, which they pretend.</hi> But of this there hath bin ſo much ſaid in ſo many Declarations, and Bookes, written to informe the world aright, that I need not be any longer troubleſome, onely I would deſire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, upon their pretending the defence of the eſtabliſhed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Lawes by theſe Armes, to conſider;</p>
               <p>Firſt, that they cannot ſay, another Religion is commanded or enforced upon them, only they will ſay they fear a change,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:111670:51"/>I would to God, that all offences, which the liberty of theſe unſetled times has produced, were taken out of the way: but was there ever any before theſe Times ſo deſperare, as to maintaine, Subjects might fight againſt their Soveraigne, for a Religion they freely enjoy, only becauſe they fear a prevailing of the Contrary? And if the Reader doe conſider, that this Army (which pretends the defence of the Eſtabliſhed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) beſides ſome Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es of Forreiners and Papiſts, and ſome Bands of unwilling Preſt-men, has its chiefe ſtrength from the prevalency of ſuch Sects, as are condemned by Lawes of this Land, he may well cry out in the words of the <hi>Homily</hi> above cited, <hi>What Religion is it that ſuch men would by ſuch meanes maintaine? — A franticke Religion needes ſuch furious Maintenances, as is Rebellion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. They cannot but ſay, that the continuance of the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Religion, and of the Governement of Church and State, together with a juſt Reformation of all abuſes has bin offered, promiſed, proteſted for by their Soveraigne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. but this will not content them, unleſſe the eſtabliſhed Liturgy may be aboliſhed, the Governement of the Church by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, which has alwayes bin, may be no more, and the Power which by Law is his Majeſties, put into their hands. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe are not granted, their Armes are continued, and for the mainteining of them, the Liberty and Property of their fellow Subjects is invaded. So that if the Queſtion bee put, who are thoſe miſimployed fellovv Subjects, that theſe men pretend to fight againſt? It is plaine, they are ſuch, as defend their Soveraignes Povver and Rights, the Eſtabliſhed Religion and Governement of this Church and State, their ovvne property and Liberty: in a vvord, ſuch, as vvill not change their Soveraigne, or the Eſtabliſhed Frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The God of povver and Wiſedome caſt out all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and defeat all deſignes, that are againſt the reſtoring of our peace, and the continuance of the true Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
